<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31670760</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evz238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evz238</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolutionary Analysis of Bile Acid-Conjugating Enzymes Reveals a Complex Duplication and Reciprocal Loss History</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kirilenko</surname><given-names>Bogdan M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hagey</surname><given-names>Lee R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>Charles N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz238-aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evz238-cor1"/><!--<email>hiller@mpi-cbg.de</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Sabyasachi</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evz238-aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics</institution>, Dresden, Germany</aff><aff id="evz238-aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Max Planck Institute for the Physics of Complex Systems</institution>, Dresden, Germany</aff><aff id="evz238-aff3"><label>3</label>
<institution>Center for Systems Biology</institution>, Dresden, Germany</aff><aff id="evz238-aff4"><label>4</label>
<institution>Department of Medicine, University of California</institution> at San Diego, USA</aff><aff id="evz238-aff5"><label>5</label>
<institution>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology</institution>, Targeted Metabolomics and Proteomics Laboratory, University of Alabama, Birmingham, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="evz238-cor1">Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>hiller@mpi-cbg.de</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-10-31"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3256</fpage><lpage>3268</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="evz238.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>To fulfill their physiological functions, bile acids are conjugated with amino acids. In humans, conjugation is catalyzed by bile acid coenzyme A: amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase (BAAT), an enzyme with a highly conserved catalytic triad in its active site. Interestingly, the conjugated amino acids are highly variable among mammals, with some species conjugating bile acids with both glycine and taurine, whereas others conjugate only taurine. The genetic origin of these bile acid conjugation differences is unknown. Here, we tested whether mutations in BAAT&#x02019;s catalytic triad could explain bile acid conjugation differences. Our comparative analysis of 118 mammals first revealed that the ancestor of placental mammals and marsupials possessed two genes, <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>, that arose by a tandem duplication. This duplication was followed by numerous gene losses, including <italic>BAATP1</italic> in humans. Losses of either <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> largely happened in a reciprocal fashion, suggesting that a single conjugating enzyme is generally sufficient for mammals. In intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes, we observed multiple changes in the catalytic triad between Cys and Ser residues. Surprisingly, although mutagenesis experiments with the human enzyme have shown that replacing Cys for Ser greatly diminishes the glycine-conjugating ability, across mammals we found that this residue provides little power in predicting the experimentally measured amino acids that are conjugated with bile acids. This suggests that the mechanism of BAAT&#x02019;s enzymatic function is incompletely understood, despite relying on a classic catalytic triad. More generally, our evolutionary analysis indicates that results of mutagenesis experiments may not easily be extrapolatable to other species.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>gene duplication</kwd><kwd>reciprocal gene loss</kwd><kwd>bile acid conjugation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Bile has been long known to be important in health and disease (<xref rid="evz238-B23" ref-type="bibr">Heaton and Morris 1971</xref>). It is a watery yellow fluid produced by the liver and excreted into ducts that transport it to the upper small intestine. The dominant components of bile are a family of cholesterol-derived compounds&#x02014;bile alcohols and bile acids. With a few exceptions, almost all mammals produce bile acids via a pathway that involves multiple enzymes (<xref rid="evz238-B45" ref-type="bibr">Russell 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Bile acids have been shown to have a multiplicity of roles (<xref rid="evz238-B28" ref-type="bibr">Hofmann and Hagey 2014</xref>). Their secretion from the liver into the bile ducts pulls in water that makes up the bile flow. As a physiological molecule, bile acids are required for the absorption of digested lipids and fat-soluble vitamins in the intestine, which is evident from human patients exhibiting bile acid synthesis defects (<xref rid="evz238-B26" ref-type="bibr">Heubi et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). Furthermore, in the past two decades, there has been a growing appreciation of the role of bile acids as signaling and communication molecules. In particular, bile acids influence the intestinal environment and affect the proportions of the different species of bacteria that make up the gut microbiome of the host (<xref rid="evz238-B41" ref-type="bibr">Nie et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). In turn, the intestinal microbiome alters the structure of bile acids, and when these structures are reabsorbed from the intestine and returned to the bloodstream, they influence host cholesterol, triglyceride, and glucose levels (<xref rid="evz238-B48" ref-type="bibr">Schaap et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), host energy homeostasis (<xref rid="evz238-B2" ref-type="bibr">Broeders et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B11" ref-type="bibr">DiMarzio et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>), and host immunity (<xref rid="evz238-B18" ref-type="bibr">Fiorucci et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). </p><p>Prior to their secretion into bile, bile acids are conjugated with the amino acids taurine or glycine (<xref rid="evz238-B29" ref-type="bibr">Hofmann et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Conjugation substantially reduces the passive reabsorption of the molecule through biological membranes. This allows bile acids in the intestine to form micelles, which are necessary for the absorption of lipids (<xref rid="evz238-B14" ref-type="bibr">Ekwall 1951</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B27" ref-type="bibr">Hofmann 1963</xref>). Subsequently, a wide variety of intestinal microbes possess the ability to deconjugate bile acids (<xref rid="evz238-B31" ref-type="bibr">Jones et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>), and these deconjugated forms are then returned to the liver for reconjugation.</p><p>Bile acid conjugation is catalyzed by the enzyme bile acid coenzyme A: amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase (BAAT), which is encoded by the <italic>BAAT</italic> gene. This enzyme has two locations in hepatocytes&#x02014;peroxisomes (25&#x02013;30%) where it conjugates newly synthesized bile acids, and the cytosol (70&#x02013;75%) where it reconjugates bile acids returning from the intestine (<xref rid="evz238-B43" ref-type="bibr">Pellicoro et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B58" ref-type="bibr">Styles et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). Bile acid conjugation is a three-step process. To form an amino acid conjugate, initially an acid&#x02013;anhydride bond is formed between the carboxylic acid of the bile acid and adenosine-5&#x02032;-monophosphate (<xref rid="evz238-B30" ref-type="bibr">Ikegawa et&#x000a0;al. 1999</xref>). The <italic>O</italic>-adenylate is then exchanged for coenzyme A to form a bile acid-CoA ester. Next, BAAT binds to the bile acid-CoA unit and breaks the CoA linkage, forming a covalent bond between the bile acid and a cysteine in the active site (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). In humans, BAAT is the only enzyme capable of bile acid conjugation, because loss-of-function mutations result in familial hypercholanemia, a disease characterized by the absence of bile acid conjugation, growth failure, and vitamin deficiency (<xref rid="evz238-B6" ref-type="bibr">Carlton et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B50" ref-type="bibr">Setchell et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>Critical for the enzymatic function of human BAAT are three amino acids&#x02014;<sup>235</sup>Cys, <sup>328</sup>Asp, and <sup>362</sup>His (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). These three amino acids constitute a catalytic triad and have a classic charge-relay system as seen in cysteine- and serine-proteases. Generally, mutations of these amino acids in these enzyme classes abolish activity (<xref rid="evz238-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pazirandeh et&#x000a0;al. 1991</xref>). However, mutagenesis experiments with human BAAT have shown that a change from <sup>235</sup>Cys to <sup>235</sup>Ser alters BAAT selectivity for glycine and taurine (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). Wild-type human BAAT can utilize either taurine or glycine (<xref rid="evz238-B16" ref-type="bibr">Falany et&#x000a0;al. 1994</xref>), but the <sup>235</sup>Ser mutant, while retaining its BAAT activity with taurine, has a substantially reduced BAAT activity with glycine as the substrate. Moreover, this mutant also exhibits a marked hydrolase activity against bile acid-CoA substrate (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>).</p><p>Consistent with human BAAT mediating conjugation with either glycine or taurine in vitro (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>), human bile contains both taurine and glycine conjugates. However, among mammals, the preferred amino acids that are conjugated to bile acids are highly variable (<xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Like in humans, several primates (such as great apes, rhesus, and sifaka), several glires (rats, naked mole rat, beaver, and rabbit), and several <italic>Laurasiatheria</italic> (cow, zebra, and pig) utilize either taurine or glycine, although the ratio of glycine to taurine conjugation can vary considerably. In contrast, other primates (such as marmosets and lemurs), other rodents (mouse, chinchilla, and squirrel), other <italic>Laurasiatheria</italic> (cetaceans, goat, carnivora, and bats), and most <italic>Afrotheria</italic> exclusively conjugate bile acids with taurine but not glycine (<xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Although the variability in the preferred conjugated amino acids has been well characterized, the genetic origin of this variation is not known.</p><p>To address the question of what drives the molecular basis of bile acid conjugation differences among mammals, we reasoned that the results of mutagenesis experiments with human BAAT can be extrapolated to other mammals, because the catalytic triad that is required for enzymatic function is well conserved (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). Specifically, we hypothesized that <sup>235</sup>Cys would be predictive for conjugation with either glycine or taurine, whereas <sup>235</sup>Ser would be predictive for taurine-only conjugation. By inspecting the active site of BAAT across 118 mammals, we surprisingly found that the <italic>BAAT</italic> gene is inactivated (lost) in many mammals that exhibit bile acid conjugation. A subsequent genomic analysis revealed that <italic>BAAT</italic> exhibits a complex duplication and reciprocal loss history in mammals, and that almost all species preserve at least one intact <italic>BAAT</italic>-like gene. Finally, comparing the active-site residues of all intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAAT</italic>-like genes shows that <sup>328</sup>Asp and <sup>362</sup>His are perfectly conserved and that the residue corresponding to position 235 provides little predictive power for observed bile acid conjugation patterns. This suggests that the mechanistic understanding of the enzymatic function of human BAAT cannot easily be extrapolated to other mammals and indicates that additional BAAT amino acid residues affect its selectivity for the amino acid conjugation of bile acids.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Detecting and Validating the Loss of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> in Mammals</title><p>Because <italic>BAAT</italic> exhibits a frameshifting deletion overlapping the active-site residue in <italic>Bovidae</italic>, we analyzed whether the coding sequence of <italic>BAAT</italic> has gene-inactivating mutations across 118 mammals (all species and genome assemblies are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). To this end, we used a previously developed approach that uses genome alignments to detect different types of gene-inactivating mutations, namely premature stop-codon mutations, frameshifting insertions and deletions, splice site disrupting mutations, and large exonic deletions (<xref rid="evz238-B53" ref-type="bibr">Sharma, Hecker, et al. 2018</xref>). This approach employs a series of filter steps to exclude false inactivation mutations. Briefly, exons that appear deleted or do not align are ignored if the corresponding locus overlaps an assembly gap in the other assembly. Frameshifts that compensate each other and return to the ancestral reading frame are ignored as well. Coding exon-structure aware realigner (CESAR) realignments are used to remove false inactivating mutations caused by alignment ambiguities and to remove false splice site mutations in case of evolutionary splice-site shifts (<xref rid="evz238-B52" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>, <xref rid="evz238-B56" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The same approach was used to analyze inactivating mutations in <italic>BAATP1</italic> orthologs with the following difference. As human <italic>BAATP1</italic> is not an intact gene, we cannot use the human gene structure as a reference. Therefore, we used the Ensembl-annotated cow <italic>BAATP1</italic> (ENSBTAT00000079956.1), which encodes an intact gene, as the reference and used CESAR to realign the three coding exons of cow <italic>BAATP1</italic> to the orthologous loci that aligned to the human <italic>BAATP1</italic> locus. The CESAR alignments were then searched for inactivating mutations. Analysis of relaxed selection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) was performed using RELAX (<xref rid="evz238-B63" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and the robust codon alignments of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes (below).</p><p>As putative gene-inactivating mutations can be base errors in genome assemblies, we validated inactivating mutations as follows. Inactivating mutations that are identical between at least two independently sequenced and assembled sister species (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">figs.&#x000a0;1 and 2</xref>) are most likely real mutations that already occurred in the common ancestor. For inactivating mutations that occur only a single genome assembly, we used unassembled sequencing reads from the NCBI TRACE and Sequence Read Archives (<xref rid="evz238-B34" ref-type="bibr">Kodama et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>) for validation. To this end, we extracted the genomic context up- and downstream of the inactivating mutation and used megablast (parameters match score 1, mismatch scores &#x02212;2, gap costs linear, expectation value threshold 10) to determine the number of reads that support this mutation, as done before (<xref rid="evz238-B24" ref-type="bibr">Hecker et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>, <xref rid="evz238-B25" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B55" ref-type="bibr">Sharma, Lehmann, et al. 2018</xref>). Putative mutations that are not supported by reads are most likely base errors in the assembly, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. SRA accessions are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online.
</p><fig id="evz238-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 1.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Repeated losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> in placental mammals. A phylogenetic tree shows the species that have gene-inactivating mutations in <italic>BAAT</italic> (red font) together with a subset of species that have an intact <italic>BAAT</italic> gene (black font). The three coding exons of <italic>BAAT</italic> are shown as yellow boxes together with the position of inactivating mutations. Red arrowheads represent frameshifting insertions, red vertical lines represent frameshifting deletions, black vertical lines represent premature stop codons, and red boxes represent exon deletions. Gray insets illustrate that all shown inactivating mutations are validated either by unassembled sequencing reads or by the presence of the same mutation in the genomes of related species. The downstream parts of exon 3 in sheep (gray color) overlap an assembly gap; however, sheep shares other inactivating mutations with related species, showing that <italic>BAAT</italic> is lost in the sheep. The status of <italic>BAAT</italic> in the sperm whale is uncertain as the genomic region around exons 1 and 2 is not properly assembled (scaffolds end up- and downstream of these exons and there is no colinear alignment). Based on inactivating mutations that are shared between related species, we infer as many as 18 independent losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> have occurred in placental mammals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz238f1"/></fig><fig id="evz238-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 2.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Evolution of a second <italic>BAAT</italic> gene (<italic>BAATP1</italic>) that arose by a tandem duplication. (<italic>A</italic>) UCSC genome browser (<xref rid="evz238-B19" ref-type="bibr">Haeussler et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>) screenshot of the human locus containing <italic>BAAT</italic> and the surrounding genes (<italic>MRPL50</italic> and <italic>PLPPR1</italic>) shows the presence of an intron-containing pseudogene <italic>BAATP1</italic> (yellow background) downstream of <italic>BAAT</italic>, suggesting that this pseudogene copy arose by a tandem duplication. This pseudogene aligns to an intact gene in other placental mammals, as shown by the Gencode or Ensembl gene annotation (<xref rid="evz238-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cunningham et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). In the mouse, a tandem duplication of the human <italic>BAATP1</italic> ortholog occurred, giving rise to two genes annotated as <italic>Acnat1</italic> and <italic>Acnat2</italic>. In addition to Ensembl, we show human genes that are mapped by CESAR to the orthologous cow, cat, and elephant locus via the genome alignment (<xref rid="evz238-B52" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B54" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and Hiller 2017</xref>). As CESAR only projects intact human genes, it cannot annotate intact <italic>BAATP1</italic> orthologs (yellow background) in other species. In cow, CESAR only annotates the intact second exon of <italic>BAAT</italic>, as the other exons have inactivating mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). (<italic>B</italic>) Similar to <italic>BAAT</italic>, <italic>BAATP1</italic> is lost repeatedly in placental mammals (visualization as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). (<italic>C</italic>) Visualizing the presence (yellow box) or loss (red cross) of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> in 118 mammals shows that losses of these genes mostly occurred in a reciprocal fashion. A question mark indicates that it is uncertain whether the gene is present or lost.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz238f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Analyzing <italic>BAAT</italic> Genes in Platypus and Nonmammalian Amniotes</title><p>We aligned the platypus VGP assembly (<xref rid="evz238-B65" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>) to the human hg38 genome by applying lastz (<xref rid="evz238-B21" ref-type="bibr">Harris 2007</xref>) with parameters <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2,400, <italic>L</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3,000 and the HoxD55 scoring matrix, axtChain (<xref rid="evz238-B33" ref-type="bibr">Kent et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>), and chainCleaner (<xref rid="evz238-B59" ref-type="bibr">Suarez et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>) (both with default parameters). Collinear alignment chains were visualized in the UCSC genome browser (<xref rid="evz238-B7" ref-type="bibr">Casper et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Using this genome alignment, we projected human genes to the platypus with CESAR (<xref rid="evz238-B52" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>, <xref rid="evz238-B56" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In addition, we visualized the platypus NCBI gene annotation (<xref rid="evz238-B46" ref-type="bibr">Sayers et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>) (downloaded from NCBI) in the UCSC genome browser. This analysis showed gene order rearrangements and only a single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene.</p><p>To understand the evolutionary history of <italic>BAAT</italic> in amniotes, we analyzed the genomic context of this gene in representative amniotes: American alligator (allMis1 assembly), chicken (galGal4), Anole lizard (anoCar2), and painted turtle (chrPic2). Chains of colinear local alignments (<xref rid="evz238-B33" ref-type="bibr">Kent et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>) between hg38 and these assemblies were previously computed with highly sensitive alignment parameters (<xref rid="evz238-B54" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and Hiller 2017</xref>) and were used to locate genomic loci in these species that is orthologous to the human <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> locus. For these genomic loci, we obtained the order and orientation of annotated genes, using the Ensembl gene annotation (<xref rid="evz238-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cunningham et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>) and human genes projected via CESAR (<xref rid="evz238-B52" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>, <xref rid="evz238-B56" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). As the chicken and lizard locus that is orthologous to the human <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> locus did not contain a <italic>BAAT</italic> gene (this is confirmed by the latest chicken galGal6 assembly), we queried the Ensembl database, which revealed a gene annotated as a 1:1 ortholog to human <italic>BAAT</italic> (chicken ENSGALG00000040619, lizard ENSACAG00000017812). This gene is contained in the second locus, flanked by <italic>ZP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). As both alligator and turtle also have a <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in this locus, this suggests that the amniote ancestor possessed two <italic>BAAT</italic> genes in two different loci and that chicken and lizard have independently lost the gene located in the first locus.
</p><fig id="evz238-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 3.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Duplication and reciprocal loss patterns of <italic>BAAT</italic> during amniote evolution. (<italic>A</italic>) Simplified phylogenetic tree of representative amniote species where we analyzed gene order conservation of both loci containing annotated <italic>BAAT</italic> genes. The gene order of ancestral lineages was inferred by parsimony and major gene loss or rearrangement events are labeled on the respective branches. The amniote ancestor likely possessed a single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene (blue font), which was flanked by <italic>MRPL50</italic> (bold font). A tandem duplication of this gene occurred before the split of placental mammals and marsupials, giving rise to <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>. Turtle and alligator exhibit a second <italic>BAAT</italic> gene (green font) in a genomic locus flanked by <italic>ZP1</italic> (bold font). As frog and fish do not appear to possess a <italic>BAAT</italic>-like gene in this locus, this second <italic>BAAT</italic> gene likely arose by duplication in the <italic>Sauropsida</italic> ancestor. The <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in the first locus was likely independently lost in the lineage leading to chicken and anole lizard. In platypus, gene order around the single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene differs from other lineages, suggesting rearrangements in this locus that involved a local translocation of <italic>BAAT</italic> (note that the <italic>MRPL50</italic> gene is downstream of <italic>BAAT</italic>). (<italic>B</italic>) Phylogenetic tree computed by phyML (<xref rid="evz238-B64" ref-type="bibr">Yang 2007</xref>) from <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>ACOT</italic> type 1 family members corroborates the duplication and loss history of <italic>BAAT</italic> genes inferred gene order analysis. Bootstrap values in percent of 1,000 iterations are shown on those branches where bootstrap support was &#x0003c;100%. Zebrafish <italic>Acot22</italic> was used as an outgroup to root the tree. The tree supports that <italic>BAAT</italic> genes are separated from other <italic>ACOT</italic> family members and that the <italic>BAAT</italic> in both loci (blue and green, see panel <italic>A</italic>) represent two groups. <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes of placental mammals and marsupials (dark blue font) form a well-supported group, supporting that a single tandem duplication occurred. Several placental mammals exhibit lineage-specific duplications of <italic>BAAT</italic> (armadillo) or <italic>BAATP1</italic> (mouse, pig).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz238f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Inferring a Tree of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>ACOT</italic> Genes</title><p>To corroborate the duplication/loss history of <italic>BAAT</italic> genes that we inferred from the analysis of conserved gene order and to provide additional evidence that <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in the second locus is not a different member of the larger <italic>ACOT</italic> type 1 gene family, we build a gene tree. To this end, we aligned the sequences of different <italic>ACOT</italic> and <italic>BAAT</italic> genes from placental mammals, opossum, platypus, chicken, alligator, turtle, and lizard (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary tables 3 and 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The zebrafish <italic>Acot22</italic> sequence was used as an outgroup to root the tree. The sequences were aligned with MAFFT (<xref rid="evz238-B32" ref-type="bibr">Katoh and Standley 2013</xref>) (default parameters), and poorly aligning regions were removed using TrimAL (<xref rid="evz238-B5" ref-type="bibr">Capella-Gutierrez et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) (parameter -nogaps). Then, we generated a gene tree using phyML (<xref rid="evz238-B64" ref-type="bibr">Yang 2007</xref>) with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. We used Notung 2.9 (<xref rid="evz238-B10" ref-type="bibr">Darby et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>) to reconcile the gene tree with the species tree.</p></sec><sec><title>Reconstructing Ancestral Amino Acids in the Active Center</title><p>To reconstruct the ancestral amino acids in the active center, we build two multiple codon alignments, using the <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes of placental mammals and marsupials. We added the single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene of platypus, alligator, and turtle as outgroup sequences to both alignments. As the accuracy of ancestral reconstruction increases with the number of species, we also included the <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> sequences of species that lost these genes. To this end, we masked all in-frame stop codons and codons overlapping frameshifting insertions or deletions by replacing them with NNN in the respective species. In addition, we also masked the two codons flanking a frameshift because the position of the frameshifting insertion and deletion is sometimes ambiguous. To increase the alignment robustness, we further aligned the sequences with three aligners (PRANK [<xref rid="evz238-B37" ref-type="bibr">Loytynoja 2014</xref>], MUSCLE [<xref rid="evz238-B13" ref-type="bibr">Edgar 2004</xref>], and MAFFT [<xref rid="evz238-B32" ref-type="bibr">Katoh and Standley 2013</xref>]) and masked all codons in all species that are not consistently aligned by all three methods. These robust codon alignments of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary tables 5 and 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. To reconstruct ancestral amino acids, we applied codeml (<xref rid="evz238-B64" ref-type="bibr">Yang 2007</xref>) to these alignments. The reconstructed ancestral states of position 235 are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref> together with the probabilities of each amino acid.
</p><fig id="evz238-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 4.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Active-site residue in mammalian BAAT and BAATP1. The active-site residue corresponding to position 235 in human BAAT is indicated as S (Ser, red font) or C (Cys, blue font). For species that have inactivated <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes, the active-site residue is shown in black font, with X representing a deletion of the residue at position 235. For the <italic>Murinae</italic>, rabbit, pig, <italic>Myotis</italic> bats and armadillo, two residues are shown, because these species exhibit a lineage-specific duplication of <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic>. The color of branches in the gene trees indicates the reconstructed ancestral amino acid using the same color code (Ser, red; Cys, blue; black, lost gene). The posterior probability of the reconstructed ancestral amino acid is indicated for all branches where this probability is &#x0003c;0.99. Arrows highlight the branches along which a mutation from the ancestral Cys to Ser (red arrow) or a mutation from Ser to Cys (blue arrow) was inferred. The bile acid conjugation profile is taken from <xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</xref>. Lineages that contradict the prediction that Cys-containing <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> gene confers the ability to conjugate either glycine or taurine are shown in red font. Lineages that contradict the prediction that the presence of Ser-containing <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> gene(s) confers only ability to conjugate taurine are shown in blue font. Rhinoceroses, elephants, manatees, and rock hyraxes are shown in gray font because these species are special, in that they do not produce C<sub>24</sub> bile acids but only C<sub>27</sub> bile alcohols that are conjugated to sulfate (Sulf) or taurine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz238f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Searching Other ACOT Type-1 Family Members</title><p>For hippopotamus, cow, deer, and pig, we searched for other ACOT type-1 family members that have a cysteine in the active center. To this end, we used NCBI protein BLAST (Max target sequences = 1,000, word size = 3) to search for homologs to the human BAAT protein sequence. No ACOT type-1 protein with a cysteine-based active center was found. This analysis was corroborated by inspecting all local alignment chains that align to the third <italic>BAAT</italic> exon in human.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Widespread Losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> in Mammals</title><p>To find the genetic basis for the variation in the conjugated amino acids, we inspected the active-site residue at position 235 in <italic>BAAT</italic> of 118 mammals. Surprisingly, we noticed that this residue overlaps a frameshifting 1-bp deletion in <italic>Bovidae</italic>, suggesting that <italic>BAAT</italic> might be inactivated in this lineage. Therefore, we first analyzed in which of the 118 mammals is this gene actually conserved (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This analysis revealed that <italic>BAAT</italic> has undergone gene-inactivating mutations, such as frameshifting insertions and deletions, premature stop codons, splice-site mutations, and exon deletions in the genomes of at least 45 mammals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>).</p><p>Being aware that sequencing and assembly errors can mimic gene loss (<xref rid="evz238-B24" ref-type="bibr">Hecker et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>, <xref rid="evz238-B25" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B55" ref-type="bibr">Sharma, Lehmann, et al. 2018</xref>), we manually validated the putative loss of <italic>BAAT</italic> in every species as follows. First, we validated the correctness of all inactivating mutations to rule out sequencing errors that can be present in genome assemblies. We found that in many cases, identical inactivating mutations are shared between independently sequenced and assembled genomes of related species (insets in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>), which supports the validity of these mutations. Furthermore, we used unassembled sequencing reads to confirm all inactivating mutations for assemblies where no closely related sister species genomes are available. With exception of the pig, where the only inactivating mutation turned out to be a base error (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), we could confirm all other inactivating mutations in the other 44 mammals (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Second, for all 44 mammals, the remnants of the inactivated <italic>BAAT</italic> gene occur in the context of conserved gene order. Together, validated inactivating mutations and conserved gene order suggest that <italic>BAAT</italic> has been lost in 44 placental mammals. Based on the presence of shared inactivating mutations, we infer that <italic>BAAT</italic> may have been inactivated as many as 18 times in the branches of mammalian evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>A Second <italic>BAAT</italic>-Like Gene Explains Bile Acid Conjugation in <italic>BAAT</italic>-Loss Species</title><p>These widespread losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> are unexpected because almost all <italic>BAAT</italic>-loss species exhibit conjugated bile acids (<xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>) and in humans, <italic>BAAT</italic> is the only gene capable of bile acid conjugation (<xref rid="evz238-B6" ref-type="bibr">Carlton et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B50" ref-type="bibr">Setchell et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, we investigated which gene could be responsible for bile acid conjugation in <italic>BAAT</italic>-loss species. Inspection of the larger locus around <italic>BAAT</italic> in humans revealed the presence of an intron-containing pseudogene annotated as <italic>BAATP1</italic> (BAAT pseudogene 1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>A</italic></xref>) that contains several inactivating mutations in humans. Interestingly, this human pseudogene locus aligns to a genomic region in other placental mammals that contains a second intact <italic>BAAT</italic>-like gene, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F2">figure&#x000a0;2<italic>A</italic></xref> for mouse, cow, cat, and elephant. This suggests that a tandem duplication of an ancestral <italic>BAAT</italic>-like gene occurred before the split of these placental mammals, giving rise to <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>, which was followed by the loss of <italic>BAATP1</italic> in humans. In the mouse, another tandem duplication of <italic>BAATP1</italic> happened, giving rise to two genes annotated as <italic>Acnat1</italic> and <italic>Acnat2</italic>. Although <italic>Acnat2</italic> has not been experimentally studied, previous experiments showed that mouse <italic>Acnat1</italic> is able to conjugate bile acids or fatty-acid CoA to taurine, even though its activity is much lower for bile acids (<xref rid="evz238-B44" ref-type="bibr">Reilly et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). This shows that intact orthologs of human <italic>BAATP1</italic> can function as a second bile acid-conjugating enzyme. Consistent with this observation, previous biochemical experiments have shown that the cow possesses a functional enzyme with <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase activity, although the identity of the protein was not determined (<xref rid="evz238-B61" ref-type="bibr">Vessey 1979</xref>). Our analysis suggests that the intact <italic>BAATP1</italic> ortholog in cow (Ensembl ENSBTAG00000025760) most likely encodes the bile acid-conjugating enzyme, providing an explanation for why conjugated bile acids were observed in many mammals that have lost <italic>BAAT</italic>. In a similar manner, the loss of <italic>BAATP1</italic> in humans explains why <italic>BAAT</italic> is their only gene capable of bile acid conjugation. To indicate that both genes arose by a tandem duplication of an ancestral <italic>BAAT</italic> gene, we consistently refer to both genes as <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>, despite the fact that <italic>BAATP1</italic> is an intact gene in many mammals.</p></sec><sec><title>Widespread Reciprocal Losses of <italic>BAATP1</italic> in Placental Mammals</title><p>Because <italic>BAATP1</italic> is an inactivated gene in humans, we analyzed in detail in which mammals this gene is also lost. Putative inactivating mutations were validated by sequencing reads and the presence of the same mutation in related species, as described above. This analysis showed that <italic>BAATP1</italic> is lost not only in humans but in total eight times independently in the primate lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>B</italic></xref>). Furthermore, <italic>BAATP1</italic> is lost in many other placental mammal lineages, comprising a total of 34 mammals in our data set. Based on inactivating mutations that are shared between related species, we estimate that 17 independent losses of <italic>BAATP1</italic> occurred in placental mammals.</p><p>Next, we tested whether the remaining sequences of inactivated <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes evolve under relaxed selection. Using RELAX (<xref rid="evz238-B63" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), we found significant evidence of relaxed selection for one of 13 <italic>BAAT</italic>-loss lineages and seven of 17 <italic>BAATP1</italic>-loss lineages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Several factors could explain the absence of significant evidence for relaxed selection in gene-loss lineages. First, for recently inactivated genes, the power to detect significant evidence for a shift from purifying selection to relaxed selection or neutral evolution is limited. Indeed, several mammalian lineages may have lost <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> more recently. For example, <italic>BAAT</italic> in <italic>Delphinoidea</italic> and the Minke whale exhibits only a single inactivating mutation; however, available RNA-seq data of liver tissue show that the inactivated <italic>BAAT</italic> is not expressed anymore (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), supporting the loss of the gene. Additionally, significant evidence for relaxation may be harder to detect for slowly evolving lineages. This is exemplified by <italic>BAAT</italic> in the <italic>Delphinoidea</italic> lineage, where RELAX estimates that 82% of the gene evolves neutrally (Ka/Ks = 1) but evidence for relaxation is not significant (<italic>P</italic>-value 0.08). Second, the detection of relaxed selection in a gene-loss lineage relies on a comparison to all species that have an intact <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic>, making the assumption that the gene evolves under purifying selection in all species with intact gene(s). If, however, either <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> alone would be sufficient for bile acid conjugation (see next paragraph), then this assumption might not hold for some of the species that possess two intact genes. Cat may be such an example. The cat possesses intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes, but available liver RNA-seq data show that <italic>BAAT</italic> is not expressed anymore (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), suggesting that <italic>BAATP1</italic> is the major bile acid-conjugating enzyme.</p><p>Interestingly, losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> are largely reciprocal, with 74 species having lost either <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>C</italic></xref>), which supports one gene is generally sufficient for bile acid conjugation. Although the term &#x0201c;reciprocal gene loss,&#x0201d; defined as &#x0201c;the situation when two lineages that have inherited a gene duplication independently lose alternative members of the duplicated pair after speciation&#x0201d; (<xref rid="evz238-B49" ref-type="bibr">Semon and Wolfe 2007</xref>), was originally used to describe patterns of gene losses after a whole-genome duplication (<xref rid="evz238-B47" ref-type="bibr">Scannell et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B49" ref-type="bibr">Semon and Wolfe 2007</xref>), our analysis reveals an example where reciprocal losses occurred following a tandem gene duplication. Only two species have lost both genes, the manatee and the Damara mole rat. For the manatee, previous measurements have shown that this species does not produce bile acids at all (similar to the related elephant and rock hyrax), but instead produces bile alcohols that are conjugated with sulfate (<xref rid="evz238-B35" ref-type="bibr">Kuroki et&#x000a0;al. 1988</xref>). This suggests that both <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> became obsolete in manatee, which led to the loss of both genes. For the Damara mole rat, the bile composition has not yet been characterized, making this species an attractive target to investigate whether it produces bile acids and if so whether they are conjugated. Apart from the double loss of both genes in these animals, the widespread reciprocal losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> suggest that almost all placental mammal lineages preserve at least one intact <italic>BAAT</italic>-like gene, which is consistent with observations that bile acid conjugation occurs in almost all mammals (<xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Complex Duplication and Loss History of <italic>BAAT</italic> Genes in Amniotes</title><p>Next, we asked when the tandem duplication that gave rise to <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> occurred. To this end, we analyzed this locus in the genomes of two marsupials (opossum and Tasmanian devil [<xref rid="evz238-B38" ref-type="bibr">Mikkelsen et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B40" ref-type="bibr">Murchison et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>]) and one monotreme (platypus). We found that opossum possesses intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes in this locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3<italic>A</italic></xref>). Likewise, the Tasmanian devil possesses <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>, even though <italic>BAATP1</italic> exon 1 is not present in the genome due to an assembly gap. As the previous Sanger sequencing-based platypus assembly (<xref rid="evz238-B62" ref-type="bibr">Warren et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>) contained the <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> locus on several scaffolds, which prevented a conclusive analysis, we analyzed a new reference-quality platypus assembly produced by the Vertebrate Genome Project (<xref rid="evz238-B65" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>) where the entire locus is contained on an &#x0223c;9.3-Mb contig. Analyzing this assembly revealed several gene order rearrangements but only a single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in the platypus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This suggests that the tandem duplication that gave rise to <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> occurred after the split of monotremes from the ancestor of both marsupials and placental mammals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3<italic>A</italic></xref>). This finding is corroborated by an analysis of nonmammal genomes (alligator and turtle), which revealed a single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in this locus in both species.</p><p>Interestingly, in contrast to alligator and turtle, two other nonmammals (chicken and green anole lizard) do not possess any <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in this locus. However, both chicken and lizard have an annotated <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in a second locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3<italic>A</italic></xref>). To investigate the evolutionary history of <italic>BAAT</italic> in amniotes, we analyzed gene order in both of these loci. As summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">figure&#x000a0;3<italic>A</italic></xref>, this analysis infers that the <italic>Sauropsida</italic> ancestor possessed two <italic>BAAT</italic> genes in two distinct genomic loci that are flanked by <italic>MRPL50</italic> in the first locus and by <italic>ZP1</italic> in the second locus. Both alligator and turtle maintain a <italic>BAAT</italic> gene at both loci. Thus, the most likely scenario explaining the absence of <italic>BAAT</italic> in the first locus in chicken and lizard is an independent loss in the lineages leading to the chicken and anole lizard. These findings are confirmed by reconstructing a gene tree, which supports that the <italic>BAAT</italic> genes at both loci are distinct from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3<italic>B</italic></xref>). Importantly, both gene tree and phylogenetic reconciliation support that the <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> genes of placental mammals and marsupials arose by a single tandem duplication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3<italic>B</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Overall, these results suggest that <italic>BAAT</italic> genes exhibit a complex duplication and loss history not only in placental mammals but also during the evolution of amniotes.</p></sec><sec><title>High Variability of Cys and Ser in the Active Site in Mammalian <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic></title><p>Having established that <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> are two genes likely capable of bile acid conjugation in placental mammals and marsupials, we investigated the active-site residues in all intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes. We found that <sup>328</sup>Asp and <sup>362</sup>His are perfectly conserved in intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes. Focusing on position 235, we found that all intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> orthologs have either Cys or Ser in the active site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>), which is consistent with either Cys or Ser being necessary for enzymatic activity (<xref rid="evz238-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pazirandeh et&#x000a0;al. 1991</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). However, we observed many changes between Cys and Ser at this position among intact <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic> orthologs. Using a codon alignment of <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic>, we reconstructed ancestral sequences, which showed that <sup>235</sup>Cys is the amino acid that was likely present in the ancestor of placental mammals and marsupials for both BAAT and BAATP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). This is consistent with the single <italic>BAAT</italic> gene of platypus, alligator, and turtle, which also exhibit <sup>235</sup>Cys. From the reconstructed ancestral states, we infer that <italic>BAAT</italic><sup>235</sup>Cys was mutated to Ser in five mammalian lineages and <italic>BAATP1</italic> Cys was mutated to Ser in five mammalian lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Back mutations from Ser to Cys happened only once in <italic>BAAT</italic> (in the ancestor of horses and the rhinoceros) and once in <italic>BAATP1</italic> (in the prairie vole).</p></sec><sec><title>Cys or Ser in the Active Site Has Little Power to Predict the Preferred Conjugated Amino Acids</title><p>Next, we tested whether the presence of <sup>235</sup>Cys is predictive for conjugation with either glycine or taurine and whether the presence of <sup>235</sup>Ser is predictive for taurine-only conjugation. The composition of bile acids and the conjugated amino acids have been experimentally determined for a total of 79 mammals in our data set or their close relatives (<xref rid="evz238-B20" ref-type="bibr">Hagey et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). We intersected these data with the active-site residue of intact <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This revealed several clades or species (Old World monkeys, sifaka, beaver, naked mole rat, rabbit, and horse) possess at least one Cys-containing <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> gene and, as predicted, exhibit conjugation with either glycine or taurine. Similarly, several other clades and species (chinchilla, squirrel, <italic>Cetacea</italic>, goats, <italic>Carnivora</italic>, <italic>Chiroptera</italic>, and <italic>Eulipotyphla</italic>) possess only Ser-containing <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> gene(s) and, as predicted, exhibit taurine-only conjugation.</p><p>However, there are numerous exceptions where the observed conjugation pattern differed from conjugation pattern predicted from the presence of Cys- or Ser-containing BAAT/BAATP1 enzymes. For example, several primates (marmoset, tarsier, bushbaby, and mouse lemur), the tree shrew, mouse, several <italic>Afrotheria</italic> (tenrec, elephant shrew, and aardvark), armadillo, and the two analyzed marsupials (opossum and Tasmanian devil) all possess at least one Cys-containing <italic>BAAT</italic>/<italic>BAATP1</italic> gene, which should confer the ability to conjugate both glycine and taurine, but exhibit taurine-only conjugation (these species are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> in red font). Furthermore, the <italic>BAAT</italic> gene of the platypus, alligator, and turtle also has a Cys, but these species only conjugate taurine to bile acids.</p><p>Even more strikingly, we also observed several violations to the prediction that Ser-containing BAAT/BAATP1 enzymes are only able to conjugate taurine. Hippopotamus, <italic>Bovinae</italic>, deer, and pig possess only Ser-containing BAAT or BAATP1 but exhibit measurable bile acid conjugation with both taurine and glycine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz238-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>, species in blue font). Overall, this analysis shows that residue corresponding to position 235 provides little predictive power for observed bile acid conjugation patterns in mammals and nonmammal species.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we investigated the evolution of the bile acid amino acid-conjugating <italic>BAAT</italic> gene in 118 mammals to explain their conjugation differences. Unexpectedly, we found that <italic>BAAT</italic> exhibits a complex evolutionary history, characterized by a tandem duplication before the split of placental mammals and marsupials giving rise to <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>, which was followed by many independent and mostly reciprocal losses. Tandem duplications of <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> subsequently happened in five individual placental mammal lineages (<italic>Murinae</italic>, rabbit, pig, <italic>Myotis</italic> bats, and armadillo), which suggests that this locus is generally prone to tandem duplications. Numerous reciprocal losses of <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> in placental mammals suggest that an additional gene copy does not provide an advantage for most species, and that a single gene is generally sufficient for bile acid conjugation. We found only two species (manatee and Damara mole rat) that have lost both <italic>BAAT</italic> and <italic>BAATP1</italic>. Although manatee is special in that it does not produce bile acids but instead sulfate-conjugated bile alcohols (<xref rid="evz238-B35" ref-type="bibr">Kuroki et&#x000a0;al. 1988</xref>), the bile of the Damara mole rat has not been characterized, making this species an attractive target to determine whether it produces bile acids and, if so, whether they are unconjugated.</p><p>The mechanism underlying the enzymatic function BAAT appears to be well understood, because the three amino acids in the active site (<sup>235</sup>Cys/Ser, <sup>328</sup>Asp, and <sup>362</sup>His) form a catalytic triad (<xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>), a very common and highly conserved configuration found at the active site of hydrolase and transferase enzymes (<xref rid="evz238-B12" ref-type="bibr">Dodson and Wlodawer 1998</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B3" ref-type="bibr">Buller and Townsend 2013</xref>). Furthermore, mutagenesis experiments with human BAAT have shown that replacing <sup>235</sup>Cys with Ser diminishes its ability to conjugate with glycine. This is consistent with the Cys-containing BAAT of the rat being able to conjugate both glycine and taurine (<xref rid="evz238-B22" ref-type="bibr">He et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>), whereas the Ser-containing mouse Acnat1 (BAATP1) enzyme is only able to conjugate taurine (<xref rid="evz238-B44" ref-type="bibr">Reilly et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). Given this apparently well-established paradigm, a surprising result of our large-scale comparative study is that the presence of Cys or Ser in BAAT/BAATP1 has little power in predicting the preferred amino acids that are conjugated to bile acids.</p><p>Specifically, our analysis revealed a number of mammalian lineages that possess Cys-containing <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> genes but conjugate only with taurine. Despite the predicted ability to conjugate either glycine or taurine, it is possible that all these species only conjugate with taurine, because glycine is not readily available in the peroxisomes of hepatocytes. Indeed, the availability of taurine and glycine influences the ratio of taurine and glycine conjugates (<xref rid="evz238-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sweeny et&#x000a0;al. 1991</xref>). However, we do not favor this hypothesis because in vitro experiments with mouse BAAT have shown that the mouse enzyme is only able to conjugate taurine even if glycine is available (<xref rid="evz238-B15" ref-type="bibr">Falany et&#x000a0;al. 1997</xref>).</p><p>Maybe even more surprising, we found that the hippopotamus, <italic>Bovinae</italic>, deer, and pig exhibit conjugation with either glycine or taurine, despite lacking any Cys-containing <italic>BAAT</italic> or <italic>BAATP1</italic> gene. Several hypotheses could explain this observation. First, it is possible that a third enzyme is capable of conjugating bile acids to glycine. However, we believe that this is less likely, because in humans, which naturally lost <italic>BAATP1</italic>, BAAT is the only enzyme capable of bile acid conjugation (<xref rid="evz238-B6" ref-type="bibr">Carlton et&#x000a0;al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B50" ref-type="bibr">Setchell et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Furthermore, we searched for other ACOT type 1 family members with a cysteine in the active site and found none in these lineages. A second hypothesis is that BAAT or BAATP1 of these lineages is able to conjugate glycine with a serine-based mechanism. For example, a previous study showed that the C-terminus of the enzyme also influences the ratio between taurine and glycine conjugation (<xref rid="evz238-B57" ref-type="bibr">Styles et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>); however, we found no obvious correlation between the C-terminal amino acids and the conjugation profile (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Furthermore, another mechanism not relying on the catalytic triad may exist. For example, the related ACOT type 2 enzymes rely on a &#x0201c;hot-dog&#x0201d; fold for enzymatic activity (<xref rid="evz238-B4" ref-type="bibr">Cantu et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). A third hypothesis relates to the fact that hippopotamus, <italic>Bovinae</italic>, and deer are obligate herbivores. The plant-based diet provides these herbivores with larger amounts of oxalate, which can be harmful as mammals cannot further metabolize oxalate. To compensate for the high intake of oxalate, herbivores prevent endogenous oxalate production by transaminating the oxalate precursor, glyoxylate, to glycine (<xref rid="evz238-B9" ref-type="bibr">Danpure 1997</xref>). This reaction is mediated by the enzyme AGT (alanine-glyoxylate aminotransferase). As glyoxylate is mainly produced in peroxisomes, many herbivores retarget AGT from mitochondria to peroxisomes (<xref rid="evz238-B9" ref-type="bibr">Danpure 1997</xref>). Because the peroxisome is the site of both glyoxylate synthesis and bile acid conjugation, the local concentration of glycine in the peroxisome could be very high in herbivores and this glycine would be readily available for BAAT. As human Ser-mutated BAAT exhibits low levels of glycine conjugation (see figure 5 of <xref rid="evz238-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sfakianos et&#x000a0;al. [2002</xref>]), high glycine concentrations may result in bile acids with measurable glycine conjugation. This hypothesis could be tested by in vitro characterizations of cow <italic>BAATP1</italic> under conditions of high glycine concentrations.</p><p>Overall, our results suggest that the mechanistic understanding of the enzymatic function of mammalian BAAT may be incompletely understood. More generally, our analysis indicates that results of mutagenesis experiments obtained from enzymes of selected mammals (such as human or mouse) cannot always be extrapolated to other mammals, even if enzymatic function involves a highly conserved active-site configuration such as the catalytic triad.</p><p>Finally, an interesting question is why most mammals prefer taurine-only conjugation. One factor might be related to the fact that glycine-conjugated bile acids start to precipitate below a pH of 3, whereas taurine conjugates remain soluble up to a pH of 1.5 (<xref rid="evz238-B17" ref-type="bibr">Fini and Roda 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evz238-B39" ref-type="bibr">Mukaisho et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). As the acidity of the stomach differs among species, for example, herbivores tend to have higher pH values than carnivores (<xref rid="evz238-B1" ref-type="bibr">Beasley et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), taurine conjugates might be preferred in species exhibiting a more acidic gastrointestinal environment. Another intriguing hypothesis is that taurine (in contrast to glycine) contains sulfur. As bile acids are deconjugated by the gut microbiome, taurine-conjugated bile acids deliver a sulfur-containing compound to the intestinal environment. Gut bacteria can use sulfur-containing compounds, such as taurine, as electron sinks in respiratory metabolism (<xref rid="evz238-B36" ref-type="bibr">Laue et&#x000a0;al. 1997</xref>). Therefore, it is possible that taurine conjugation is beneficial for the host by indirectly providing energy to the gut microbiome, which in turn may contribute to a healthy gut microbiome composition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>evz238_Supplementary_Data</label><media xlink:href="evz238_supplementary_data.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="A1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank the genomics community for sequencing and assembling the genomes and the UCSC genome browser group for providing software and genome annotations. We thank Guojie Zhang and Erich Jarvis for access to the VGP platypus assembly. We also thank David Jebb for helpful discussions and the Computer Service Facilities of the MPI-CBG and MPI-PKS for their support. This work was supported by the Max Planck Society. The authors have no competing interests.</p></ack><ref-list id="R1"><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evz238-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koltz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>RR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The evolution of stomach acidity and its relevance to the human microbiome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e0134116</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26222383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broeders</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The bile acid chenodeoxycholic acid increases human brown adipose tissue activity</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>. <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26235421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buller</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>CA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Intrinsic evolutionary constraints on protease structure, enzyme acylation, and the identity of the catalytic triad</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>110</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>E653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ardevol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rovira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Molecular mechanism of a hotdog-fold acyl-CoA thioesterase</article-title>. <source>Chemistry</source><volume>20</volume>(<issue>29</issue>):<fpage>9045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9051</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silla-Martinez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>trimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1973</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Complex inheritance of familial hypercholanemia with associated mutations in TJP2 and BAAT</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12704386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>The UCSC Genome Browser database: 2018 update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>46</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D762</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D769</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29106570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>Ensembl 2019</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D751</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danpure</surname><given-names>CJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Variable peroxisomal and mitochondrial targeting of alanine: glyoxylate aminotransferase in mammalian evolution and disease</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source><volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9136629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stolzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ropp</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Xenolog classification</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>649</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27998934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiMarzio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Identification of a mouse <italic>Lactobacillus johnsonii</italic> strain with deconjugase activity against the FXR antagonist T-beta-MCA</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>12</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0183564</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28910295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wlodawer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Catalytic triads and their relatives</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9787641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekwall</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1951</year>
<article-title>Micelle formation in sodium cholate solutions. Acta Acad</article-title><source>Aboensis Math Phys</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fortinberry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Cloning, expression, and chromosomal localization of mouse liver bile acid CoA:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9215542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diasio</surname><given-names>RB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Glycine and taurine conjugation of bile acids by a single enzyme. Molecular cloning and expression of human liver bile acid CoA:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>269</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>19375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8034703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Chemical properties of bile acids. IV. Acidity constants of glycine-conjugated bile acids</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>759</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3625035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biagioli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zampella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Distrutti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Bile acids activated receptors regulate innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1853</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30150987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haeussler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>The UCSC Genome Browser database: 2019 update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagey</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krasowski</surname><given-names>MD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary diversity of bile salts in reptiles and mammals, including analysis of ancient human and extinct giant ground sloth coprolites</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>133.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20444292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>. Improved pairwise alignment of genomic DNA [Ph.D. Thesis]. The Pennsylvania State University.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>CN.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Rat liver bile acid CoA:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase: expression, characterization, and peroxisomal localization</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>44</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12951368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>Bitter humour: the development of ideas about bile salts</article-title>. <source>J R Coll Physicians Lond</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4942482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Transition to an aquatic habitat permitted the repeated loss of the pleiotropic KLK8 gene in mammals</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29145610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>Convergent gene losses illuminate metabolic and physiological changes in herbivores and carnivores</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>116</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3036</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3041</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heubi</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Setchell</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>KE.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Inborn errors of bile acid metabolism</article-title>. <source>Semin Liver Dis</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17682975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>AF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1963</year>
<article-title>The function of bile salts in fat absorption. The solvent properties of dilute micellar solutions of conjugated bile salts</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>. <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14097367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagey</surname><given-names>LR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Key discoveries in bile acid chemistry and biology and their clinical applications: history of the last eight decades</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>55</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24838141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagey</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krasowski</surname><given-names>MD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Bile salts of vertebrates: structural variation and possible evolutionary significance</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>51</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19638645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikegawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Characterization of cholyl-adenylate in rat liver microsomes by liquid chromatography/electrospray ionization-mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <volume>266</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9887221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gahan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchesi</surname><given-names>JR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Functional and comparative metagenomic analysis of bile salt hydrolase activity in the human gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>105</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>13580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13585</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baertsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Evolution&#x02019;s cauldron: duplication, deletion, and rearrangement in the mouse and human genomes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>100</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>11484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>International Nucleotide Sequence Database C 2012. The Sequence Read Archive: explosive growth of sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Bile salts of the West Indian manatee, <italic>Trichechus manatus latirostris</italic>: novel bile alcohol sulfates and absence of bile acids</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3392467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>AM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Taurine reduction in anaerobic respiration of <italic>Bilophila wadsworthia</italic> RZATAU</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>2016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2021</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9143131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loytynoja</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Phylogeny-aware alignment with PRANK</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <volume>1079</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24170401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Genome of the marsupial <italic>Monodelphis domestica</italic> reveals innovation in non-coding sequences</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>447</volume>(<issue>7141</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17495919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaisho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Potential mechanism of corpus-predominant gastritis after PPI therapy in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>-positive patients with GERD</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>. <volume>20</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>11962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11965</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25232231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murchison</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genome sequencing and analysis of the Tasmanian devil and its transmissible cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>148</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>780</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>XH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Cross-talk between bile acids and intestinal microbiota in host metabolism and health</article-title>. <source>J Zhejiang Univ Sci B</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>446</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pazirandeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chirala</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wakil</surname><given-names>SJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Site-directed mutagenesis studies on the recombinant thioesterase domain of chicken fatty acid synthase expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>266</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>20946</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20952</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1939144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellicoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Human and rat bile acid-CoA:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase are liver-specific peroxisomal enzymes: implications for intracellular bile salt transport</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source><volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17256745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A peroxisomal acyltransferase in mouse identifies a novel pathway for taurine conjugation of fatty acids</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The enzymes, regulation, and genetics of bile acid synthesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>. <volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12543708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30395293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Multiple rounds of speciation associated with reciprocal gene loss in polyploid yeasts</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>440</volume>(<issue>7082</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trauner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>PL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Bile acid receptors as targets for drug development</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23982684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Reciprocal gene loss between <italic>Tetraodon</italic> and zebrafish after whole genome duplication in their ancestor</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17275132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Setchell</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genetic defects in bile acid conjugation cause fat-soluble vitamin deficiency</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>144</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>955</lpage>.e6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23415802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sfakianos</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakalian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Conserved residues in the putative catalytic triad of human bile acid coenzyme A:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>277</volume>(<issue>49</issue>):<fpage>47270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elghafari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Coding exon-structure aware realigner (CESAR) utilizes genome alignments for accurate comparative gene annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>44</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e103.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27016733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>A genomics approach reveals insights into the importance of gene losses for mammalian adaptations</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1215.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29572503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Increased alignment sensitivity improves the usage of genome alignments for comparative gene annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>45</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>8369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28645144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuckas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Loss of RXFP2 and INSL3 genes in <italic>Afrotheria</italic> shows that testicular descent is the ancestral condition in placental mammals</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e2005293.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29953435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwede</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>CESAR 2.0 substantially improves speed and accuracy of comparative gene annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>33</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>3985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3987</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28961744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Styles</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Carboxy-terminal mutations of bile acid CoA:<italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase alter activity and substrate specificity</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>57</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27230263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Styles</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falany</surname><given-names>CN.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Quantification and regulation of the subcellular distribution of bile acid coenzyme A:amino acid <italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase activity in rat liver</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>. <volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>chainCleaner improves genome alignment specificity and sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1596</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1603</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28108446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweeny</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diasio</surname><given-names>RB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Bile acid conjugation pattern in the isolated perfused rat liver during infusion of an amino acid formulation</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1907679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vessey</surname><given-names>DA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>The co-purification and common identity of cholyl CoA:glycine- and cholyl CoA:taurine-<italic>N</italic>-acyltransferase activities from bovine liver</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>254</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2063</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">422567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Genome analysis of the platypus reveals unique signatures of evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>453</volume>(<issue>7192</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18464734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>RELAX: detecting relaxed selection in a phylogenetic framework</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25540451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>24</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1591</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz238-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2019</year> BGI-G10K-VGP platypus male genome, primary haplotype. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/assembly/GCF_004115215.1">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/assembly/GCF_004115215.1</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>