<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PNAS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0027-8424</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1091-6490</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32241894</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">202002235</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2002235117</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>524</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biological Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><series-title>Brief Report</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Convergent spectral shifts to blue-green vision in mammals extends the known sensitivity of vertebrate M/LWS pigments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Yimeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>Stephen J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9258-7237</contrib-id><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>d</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>a</sup>College of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine, <institution>Shenyang Agricultural University</institution>, 110866 Shenyang, <country>China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>b</sup>College of Life Sciences, <institution>Shaanxi Normal University</institution>, 710119 Xi&#x02019;an, <country>China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>c</sup>School of Biological and Chemical Sciences, <institution>Queen Mary University of London</institution>, E1 4NS London, <country>United Kingdom</country>;</aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>d</sup>Key Laboratory of Zoonosis of Liaoning Province, <institution>Shenyang Agricultural University</institution>, 110866 Shenyang, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>1</sup>To whom correspondence may be addressed. Email: <email>yliu@snnu.edu.cn</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by Jeremy Nathans, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, and approved March 10, 2020 (received for review February 11, 2020)</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Author contributions: Y.L. designed research; H.C. and Y.C. performed research; Y.L. contributed new reagents/analytic tools; H.C. and Y.L. analyzed data; and H.C., S.J.R., and Y.L. wrote the paper.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>117</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>8303</fpage><lpage>8305</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 the Author(s). Published by PNAS.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="vor">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This open access article is distributed under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0 (CC BY-NC-ND)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="pnas.202002235.pdf"/><abstract><p>Daylight vision in most mammals is mediated predominantly by a middle/long wavelength-sensitive (M/LWS) pigment. Although spectral sensitivity and associated shifts in M/LWS are mainly determined by five critical sites, predicted phenotypic variation is rarely validated, and its ecological significance is unclear. We experimentally determine spectral tuning of M/LWS pigments and show that two highly divergent taxa, the gerbil and the elephant-shrew, have undergone independent dramatic blue-green shifts to 490 nm. By generating mutant proteins, we identify additional critical sites contributing to these shifts. Our results, which extend the known range of spectral tuning of vertebrate M/LWS, provide a compelling case of functional convergence, likely related to parallel adaptive shifts from nocturnal to brighter light conditions in similar habitats.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>opsin</kwd><kwd>middle/long wavelength-sensitive pigment</kwd><kwd>spectral tuning</kwd><kwd>functional convergence</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="gs1"><funding-source id="sp1">National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)<named-content content-type="funder-id">501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">31601855</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Yang Liu</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs2"><funding-source id="sp2">Shaanxi Normal University<named-content content-type="funder-id">501100004303</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">start-up fund</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Yang Liu</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs3"><funding-source id="sp3">European Research Council</funding-source><award-id rid="sp3">310482</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Stephen J Rossiter</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="flushleft">Light sensitivity to daylight conditions in most mammals is conferred by a middle/long wavelength-sensitive (M/LWS) pigment, normally complemented by a short wavelength-sensitive visual pigment (SWS1), and rhodopsin (RH1) for dim-light vision, with the pigment opsin encoded by the genes <italic>OPN1MW</italic>/<italic>LW</italic>, <italic>OPN1SW</italic>, and <italic>RHO</italic>, respectively (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). While some lineages have lost the SWS1 opsin via relaxed selection linked to low-light niches (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), the M/LWS opsin is functional across mammals, with a few exceptions (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Evidence, to date, indicates that the spectral tuning of M/LWS pigments (499 nm to 571 nm) (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), measured by the wavelength of maximum sensitivity (&#x003bb;<sub>max</sub>), is mainly controlled by amino acid identity at five critical sites (positions 180, 197, 277, 285, and 308) (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), although other sites (e.g., 213 and 294) may also affect spectral tuning via epistatic interactions (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Predicted &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values from known critical sites imply spectral shifts in M/LWS pigments during the diversification of mammals (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), yet these have rarely been validated (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and their ecological significance is not known.</p><p>Here we determined the spectral phenotypes of M/LWS pigments in the highly divergent mammalian clades Rodentia (superorder Euarchontoglires) and Afrotheria, for which sequence-based predictions have suggested marked short-wavelength spectral shifts (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Our results indicate that five rodents&#x02014;the alpine marmot, degu, golden hamster (&#x0201c;hamster&#x0201d;), lesser Egyptian jerboa (&#x0201c;jerboa&#x0201d;), and Mongolian gerbil (&#x0201c;gerbil&#x0201d;)&#x02014;are all sensitive to shorter wavelengths of light (516, 502, 504, 501, and 490 nm, respectively) than the predicted values (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S1</ext-link>). We also found that the pigment of one species, the Damaraland mole-rat, showed no readable peak despite possessing an intact open reading frame, implying a potentially unstable pigment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="featured" id="fig01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Phenotypic evolution of M/LWS pigments in Rodentia and Afrotheria. (<italic>A</italic>) Values of &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> for M/LWS for extant and ancestral taxa. The values obtained in this study by either direct measurement (*) or estimation from critical sites (&#x02020;). Published &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values are based on either direct measurements or sequence-based predictions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S1</ext-link>). Across the two clades, branches and &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values are colored by wavelength sensitivity, as yellow (550 nm to 556 nm), green (&#x02264;549 nm), and blue (490 nm). Gray indicates no value. Predicted values are shown in italics. For branches leading to gerbil and elephant-shrew, all amino acid substitutions are shown, with critical sites identified here underlined. Other focal branches show known critical substitutions only (bold) (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). For gerbil and elephant-shrew, recorded absorbance peaks (difference spectra) and &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values for all three pigments are shown. (<italic>B</italic>) Phylogenetic tree showing position of the focal orders Rodentia and Macroscelidea (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Published &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values for each mammalian order are shown as either ranges (black bars) or single point values (black triangles). The &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> values measured in this study are indicated by red triangles (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S1</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.2002235117fig01"/></fig><p>We also performed M/L opsin in vitro expression assays for representatives of three orders of Afrotheria: the aardvark (order Tubulidentata), Cape rock elephant-shrew (Macroscelidea), and lesser hedgehog tenrec (Afrosoricida), hereafter referred to as elephant-shrew and tenrec. For the aardvark and tenrec, the respective spectral peaks (522 and 554 nm) were similar to values predicted by sequences (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In contrast, the elephant-shrew&#x02019;s pigment had a &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> of 490 nm, showing a wide discrepancy (32 nm) with the predicted value (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). The highly divergent elephant-shrew and gerbil appear to have both undergone dramatic functionally convergent shifts (&#x02212;60 and &#x02212;20 nm) in M/L opsin sensitivity toward blue-green light, extending the lowest known limits for vertebrates (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Both taxa occur in similar desert and/or grassland habitats (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), and also show more daylight activity patterns than their respective closest relatives (e.g., tenrec or mouse/rat in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>) (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Thus the observed spectral changes are likely to be associated with transitions from a nocturnal niche to one characterized by a wider range of light conditions.</p><p>To determine the molecular basis of spectral tuning, we performed in vitro expression of ancestral proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>), and, using site-directed mutagenesis, generated mutants containing derived substitutions. For the degu, hamster, and jerboa, differences in spectral sensitivity between the expressed derived and respective ancestral proteins could be explained by observed substitutions at known critical sites (Y277F, T285A, and A308S). In contrast, the gerbil and elephant-shrew were each characterized by an amino acid substitution at a single critical site (T285A and A308S, respectively). Introducing these residues into the ancestral proteins did not recover the recorded &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> value of the wild types. We therefore searched the protein sequences of each taxon for other potentially important substitutions on the basis of changes in the presence of a hydroxyl group (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). For gerbil M/LWS pigment, we found that S107G and S134A gave rise to spectral shifts in &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> (&#x02212;3 and &#x02212;6 nm, respectively), and that the combination of S107G, S134A, and T285A recovered the &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> shift to 490 nm seen in the wild-type gerbil (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S2</ext-link>).</p><p>We repeated this approach for the elephant-shrew, and found a critical site (position 48), with an A48T mutation producing a &#x02212;9-nm &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> shift. This species also showed an amino acid substitution (H294Y) at a known critical site (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) that resulted in a &#x02212;3-nm shift. When combined with the A308S critical replacement, these three substitutions caused a 44-nm &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> shift toward blue-green range, which is still 16 nm short of the observed &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S2</ext-link>). Our findings thus indicate that lineages of two distantly related superorders of mammals have undergone tuning to blue-green light via nonidentical molecular routes, and that shifts in the latter stem, in part, from unknown molecular mechanisms.</p><p>Both identified critical sites associated with large spectral shifts (i.e., S134A in gerbil and A48T in elephant-shrew) occur in exon 2. By comparing orthologous exonic sequence across vertebrates, we found the same S134A replacement in some ray-finned fishes, lobe-finned fishes, and jawless fishes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S3</ext-link>). Thus the mechanism underlying the &#x02212;6-nm &#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> shift in the gerbil may have evolved independently in multiple vertebrate lineages. Indeed, the S134A replacement may also explain tuning in the cave fish, where a reported shift from 564 nm to 558 nm could not be fully explained by the five critical sites (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The second replacement, A48T, was only seen in hedgehog (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S3</ext-link>).</p><p>While our results from the gerbil and elephant-shrew M/LWS reveal a possible link between molecular adaptations and ecological shifts, their daylight color vision is also mediated by SWS1, and possibly by RH1 pigment under mesopic conditions (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). To gain a more complete picture of visual phenotypes in these taxa, we also expressed these two pigments in vitro. We found that both of the SWS1 pigments are ultraviolet sensitive (&#x003bb;<sub>max</sub> 360 and 359 nm, respectively) and that RH1 has near-identical sensitivities (502 and 503 nm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). Moreover, neither SWS1 nor RH1 shows clear changes since the ancestral state (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). We thus conclude that parallel transitions in color vision range of these two highly divergent mammals have been driven by functionally convergent changes in their M/LWS opsins, and may reflect ecological or temporal convergence on similar photic niches.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p content-type="flushleft">To interrogate reported shifts in M/LWS spectral sensitivity in rodents (Rodentia, Euarchontoglires) and some lineages of Afrotheria, we expressed pigments in vitro using published sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Dataset S1</ext-link>) and directly measured spectral sensitivity following previous experimental protocols (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). We confirmed extreme phenotypes by repeating these steps based on either newly generated sequences (Damaraland mole-rat and gerbil) or additional published sequence from elephant-shrew (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Datasets S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">S2</ext-link>). For the latter two taxa, we also determined the phenotypes for SWS1 and RH1 pigments.</p><p>To elucidate the molecular basis of phenotypic change in the Rodentia and Afrotheria clades, we generated variants of ancestral pigments (A to E in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>) in which we introduced one or more of the derived residues by PCR-based site-directed mutagenesis (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). We identified more critical sites and screened for these in other vertebrate species in National Center for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" xlink:show="new">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>).</p><sec id="s2"><title>Data Availability.</title><p>All data discussed are available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">Datasets S1&#x02013;S3</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><label>Supplementary File</label><media xlink:href="pnas.2002235117.sd01.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><label>Supplementary File</label><media xlink:href="pnas.2002235117.sd02.xlsx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><label>Supplementary File</label><media xlink:href="pnas.2002235117.sd03.txt"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank R. Crouch (Medical University of South Carolina) and L. Neuhold (NIH) for 11-<italic>cis</italic>-retinal, and C. Faulkes for providing DNA. This study was funded by grants awarded to Y.L. by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant 31601855) and Shaanxi Normal University, and European Research Council Starting Grant 310482 to S.J.R.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no competing interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Data deposition: Data related to this work have been deposited in GenBank (accession nos. <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MT024768" specific-use="dataset is-supplemented-by" xlink:show="new">MT024768</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MT024769" specific-use="dataset is-supplemented-by" xlink:show="new">MT024769</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains supporting information online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>W. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Molecular ecology and adaptation of visual photopigments in craniates</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>3121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3158</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22650357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emerling</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Spectral shifts of mammalian ultraviolet-sensitive pigments (short wavelength-sensitive opsin 1) are associated with eye length and photic niche evolution</article-title>. <source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>282</volume>, <fpage>20151817</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Inactivation of cone-specific phototransduction genes in rod monochromatic cetaceans</article-title>. <source>Front. Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Visual opsin diversity in sharks and rays</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>827</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31770430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radlwimmer</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>The molecular genetics and evolution of red and green color vision in vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>1697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1710</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11545071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Evolutionary renovation of L/M opsin polymorphism confers a fruit discrimination advantage to ateline New World monkeys</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1812</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24612406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Molecular data support an early shift to an intermediate-light niche in the evolution of Mammals</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1134</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29462332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Vuuren</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Coalescence methods reveal the impact of vicariance on the spatial genetic structure of <italic>Elephantulus edwardii</italic> (Afrotheria, Macroscelidea)</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2692</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17594439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Home-range sizes of social groups of Mongolian gerbils <italic>Meriones unguiculatus</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Arid Environ.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennie</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Biogeography of time partitioning in mammals</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>13727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13732</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekharan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morokuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>Color vision: &#x0201c;OH-site&#x0201d; rule for seeing red and green</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>10706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10712</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22663599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faggionato</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <article-title>A simple method for studying the molecular mechanisms of ultraviolet and violet reception in vertebrates</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27001075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <article-title>Scotopic rod vision in tetrapods arose from multiple early adaptive shifts in the rate of retinal release</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>12627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12628</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31182589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>