<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23555726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-31504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Species Extinction</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Systematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Phylogenetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobiology</subject><subject>Vertebrate Paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Phylogenetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Molecular Phylogeny of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> Reassigns the Extinct Mammalian Order &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019;</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Molecular Phylogeny of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Computational and Evolutionary Biology, Faculty of Life Sciences, Manchester Institute of Biotechnology, Manchester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Turvey</surname><given-names>Samuel T.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Zoological Society of London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>m.buckley@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MB. Performed the experiments: MB. Analyzed the data: MB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MB. Wrote the paper: MB.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e59614</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Michael Buckley</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Michael Buckley</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Madagascar is well known for its diverse fauna and flora, being home to many species not found anywhere else in the world. However, its biodiversity in the recent past included a range of extinct enigmatic fauna, such as elephant birds, giant lemurs and dwarfed hippopotami. The &#x02018;Malagasy aardvark&#x02019; (<italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>) has remained one of Madagascar&#x02019;s least well-understood extinct species since its discovery in the 19<sup>th</sup> century. Initially considered a close relative of the aardvark (<italic>Orycteropus</italic>) within the order Tubulidentata, more recent morphological analyses challenged this placement on the grounds that the identifiably derived traits supporting this allocation were adaptations to digging rather than shared ancestry. Because the skeletal evidence showed many morphological traits diagnostic of different eutherian mammal orders, they could not be used to resolve its closest relatives. As a result, the genus was tentatively assigned its own taxonomic order &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019;, yet how this order relates to other eutherian mammal orders remains unclear despite numerous morphological investigations. This research presents the first known molecular sequence data for <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>, obtained from the bone protein collagen (I), which places the &#x02018;Malagasy aardvark&#x02019; as more closely related to tenrecs than aardvarks. More specifically, <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> was recovered within the order Tenrecoidea (golden moles and tenrecs) within Afrotheria, suggesting that the taxonomic order &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019; is obsolete. This research highlights the potential for collagen sequencing in investigating the phylogeny of extinct species as a viable alternative to ancient DNA (aDNA) sequencing, particularly in cases where aDNA cannot be recovered.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by NERC &#x00026; Wellcome Trust. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The island of Madagascar had a wide range of enigmatic Quaternary fauna that are now extinct, including &#x02018;giants&#x02019; (giant lemurs, giant fossa, elephant birds) and &#x02018;dwarfs&#x02019; (dwarf and pygmy hippopotami). The variations in size are considered an evolutionary response to insularisation <xref rid="pone.0059614-VanderGeer1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, but such changes do not usually obscure their ancestry because many morphological characteristics remain recognisable. However, the &#x02018;Malagasy aardvark&#x02019; (<italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>) is one of the few recently extinct Madagascan mammals that remains poorly understood and its phylogenetic placement within eutherian mammals unclear <xref rid="pone.0059614-Lamberton1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Patterson2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> despite being discovered over one hundred years ago <xref rid="pone.0059614-Filhol1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>The first known collected specimen of this unique digging creature was found at Belo in western Madagascar but remained poorly described <xref rid="pone.0059614-Filhol1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> until French palaeontologist Charles Lamberton subsequently excavated sites in central and southern Madagascar in the early 20<sup>th</sup> century. Lamberton <xref rid="pone.0059614-Lamberton1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> recognized that <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> displayed the greatest number of resemblances to aardvarks, but subsequently described a series of features strikingly different from tubulidentates, noting that these other features were more akin to those in pangolins, others to armadillos and anteaters and ultimately proposed several hypotheses. These included that it is 1) a &#x02018;palaeontological chimera&#x02019; composed of characteristics to distantly related mammals; 2) it is representative of a single type of mammal showing convergently evolved characteristics of distantly related mammals with uncertain affinity; or 3) it is a member of a deep mammalian lineage that, isolated by insularisation, retained ancestral traits that have since been lost in derivative lineages facing more intense selection pressures. Several further studies accepted <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as a tubulidentate, but also remained uncertain as to its phylogenetic placement <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacInnes1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Horovitz1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In the 1970s, Patterson <xref rid="pone.0059614-Patterson1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Patterson2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> concluded that the hypodigm of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> was indeed only from one type of mammal, and was confident in its systematic position within Tubulidentata considering comparisons with xenarthrans as phylogenetically distracting. Throughout most of the early 20<sup>th</sup> century, it was regarded as an &#x02018;edentate&#x02019; (the former grouping that included Tubulidentata with Pholidota, Cingulata and Pilosa) or more specifically as a tubulidentate and therefore most closely related to the extant aardvark (<italic>Orycteropus</italic>; hence its chosen genus name).</p><p>However, towards the end of the 20<sup>th</sup> century, this association was challenged on the grounds that many of the identifiably derived traits of the skeleton of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>, particularly those associated with scratch-digging, are shared not only by aardvarks but a number of other mammalian groups, including the armadillos (Dasypodidae), pangolins (Manidae), anteaters (Myrmecophagidae), and many others <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Of the few derived traits of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> that had no obvious connection with digging, the ones that could be adequately documented were also found not to be unique to aardvarks but instead sharing traits with various groups from &#x02018;Condylarthra&#x02019;, a paraphyletic grouping within the ungulates <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, no clear relationships between <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> and any other group within the ungulates could be confidently identified. Rather than making <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> the only recent mammal without a recognised order, a new order was created for it termed &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019; <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Ordinal-level placements for recently extinct eutherian mammals is not usually difficult, but the variety of morphological characteristics for <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> made it difficult to ascertain which of the apparently derived features document its true affinity <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p>Towards the beginning of the 21<sup>st</sup> century were the first phylogenies to include <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> that sampled widely across mammals <xref rid="pone.0059614-Horovitz1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-Asher1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Asher2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Even these more recent analyses, some of which used combined morphological and molecular data for extant species but only morphological data for extinct species, could not confidently reconstruct the phylogeny of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0059614-Asher1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Asher2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, more often than not placing it next to <italic>Orycteropus</italic> albeit with little support. Although more recent molecular studies on extant species has changed our understanding of phylogenetic relationships among eutherian mammals, such as the pseudoungulates (tubulidentates and the paenungulates Hyracoidea, Sirenia and Proboscidea) <xref rid="pone.0059614-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Seiffert1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, the confident placement of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> has remained elusive.</p><p>With novel methods in extracting molecular sequence data from fossils, particularly the sequencing of collagen using soft-ionization mass spectrometry <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Schweitzer1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, the various hypotheses for <italic>Plesiorycteropus&#x02019;</italic> phylogenetic placement can be re-investigated. Given the recent revisions in systematics using molecular sequence data <xref rid="pone.0059614-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Stanhope1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, Lamberton&#x02019;s &#x02018;edentate&#x02019; hypothesis <xref rid="pone.0059614-Lamberton1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> could be considered to place <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as more closely related to any of the former &#x02018;Edentata&#x02019; group including the aardvarks, armadillos, anteaters or pangolins; Patterson&#x02019;s tubulidentate hypothesis <xref rid="pone.0059614-Patterson2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> would specifically have <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> and <italic>Orycteropus</italic> forming a monophyletic group with <italic>Orycteropus</italic>; whereas MacPhee&#x02019;s &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019; hypothesis <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> would have <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> placed separate from all known orders, and not most closely related to Tubulidentata. To resolve the molecular phylogeny of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>, sequence data was obtained for bone type 1 collagen from the fossil specimen and compared with all previously hypothesized closest relatives.</p><p>In brief, mass spectrometry is an analytical technique in which molecules are converted to gaseous ions that are subsequently separated in a mass spectrometer and detected. &#x02018;Soft-ionization&#x02019; techniques are where the evaporation and ionisation of the molecules into the gaseous phase are carried out without extensive fragmentation, and thus peptides can be analysed (sequenced) without breaking apart into constituent amino acids. The two most commonly used soft-ionization techniques are Matrix Assisted Laser Desorption Ionization (MALDI) and Electrospray Ionization (ESI) <xref rid="pone.0059614-ElAneed1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, which are linked to various types of mass analyser (e.g., Time of Flight (ToF)) and an ion detector. In a typical &#x02018;shotgun proteomics&#x02019; experiment, mixtures of proteins extracted from a sample are collectively digested into fragments (peptides) using a protease (commonly the enzyme trypsin). The peptides are then ionized and their mass-to-charge ratio (<italic>m/z</italic>) determined (in MALDI peptides are most often singly charged, whereas in ESI they more commonly exist in multiple charge states) producing &#x02018;MS spectra&#x02019;. These peptides can then be further fragmented into smaller peptide fragments and these fragment ions are further analysed by the mass analyzer and recorded as &#x02018;MS/MS spectra&#x02019; (also known as &#x02018;MS2 spectra&#x02019; or &#x02018;tandem MS spectra&#x02019;). These MS/MS spectra are then either sequenced manually, or compared with the expected fragmentation patterns of known amino acid sequences within a given protein sequence database (e.g., UniProt) using a specialist search engine (e.g., Mascot), the &#x02018;ion scores&#x02019; being indicative of the relative quality of the sequence match.</p><p>&#x02018;Shotgun proteomics&#x02019; techniques are ideal for the analysis of ancient samples because typical protein isolation techniques, such as gel electrophoresis, are often rendered ineffective due to protein degradation. This is because collagen, making up approximately 90% of the total protein in bone, progressively degrades in a way that produces a vast range of collagen fragments that are unpredictable in size <xref rid="pone.0059614-Collins1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, and so smear through a polyacrylamide gel; this smearing effect is commonly noted in collagen extracted from archaeological bone <xref rid="pone.0059614-Tuross1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Dobberstein1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Their unpredictable range of biochemical properties also negates suitable isolation by many other separation techniques. Sequencing by soft-ionization mass spectrometry now allows us the ability to infer evolutionary relationships from long extinct organisms much deeper into the past than previously thought possible and although the claims of protein sequence retrieval from dinosaur fossils <xref rid="pone.0059614-Asara1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> remain controversial <xref rid="pone.0059614-BuckleyMWalker1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Kaye1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, their survival in Early Pleistocene remains (&#x0223c;1.5 Ma) from temperate climes <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Palmqvist1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> at much greater lengths of time than aDNA <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley3" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> is widely accepted.</p><p>Several proteins, such as albumin and osteocalcin, have been investigated in fossil material as potential alternatives for obtaining phylogenetic information <xref rid="pone.0059614-Tuross2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Huq1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, but collagen (I) is by far the most abundant protein in bone and, because of its highly-insoluble and stable structure, is the most likely protein to be found in fossilised tissues. However, it initially received much less attention than other proteins due to its highly repetitive Gly-Xaa-Yaa amino acid sequence (where Xaa and Yaa can be any amino acid but most frequently Proline and Hydroxyproline respectively). It is a fibrous protein of which the basic unit is made up of two &#x003b1;1(I) chains and a genetically distinct &#x003b1;2(I) chain, which contain an uninterrupted triple helical domain (&#x0223c;1000 amino acid residues per chain) flanked by short non-helical peptides. Although type I collagen has a highly repetitive amino acid sequence to maintain its triple helical structure, recent studies have shown that this motif is only closely adhered to in one of its two genetically distinct alpha chains (the &#x003b1;1 (I) chain), the other (&#x003b1;2(I)) being much more variable and can offer sequence specificity to at least the genus level <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley4" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> and can produce a good phylogenetic signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Because collagen is also known to survive greater periods of time than ancient DNA (aDNA) <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley3" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> to the extent that it has been reported in Mesozoic dinosaur fossils <xref rid="pone.0059614-Schweitzer1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-Asara1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, it is an ideal target for molecular phylogenies of extinct taxa. In this study we use collagen sequences as a viable alternative to aDNA sequencing, which suffers greater contamination issues and requirements of more specialist laboratory arrangements, to place the fossil species <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as a pioneering example of the application of proteomics techniques to palaeobiology.</p><fig id="pone-0059614-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic analysis of 25 concatenated collagen &#x003b1;1 (I) and &#x003b1;2 (I) sequences taken from the Ensembl Genome Browser.</title><p>Maximum Likelihood analyses produce a phylogenetic signal in good agreement with previously published genomic data (e.g. <xref rid="pone.0059614-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Stanhope1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>). Branch lengths are reported as the mean number of changes per site, bootstrap support is labelled and chicken (<italic>Gallus gallus</italic>) used as the outgroup.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059614.g001"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Samples</title><p>Protein sequencing analyses were carried out on sub-fossil specimens of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as well as modern samples of postulated close relatives. The sub-fossil <italic>Plesiorycteropus madagascariensis</italic> sample was drilled from femur specimen Oxford University Museum (OUM) 14395, which was collected by Paul Methuen from Antolambiby, Madagascar and presented to the Oxford University Museum of Natural History in 1911. A modern bone specimen aardvark (<italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>) was also obtained from OUM. Additional modern bone specimens obtained from University Museum of Zoology Cambridge (UMZC) included Sunda pangolin (<italic>Manis javanica</italic>) (UMZC E.1308), tamandua (<italic>Tamandua tetradactyla</italic>) (UMZC E.583), giant anteater (<italic>Myrmecophaga tridactyla</italic>) (UMZC E.562), hairy armadillo (<italic>Chaeotophractus villosus</italic>) (UMZC E.1062), golden mole (<italic>Ambylosomus hottentotus</italic>) (NFC-2), greater hedgehog tenrec (<italic>Setifer setosus</italic>) (UMZC 2011.2.2) and rock hyrax (<italic>Procavia capensis</italic>) (UMZC_H.4891.C). A skin cut from modern elephant shrew (<italic>Petrodromus tetradactylus</italic>) (A.533) was also obtained from Manchester Museum. LC-MS data for American mastodon (<italic>Mammut americanum</italic>) was taken from a previous publication <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Protein Extraction and MS Analysis</title><p>Soluble proteins were extracted from modern and fossil samples by agitation in 0.6 M hydrochloric acid (HCl) for 4 h and exchanged into 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate using ultrafiltration (30 kDa molecular weight cut-off (MWCO)). The proteins were then digested by trypsin (37&#x000b0;C for 18 h), acidified to 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) and further purified and concentrated by C18 ziptip following <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Peptide Mass Fingerprints (PMFs) were then obtained by MALDI-ToF-MS and MS/MS spectra acquired for selected peptides. MS/MS spectra were obtained with approximately 500 ion counts for the precursor ion followed by 3000&#x02013;5000 ion counts for the fragment ions and the peptide sequences interpreted manually. These were used to help create an initial local database that included sequences the species of interest where unknown sequence replaced with the consensus sequence. Digested samples were analysed by LC-MS/MS (Waters nanoAcquity Ultra Performance Liquid Chromatography (UPLC) instrument coupled to a Thermo Scientific Linear Trap Quadrupole (LTQ) Velos Dual Pressure mass spectrometer) on which the peptides were concentrated on a pre-column (20 mm&#x000d7;180 &#x000b5;m) then separated on a 1.7 &#x000b5;M Waters nanoAcquity BEH (Ethylene Bridged Hybrid) C18 analytical column (75 mm&#x000d7;250 &#x000b5;m i.d.), using a gradient from 99% buffer A (0.1% formic acid (FA) in H<sub>2</sub>O)/1% buffer B (0.1% FA in acetonitrile (ACN)) to 25% B in 45 min at 200 nL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Peptides were selected for fragmentation automatically by data dependent analysis. Proteomics data files were searched using Mascot against a local database that incorporates UniProt with sequences identified from MALDI-ToF/ToF-MS/MS using two missed cleavages, error tolerances of 0.5 Da (MS and MS/MS) using &#x02018;Error tolerant&#x02019; searches with the two (maximum allowed) variable modifications, oxidation of Proline (P) and Lysine (K) that search the Unimods database for further modifications that could occur as a result of amino acid substitution or amino acid modification during diagenesis. Following revision of the sequences from these results, the searches were carried out as normal searches but with pyro-glutamic acid, oxidation (P, K and Methionine (M)) and deamidation of asparagine (N) and glutamine (Q) modifications. LC-MS collagen peptide sequence matches were selected with a peptide ion score &#x0003e;40 and are listed with their respective ion scores in the Supplementary Information (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s004">Tables S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s011">S11</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Sequence Analysis</title><p>The collagen &#x003b1;1(I) and &#x003b1;2(I) sequences were concatenated and aligned with orthologues from 11 LC-MS datasets as well as 26 other species <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-BuckleyMWalker1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. In sites where isobaric residues (e.g., Isoleucine (I) and Leucine (L)) were present, the most common was used throughout for purposes of phylogenetic inference (listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s015">Text S1</xref>). Phylogenetic trees were created using PhyML v2.0.7 <xref rid="pone.0059614-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> (10,000 bootstrap generations, invariable sites fixed, with four substitution categories) and MrBayes <xref rid="pone.0059614-Huelsenbeck1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> with 1,000,000 bootstrap generations in four chains, first 20% of trees discarded, sampling frequency 1000, heated chain temperature 0.2, with 4 gamma rate variation categories in Geneious v5.5.6 with amino acid models set to Dayhoff. Neighbor-Net analysis was also carried out using the software SplitsTree 4 <xref rid="pone.0059614-Huson1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Bryant1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p>Digests of proteins extracted from a range of candidate phylogenetic neighbours were analysed by MALDI-ToF-MS producing collagen-dominated PMFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g002">Fig. 2</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). Prior to in depth LC-MS analyses, the <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> PMF was compared with those of other mammalian groups in order to identify some of the dominant peptides present that differed between the taxa, particularly the highly variable &#x02018;species biomarker&#x02019; peptides described previously <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-Buckley4" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. A greater similarity between <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> and tenrecs, golden moles and elephant shrews, and between aardvark and hyrax could be observed in these PMFs. However, to get robust statistical support, LC-MS sequencing and subsequent phylogenetic analysis was carried out. Selected peptides with sufficiently high peak intensities in the MALDI-ToF PMFs were analysed by MS/MS for sequence analysis (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g003">Fig. 3</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s002">Fig. S2</xref>) and these preliminary sequences were compiled into a local database and searched against using the more comprehensive LC-MS data obtained for each.</p><fig id="pone-0059614-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>MALDI-ToF-MS spectra of collagen digests from the sub-fossil &#x02018;malagasy aardvark&#x02019; <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> and modern specimens.</title><p>The peptide mass fingerprints (PMFs) show that the quality of the collagen extracted from the fossil is as good as from modern specimens (from top to bottom; aardvark (<italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>), <italic>Plesiorycteropus sp.,</italic> rock hyrax (<italic>Procavia capensis</italic>) and greater hedgehog tenrec (<italic>Setifer setosus</italic>)). Peaks marked &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; represent some of the most variable homologous peptides manually sequenced (Fig. 3 &#x00026; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). A greater similarity between peptide <italic>m/z</italic> values can be seen between <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> and tenrec than any other species sampled.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059614.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone-0059614-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Example tandem MS spectra of three homologous peptides.</title><p>The spectra are from peptide COL1A2<sub>495&#x02013;509</sub> (peak &#x02018;&#x003b1;&#x02019; in Fig. 2) with precursor (MH+) ions at (from top to bottom) <italic>m/z</italic> 1453 (elephants, pangolin anteater and tamandua), 1463 (hyrax and aardvark) and 1477 (armadillos and all afrosoricids including the extinct <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic>). Labeling of fragment ions (inset) follows <xref rid="pone.0059614-Roepstorff1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, underline represents hydroxylation site, red text highlights amino acids that differ from the inset (elephant, anteater &#x00026; pangolin) sequence. Isobaric amino acids (I/L) were estimated based on conserved DNA sequence data where possible; for sites that have more than one isobaric amino acid present, the most abundant was used (see Supplementary Information).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059614.g003"/></fig><p>Confident peptide sequence matches (ion score &#x0003e;40) from the LC-MS analyses were manually aligned and analysed by Maximum Likelihood (ML; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>) and NeighbourNet analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). Even in cases where a high level of peptide match confidence is assumed, the tree topology with regards the species analysed in this study remained consistent where <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> always groups with tenrecs within the order Tenrecoidea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059614.s003">Fig. S3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0059614-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic analyses of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> collagen (I) sequences obtained by LC-MS in comparison to previously postulated closest relatives.</title><p>The results are from A) Maximum Likelihood (rooted to <italic>Gallus</italic>; only bootstrap support &#x0003e;50 is shown) and B) Neighbor-Net analysis in SplitzTree4. <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> consistently forms a monophyletic group with the tenrecs within the order Tenrecoidea, forming a sister group to the aardvark (tubulidentates), rock hyrax, and the proboscideans. Silhouette denotes sequences obtained from LC-MS data; scale shows average amino acid substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0059614.g004"/></fig><p>One major limitation of protein (peptide) sequencing by soft-ionization mass spectrometry relies on the matching of peptide fragments ions observed in tandem mass spectra with those predicted from a given database. Thus for fragment ion mass spectra deriving from extinct taxa that do not have closely-related representative species, levels of confidence need to be placed on inference from such data. In the case of collagen (I) analyses, the typical sequence coverage for unconstrained searches is approximately 70&#x02013;80%, which reduces to &#x0223c;50% when appropriate (&#x0223c;40) ion scores are used. Thus with increasing confidence thresholds in peptide matching using conventional approaches (e.g., Mascot algorithms) there is an observable increase in the amount of missing sequence information.</p><p>The sequence analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) consistently place <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> within Afrotheria, and more specifically as being more closely related to tenrecs than any other previously postulated species (Bootstrap score&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;81). Because it consistently forms a monophyletic grouping with tenrecs within a clade that includes the golden moles, these results not only support the order Tenrecoidea (golden moles and tenrecs) but include <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as a new member of this order. The close relationship consistently observed between hyracoids and tubulidentates has long been considered on morphological grounds <xref rid="pone.0059614-LeGrosClark1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> and supported by early molecular systematic studies using proteins <xref rid="pone.0059614-Rainey1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-DeJong1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> but differs from more recent nucleotide data showing closer affinities between hyracoids and proboscideans <xref rid="pone.0059614-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. With the exclusion of Tubulidentata, it is the Afroinsectivora (Tenrecoidea+Macroscelidea) that is consistently monophyletic, not Afroinsectiphilia (Tenrecoidea+Tubulidentata). The placement of the pangolins (Pholidota) as closely related to Carnivora (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), as well as the grouping of the xenarthrans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059614-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) is consistent with other molecular sequence data <xref rid="pone.0059614-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Stanhope1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, further supporting the use of proteomics-derived collagen sequence data. Interestingly, both the Maximum Likelihood and Neighbour-Net analyses recovered the xenarthrans as more basal than afrotherians. The only discrepancy between these phylogenetic methods lies in the higher-level groupings (e.g., super-order), in which the ML methods do not recover the euarchontoglires as forming a monophyletic clade (Euarchonta and Laurasiatheria forming a sister group to Glires), which is recovered with the NeighborNet analyses.</p><p>However, the results clearly show that <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> is more closely related to tenrecoids than to tubulidentates, and that because its collagen sequence confidently places it within the order Tenrecoidea, the molecular phylogeny obtained does not support the creation of the taxonomic order &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019; that was proposed in the mid 1990s <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Although <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> retained some morphological characteristics from its earlier common ancestor with aardvarks, characters such as its relatively small eyes and adaptations to climbing <xref rid="pone.0059614-Lamberton1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> are consistent with other members of Tenrecoidea. Given that its resolved affinity is to Tenrecoidea, particularly close to the tenrecs, which can occupy a diverse range of environments including terrestrial, fossorial, arboreal and aquatic ones <xref rid="pone.0059614-Poux1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, it is perhaps not surprising to find this much larger extinct form that acquired a wide range of morphological attributes that has made it so difficult to place for so long.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The inconclusive results from multiple investigations over the past one hundred years <xref rid="pone.0059614-Lamberton1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Patterson2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0059614-MacPhee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0059614-Asher2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> illustrate how difficult it is to place isolated taxa displaying many morphological novelties but few obvious synapomorphies. This problem can occur at any hierarchical level, but it is most prevalent in situations where higher taxa are being compared, which has obvious implications for the positioning of <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> as well as many other extinct taxa. These results suggest that this mysterious <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> is likely a form of &#x02018;giant&#x02019; tenrec, a diverse family that are now only represented by much smaller taxa. The results presented here demonstrate that fossil collagen (I) can be used to resolve such questions of taxonomy and, given its longevity over millions of years, has enormous potential to build a more complete Tree of Life than possible with DNA sequencing alone.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s4"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>MALDI-ToF-MS spectra showing the PMFs of collagen digests extracted from elephant shrew (</bold>
<bold><italic>Petrodromus tetradactylus</italic></bold>
<bold>), golden mole (</bold>
<bold><italic>Ambylosomus hottentotus</italic></bold>
<bold>), Sunda pangolin (</bold>
<bold><italic>Manis javanica</italic></bold>
<bold>), anteater (</bold>
<bold><italic>Myrmecophaga tridactyla</italic></bold>
<bold>) and hairy armadillo (</bold>
<bold><italic>Chaeotophractus villosus</italic></bold>
<bold>).</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Tandem MS spectra of nine homologous peptides with precursor ions at </bold>
<bold><italic>m/z</italic></bold>
<bold> 2161 (Sunda pangolin), 2147 (anteaters), 2129 (</bold>
<bold><italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic></bold>
<bold>), 2131 (hairy armadillo), 2089 (aardvark), 2073 (rock hyrax), 2145 (golden mole), 2161 (elephant shrew) and 2115 (elephantids) split into two windows of </bold>
<bold><italic>m/z</italic></bold>
<bold> range 200&#x02013;1100 (A) and 1100&#x02013;2000 (B).</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Bayesian analysis of the 37 collagen sequences used in this study rooted to </bold>
<bold><italic>Gallus</italic></bold>
<bold> including the LC-MS-derived sequences.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s004"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Manis</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s004.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s005"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Orycteropus</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s005.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s006"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Tamandua</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s006.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s007"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Petrodromus</italic></bold>
<bold> skin acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s007.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s008"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Ambylosomus</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s008.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s009"><label>Table S6</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Chaetophractus</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s009.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s010"><label>Table S7</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s010.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s011"><label>Table S8</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Setifer</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s011.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s012"><label>Table S9</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Procavia</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s012.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s013"><label>Table S10</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Myrmecaphaga</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s013.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s014"><label>Table S11</label><caption><p>
<bold>Mascot results for </bold>
<bold><italic>Mammut</italic></bold>
<bold> bone acid-insoluble protein digest LC-MS data.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s014.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s015"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Collagen (I) sequence accession numbers.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s015.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0059614.s016"><label>Text S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Concatenated collagen sequences.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0059614.s016.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was made possible through permission to sample the <italic>Plesiorycteropus</italic> specimens in the Oxford Museum of Natural History archive, given by Malgosia Nowak-Kemp, as well as samples of modern specimens from the Cambridge Natural History Museum and the Manchester Museum for which I thank Robert Asher and Henry McGhie for time in identifying numerous tissue samples for analysis. The author would like to thank the Michael Barber Centre for Mass Spectrometry, the Manchester Life Sciences Proteomics Core Facility, Julian Selley for bioinformatics support and Sarah Howard, William Sellers, Terry Brown, Robert Asher and Ross MacPhee for reviewing early forms of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0059614-VanderGeer1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van der Geer A, Lyras G, de Vos J, Dermitzakis M (2010) Evolution of Island Mammals. Wiley-Blackwell: Oxford, UK.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Lamberton1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lamberton C (1946) Contribution a la connaissance de la faune de Madagascar. Bull. Acad. Malgache 25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-MacInnes1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>MacInnes</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1956</year>) <article-title>Fossil Tubulidentata from East Africa. Foss. Mamm</article-title>. <source>Africa</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Lavocat1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lavocat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>Tubulidentata</article-title>. <source>Trait de paleontology</source>
<volume>6(2)</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Thewissen1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Thewissen</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Cephalic evidence for the affinities of Tubulidentata</article-title>. <source>Mammalia</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Horovitz1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Horovitz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Eutherian mammal systematics and the origins of South American ungulates as based on postcranial osteology. Bull. Carn. Mus. Nat. His</article-title>. <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Patterson1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>The fossil aardvarks (Mammalia: Tubulidentata). Bull. Mus. Comp. Zool</article-title>. <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Patterson2"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Patterson B (1978) in <italic>Evolution of African Mammals,</italic> eds Maglio VJ, Cooke HS (Cambridge, Mass; Harvard Univ. Press), 268&#x02013;278.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Filhol1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Filhol</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1895</year>) <article-title>Observations concernant les mammiferes contemporains des Aepyornis a Madagascar. Bull. Mus. Hist</article-title>. <source>Nat., Paris</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-MacPhee1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">MacPhee R (1994) Morphology, adaptations, and relationships of Plesiorycteropus, and a diagnosis of a new order of eutherian mammals. Bull. Am. Mus. Nat. His. 220.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Asher1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novacek</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Relationships of endemic African mammals and their fossil relatives based on morphological and molecular evidence. J. Mam. Evol</article-title>. <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Asher2"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A web-database of mammalian morphology and a reanalysis of placental phylogeny. BMC Evol. Biol</article-title>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Murphy1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Resolution of the early placental mammal radiation using Bayesian phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>294</volume>: <fpage>2348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Stanhope1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Molecular evidence for multiple origins of Insectivora and for a new order of endemic African insectivore mammals</article-title>. <source>PNAS USA</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>9967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9972</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Seiffert1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Seiffert</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A new estimate of afrotherian phylogeny based on simultaneous analysis of genomic, morphological and fossil evidence. BMC Evol. Biol</article-title>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>224</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Buckley1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mammoth and Mastodon collagen sequences; survival and utility. Geochim. Cosmochim</article-title>. <source>Acta</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>2007</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2016</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Schweitzer1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Organ</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biomolecular characterization and protein sequences of the Campanian hadrosaur B. canadensis</article-title>. <source>Science 1;324</source>
<volume>(5927)</volume>: <fpage>626</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-ElAneed1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>El-Aneed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banoub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mass Spectrometry, Review of the Basics: Electrospray, MALDI and Commonly Used Mass Analyzers</article-title>. <source>Applied Spectroscopy Reviews 44</source>
<volume>(3)</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Steen1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The ABC&#x02019;s (and XYZ&#x02019;s) of peptide sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 5</source>
<volume>(9)</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>711</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Collins1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Collins MJ, Riley MS, Child AM, Turner-Walker G (1995) A basic mathematical simulation of the chemical degradation of ancient collagen. J. Archaeol. Sci. 22, 175&#x02013;183.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Tuross1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tuross N, Eyre DR, Holtrop ME, Glimcher MJ, Hare PE (1980) Collagen in fossil bones. New York: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Dobberstein1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dobberstein R, Collins M, Craig O, Taylor G, Penkman K, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2009) Archaeological collagen: Why worry about collagen diagenesis? Archaeological and Anthropological Sciences. 1, 31&#x02013;42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Asara1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Asara</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freimark</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Protein sequences from mastodon and tyrannosaurus tex revealed by mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Science 316</source>
<volume>(5822)</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-BuckleyMWalker1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley M. Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comment on &#x0201c;Protein Sequences from Mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex Revealed by Mass Spectrometry&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>319</volume>: <fpage>33c</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33c</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Bern1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phinney</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reanalysis of Tyrannosaurus rex Mass Spectra. J. Prot. Res</article-title>. <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>4328</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Kaye1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaugler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawlowicz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dinosaurian Soft Tissues Interpreted as Bacterial Biofilms</article-title>. <source>PlosONE</source>
<volume>3(7)</volume>: <fpage>e2808</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Buckley2"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Collagen survival and its use for species identification in Holocene-lower Pleistocene bone fragments from British archaeological and palaeontological sites</article-title>. <source>Antiqua</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>e1</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Palmqvist1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Palmqvist</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grocke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arribas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Paleoecological reconstruction of a lower Pleistocene large mammal community using biogeochemical (<sup>13</sup>C, <sup>15</sup>N, <sup>18</sup>O, Sr:Zn) and ecomorphological approaches</article-title>. <source>Paleobiology</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Buckley3"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penkman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotherstrom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comparing the survival of osteocalcin and mtDNA in archaeological bone from four European sites. J. Archaeol. Sci</article-title>. <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1764</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Tuross2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tuross</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Albumin preservation in the Taima-taima mastodon skeleton</article-title>. <source>Applied Geochemistry</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Huq1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Partial amino acid sequence of osteocalcin from an extinct species of ratite bird</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry International</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2222494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Buckley4"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas-Oates</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Species identification of bone collagen using Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization Mass Spectrometry. Rapid Comm. Mass Spectrom</article-title>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3854</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Guindon1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood. Syst. Biol</article-title>. <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Huelsenbeck1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>755</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Huson1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Application of phylogenetic networks in evolutionary studies molecular biology and evolution</article-title>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Bryant1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Neighbor-Net: An agglomerative method for the construction of phylogenetic networks</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Roepstorff1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Roepstorff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fohlman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Proposal for a common nomenclature for sequence ions in mass spectra of peptides. Biomed. Mass Spectrom</article-title>. <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-LeGrosClark1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Le Gros Clark WE, Sonntag F (1926) A monograph of Orycteropus afer. III. Proc. Zool. Soc. London: 445&#x02013;485.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Rainey1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rainey</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarich</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Magor</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Sirenian macromolecular systematic including the extinct Steller&#x02019;s sea cow (Hydrodamalis gigas)</article-title>. <source>Naturwissensh</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>588</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-DeJong1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zweers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Relationship of aardvark to elephants, hyraxes and sea cows from &#x003b1;-crystallin sequences</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>292</volume>: <fpage>538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7254349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0059614-Poux1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Poux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vences</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Moecular phylogeny and divergence times of Malagasy tenrecs: Influence of data partitioning and taxon sampling on data analyses. BMC Evol Biol</article-title>. <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>