<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open-access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pgen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plge</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosgen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16848642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0020109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PLGE-RA-0016R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plge-02-07-12</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolution</subject><subject>Genetics/Comparative Genomics</subject><subject>Genetics/Chromosome Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Vertebrates</subject><subject>Mammals</subject><subject>Xenarthra</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Ancestral Eutherian Karyotype Is Present in Xenarthra</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Ancestral Eutherian Karyotype in Xenarthra</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svartman</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Gary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>Roscoe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Comparative Molecular Cytogenetics Core, Genetics Branch, National Cancer Institute-Frederick, Frederick, Maryland, United States of America</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Trask</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>svartmanm@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e109</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration, which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Molecular studies have led recently to the proposal of a new super-ordinal arrangement of the 18 extant Eutherian orders. From the four proposed super-orders, Afrotheria and Xenarthra were considered the most basal. Chromosome-painting studies with human probes in these two mammalian groups are thus key in the quest to establish the ancestral Eutherian karyotype. Although a reasonable amount of chromosome-painting data with human probes have already been obtained for Afrotheria, no Xenarthra species has been thoroughly analyzed with this approach. We hybridized human chromosome probes to metaphases of species <italic>(Dasypus novemcinctus, Tamandua tetradactyla,</italic> and <italic>Choloepus hoffmanii)</italic> representing three of the four Xenarthra families<italic>.</italic> Our data allowed us to review the current hypotheses for the ancestral Eutherian karyotype, which range from 2<italic>n</italic> = 44 to 2<italic>n</italic> = 48. One of the species studied, the two-toed sloth <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 50), showed a chromosome complement strikingly similar to the proposed 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 ancestral Eutherian karyotype, strongly reinforcing it.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="synopsis"><title>Synopsis</title><p>Living mammals are classified into three major groups: monotremes, marsupials, and placental mammals or Eutherians, composed of 18 orders. Phylogenetic studies point to Afrotheria (a clade of six endemic African orders) or Xenarthra (armadillos, anteaters, and sloths, mostly found in Central and South America) as the most basal Eutherian group. One of the most daring aims of molecular cytogenetics in the past decade has been to establish the karyotype present in a common ancestor of all Eutherians. The approach used, cross-species chromosome painting, involves the use of probes from specific chromosomes or chromosome segments from one species, which are hybridized to metaphases of another species, highlighting regions of homology between both genomes. More than 60 species have already been analyzed with this method, and it is believed that the ancestral karyotype had 44, 46, or 48 chromosomes. The authors, using human chromosomes as probes to study three Xenarthra species, found that one of them, the two-toed sloth <named-content content-type="genus-species">Choloepus hoffmannii</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 50), has a karyotype strikingly similar to the proposed 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 ancestral Eutherian complement. This observation, besides reinforcing the hypothesized karyotype, suggests that Xenarthra may be at the root of the Eutherian tree.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Svartman M, Stone G, Stanyon R (2006) The ancestral Eutherian karyotype is present in Xenarthra. PLoS Genet 2(7): e109. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0020109">10.1371/journal.pgen.0020109</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Extensive molecular data on mammalian genomes have led recently to the proposal of a new phylogenetic tree for Eutherians, which encompasses four super-orders: Afrotheria (elephants, manatees, hyraxes, tenrecs, aardvark, and elephant shrews); Xenarthra (sloths, anteaters, and armadillos); Euarchontoglires (rodents and lagomorphs as a sister taxon to primates, flying lemurs, and tree shrews); and Laurasiatheria (cetaceans, artiodactyls, perissodactyls, carnivores, pangolins, bats, and insectivores) [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. At first very debated, the grouping of the 18 living placental mammalian orders into these four clades is rapidly approaching a consensus [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. One of the pivotal questions still remaining relates to the root of the placental tree. Either Xenarthra or Afrotheria, or the combination Xenarthra plus Afrotheria, could represent the first split from a common Eutherian ancestor (reviewed in [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]). Although Afrotheria has been favored as the first offshoot in the Eutherian tree [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], both Xenarthra and Afrotheria emerged around 100 million years ago (mya), within a short interval from each other [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This is also the time of the separation between South America, where Xenarthrans are endemic, and Africa, home to the Afrotheria. Therefore, a causal connection between the plate-tectonic events and the diversification of mammals has been proposed [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Extant Xenarthra (sloths, anteaters, and armadillos) are restricted to the Americas, mostly Central and South America. The 30 known living species are relicts of the once highly diversified Xenarthra that dominated the South American fauna from the late Cretaceous (80&#x02013;65 mya) until the late Tertiary (3&#x02013;2.5 mya), while South America was an isolated landmass. Xenarthrans were abundant until the Pleistocene (10,000 years ago), and more than 200 fossil genera have been reported [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Morphological and molecular studies support the monophyly of the group, which also extends to each of the four recognized extant families: Myrmecophagidae (four species of anteater), Bradypodidae (four species of three-toed sloth), Megalonychidae (two species of two-toed sloth), and Dasypodidae (about 20 species of armadillo) [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. According to molecular data estimates, the radiation of Xenarthra occurred around 65 mya, during the Cretaceous/Tertiary boundary. Armadillos, the most basal group of Xenarthra, diverged around 65 mya, followed by the divergence between anteaters and sloths around 55 mya [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Molecular data on Xenarthra are rapidly accumulating in the literature [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], but only scarce information is available on their chromosomes. Nineteen species had their karyotypes described [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], but only a few with banding techniques [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The reported diploid numbers range from 2<italic>n</italic> = 38 in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Tolypeutes matacus</named-content> to 2<italic>n</italic> = 64 in <italic>Dasypus novemcinctus, D</italic>. <italic>hybridus,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">Cyclopes didactyla</named-content> [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The first comparative study between karyotypes of different Xenarthra species using molecular cytogenetics has recently been published, and the rate of chromosome repatterning in Xenarthra was considered low [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Chromosome painting to establish the karyotype of a common ancestral Eutherian mammal has already been applied in 12 out of the 18 orders in the group. The proposed diploid numbers range from 2<italic>n</italic> = 44 to 2<italic>n</italic> = 50 [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The most recent studies suggest 2<italic>n</italic> = 44 [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], 2<italic>n</italic> = 46 [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Chromosome-painting studies in Afrotheria and Xenarthra, the most basal of the living Eutherians, are essential to establish the putative ancestral Eutherian complement. Some Afrotheria have already had their genomes analyzed by chromosome painting with human probes [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Data of comparative molecular cytogenetics in Xenarthra using human chromosomes as painting probes are restricted to very limited data for two species [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>In this study, we hybridized paints of all human chromosomes in species representing three of the four families of Xenarthra, and reevaluated the current hypotheses for the ancestral Eutherian karyotype based on our results.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>Some examples of human chromosome paints hybridized to the three Xenarthra species are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g001">Figure 1</xref>. The results of the chromosome painting with human probes in the three species are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0020109-t001">Table 1</xref>. The G-banded karyotype of the three species studied were mounted according to Jorge et al. [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and are presented with the corresponding human chromosome segments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g002">Figure 2</xref>
<italic>(D. novemcinctus</italic> and <italic>Tamandua tetradactyla)</italic> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g003">Figure 3</xref>A <italic>(Choloepus hoffmanii).</italic>
</p><fig id="pgen-0020109-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Partial Metaphases of <italic>D. novemcinctus, T. tetradactyla,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> after In Situ Hybridization with Human Chromosome&#x02013;Specific Probes</title><p>(A&#x02013;C) <italic>D. novemcinctus,</italic> (D&#x02013;F) <italic>T. tetradactyla,</italic> and (G&#x02013;I) <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content>. Two probes were used in each experiment, and the hybridizations were detected with avidin&#x02013;FITC (green) and antidigoxigenin&#x02013;rhodamine (red). The chromosomes were counterstained with DAPI, and the human chromosome probes used are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0020109.g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="pgen-0020109-t001" content-type="2col" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of Chromosome Painting with Human Probes in Xenarthra</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0020109.t001"/></table-wrap><p>The X chromosome of the three Xenarthra species hybridized with human chromosome X and showed a highly conserved G-banding pattern when compared to the human X chromosome, reinforcing its known conservation. No signals were obtained with human chromosome Y.</p><p>In the nine-banded armadillo <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 64; fundamental number [<italic>FN</italic>] = 78), chromosome painting resulted in 41 segments, and seven associations, or combinations of segments from two human chromosomes, were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g002">Figure 2</xref>A).</p><fig id="pgen-0020109-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>G-Banded Karyotypes of Female Nine-Banded Armadillo and Female Lesser Anteater</title><p>(A) Female nine-banded armadillo <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 64) and (B) female lesser anteater <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 54).</p><p>The correspondence to human chromosomes as revealed by chromosome painting is shown on the left of each chromosome. The question mark indicates questionable results. Some regions were not painted by any human probe and are probably composed of repetitive sequences (see text).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0020109.g002"/></fig><p>The karyotype of the lesser anteater <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 54; <italic>FN</italic> = 104) consists exclusively of biarmed chromosomes. Painting with human probes resulted in a total of 44 segments, and 15 associations were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g002">Figure 2</xref>B).</p><p>The two-toed sloth <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> is the species with the lowest diploid number (2<italic>n</italic> = 50; <italic>FN</italic> = 61). Owing to a heterozygous translocation between pairs 2 and 24, pair 2 was heteromorphic in the cells analyzed; this individual is thus trisomic for Chromosome 24. A total of 32 segments and six associations were detected with the human probes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g003">Figure 3</xref>A).</p><fig id="pgen-0020109-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The Karyotype of Hoffmann's Two-Toed Sloth (2<italic>n</italic> = 50) Closely Resembles the Proposed Eutherian Ancestral Karyotype (2<italic>n</italic> = 48)</title><p>(A) G-banded karyotype of a male <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 50) with the corresponding human chromosomes indicated to the left of each chromosome. (B) Diagram of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> chromosomes. (C) The proposed ancestral Eutherian karyotype (2<italic>n</italic> = 48) [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In (B) and (C), the corresponding human chromosomes are each represented by a different color, and their numbers are indicated at the bottom of each chromosome. The chromosomes are drawn only roughly to scale. In (C), the corresponding <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> chromosomes are indicated to the left of each ancestral chromosome. The asterisks and lines show the chromosomes that differ between the karyotypes of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> (CHO) and those proposed as ancestral (ANC) for Eutheria (CHO 14 and ANC 10q and 10p [black asterisks]; CHO 13 and 19 and ANC 8q [green asterisks]; and CHO 20 and 21 and ANC 7b/16p [red asterisks]).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0020109.g003"/></fig><p>It is interesting to note that some chromosome regions of the three Xenarthra species were not labeled by any of the human probes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g003">3</xref>A). These regions, which were either proximal (for instance <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> Chromosomes 25 and 30), distal (<named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> Chromosome 1 and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> Chromosome 7), or encompassed whole short arms (as with <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> Chromosomes 2 and 4, <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> Chromosome 12, and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> Chromosomes 3, 4, and 5), are very likely to represent repetitive sequences that are absent from the human genome.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The effort to establish the ancestral Eutherian karyotype relies on the concept of parsimony, according to which likely ancestral chromosomes are present in species of divergent Eutherian orders. There is a conspicuous lack of data from Xenarthra, one of the most basal mammalian groups, in the quest to establish the ancestral karyotype. Aiming to fill this gap, we conducted painting experiments with human chromosome&#x02013;specific probes in species representing three of the four major Xenarthra groups.</p><p>Richard et al. [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] previously reported results for ten human chromosomes (3, 7, 12, 14, 15, 16, 18, 21, 22, and the X chromosome) in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> metaphases. The armadillo chromosomes labeled were not specified, and three of the probes (human Chromosomes 7, 12, and 22) gave results that were questioned by Richard et al. In the three cases, only one signal was observed, while the same probes labeled two (human Chromosomes 7 and 22) or three (human Chromosome 12) autosomes in our sample. We obtained the same number of signals already reported for human Chromosomes 3, 14, 15, 16, 18, and the X chromosome [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], but we detected two signals for human Chromosome 21, instead of the single labeling described by Richard et al. [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Human Chromosome 1 was previously shown to be conserved in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and this was confirmed in our experiments.</p><p>Six human chromosome associations (human Chromosomes 3/21, 4/8, 7/16, 12/22 twice, 14/15, and 16/19) are agreed, by most authors, as having been present in the ancestral Eutherian karyotype. All of these syntenies were found in the three species of Xenarthra that we studied (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0020109-t001">Table 1</xref>). The associations human Chromosomes 3/21 and 14/15 were each disrupted in, respectively, <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g001">Figure 1</xref>F), suggesting that they underwent rearrangements in these species after the split from a common ancestor. In <italic>C. hoffmanii,</italic> no other syntenies besides the six already mentioned were found, and in <italic>D. novemcinctus,</italic> a single extra combination (human Chromosome 10/12) was identified. Human Chromosomes 9, 13, 17, 18, and 20 were found to be conserved in toto in the three Xenarthra species.</p><p>Although Xenarthra is widely accepted as a monophyletic group on morphological and molecular grounds, no common chromosome syntenies besides those considered present in the common Eutherian ancestral karyotype were found in the three species studied. Thus, there is an unusual absence of chromosome synapomorphic traits linking the three families that we studied. The only exception might be human Chromosome 8, believed to be disrupted into two blocks in a common Eutherian ancestral and found as three segments in both <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> and possibly also in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0020109-t001">Table 1</xref>). Additional experiments are needed to confirm this observation.</p><p>On the other hand, we observed a striking resemblance of Xenarthran complements to the proposed 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 ancestral Eutherian karyotype [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], particularly in the case of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 50) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g003">Figure 3</xref>B). In this species, 20 autosome pairs appear to be the same as the most recent hypothesis for the putative Eutherian ancestral karyotype with 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 (human Chromosomes 1, 2p, 2q, 3/21, 4/8p, 5, 6, 7a, 7b/16p, 9, 11, 12/22 twice, 13, 14/15, 16q/19q, 17, 18, 19p, and 20). The only differences are with regard to human Chromosome 10, considered as two blocks in the ancestral karyotype and kept intact in this species; human Chromosome 8q, which might be further disrupted in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmannii</named-content> resulting in a third signal for this chromosome; and an additional signal for human Chromosome 16, represented by <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> Chromosome 20 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0020109-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>D. novemcinctus,</italic> some of the putative ancestral Eutherian chromosomes are disrupted into further blocks (for instance, human Chromosomes 1, 3/21, 6, 7, and 11), which would account for its higher diploid number (2<italic>n</italic> = 64) in relation to an ancestral karyotype, but otherwise this chromosome complement is also very close to that considered to be the ancestral one.</p><p>
<named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> presents the most rearranged complement in relation to the ancestral karyotype, and was also reported as such when compared to other Xenarthra taxa [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this case, several rearrangements seem to have occurred, resulting in chromosome disruptions and new associations in relation to a common ancestral complement. This species presented two associations previously reported in Afrotheria (human Chromosomes 1/19 and 2/8). One of them, human Chromosome 1/19, was considered as a synapomorphic trait of Afrotheria [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and was postulated as ancestral to all Eutheria by Yang et al. [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Nevertheless, its occurrence in only one highly rearranged primate species [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] outside Afrotheria was considered insufficient to accept it as ancestral [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. As human Chromosome 1/19 was found only in one of the Xenarthrans herein analyzed, and it is likely to be a different association regarding the segments involved, we do not consider it as a probable ancestral Eutherian combination.</p><p>Human Chromosome 2/8 was absent in elephants, but was found in four other species of Afrotheria that were analyzed with chromosome painting [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It was thus considered a phylogenetic link between those species after the divergence of the elephant [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Human Chromosome 2/8 was observed only in one species of Xenarthra, and it is not clear whether the segments involved are the same as those detected in Afrotheria, which rules out this association as a common ancestral one.</p><p>An alternative putative ancestral karyotype with 2<italic>n</italic> = 46 was proposed, in which the combination human Chromosome 10/12/22 would be present [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Although we observed an association human Chromosome 10/12 in <italic>D. novemcinctus,</italic> we could not detect it in the other two species. As previously discussed [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], the ancestral status of human Chromosome 10/12/22, which seems to be widespread in Afrotheria and Carnivores, remains doubtful. Our new data on Xenarthra do not lend support to this association as an ancestral Eutherian karyotype feature, thus reinforcing the 2<italic>n</italic> = 48 ancestral karyotype hypothesis.</p><p>The status of Xenarthra as a basal group in the Eutherian phylogenetic tree is still disputed on molecular grounds [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Based on the chromosome-painting results, it is clear that no Afrotheria has a complement so close to the putative ancestral Eutherian karyotype as the one we found herein in Xenarthra. Thus, Xenarthra cannot yet be ruled out as the most basal Eutheria, and more data should be gathered on the two basal groups before a more definitive answer is reached.</p><p>A final conclusion on the ancestral Eutherian karyotype will ultimately depend on comparisons with the most suitable outgroup, represented by marsupials. Technical constraints currently prevent cross-species chromosome painting between such distantly related groups as Eutherians and marsupials.</p><p>It is important to point out that the resolution limit of interspecies chromosome painting is about 5 Mbp. Another constraint of this approach is that it cannot detect intrachromosomal rearrangements, as inversions, that result in gene-order changes. Recent comparative studies encompassing results obtained from chromosome painting, radiation hybrid maps, and whole-genome sequencing of various mammalian groups show the potential of this broad kind of study to reveal conserved genome segments in mammals as well as the breakpoints involved in chromosome repatterning at a much more detailed level [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This approach promises ultimately to allow the reconstruction of the ancestral Eutherian karyotype, as whole-genome sequencing data become available for more mammalian species, including marsupials and monotremes, in the not too distant future.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Chromosome preparations were obtained from cultured fibroblasts of a female nine-banded armadillo <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. novemcinctus</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 64), a male two-toed sloth <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. hoffmanii</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 50), and a female lesser anteater <named-content content-type="genus-species">T. tetradactyla</named-content> (2<italic>n</italic> = 54). The cells from the two former species were kindly supplied by the Center for Reproduction of Endangered Species (CRES) of the San Diego Zoo, California, United States. The lesser anteater cells were purchased from ATCC (Manassas, Virginia, United States). Cells were cultivated in &#x003b1;DMEM with 10% fetal bovine serum at 35 &#x000b0;C. Routine procedures were used for chromosome preparations. GTG banding was performed as described [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] with modifications.</p><p>Human chromosome&#x02013;specific probes were obtained by flow sorting, and DOP-PCR as well as the interspecific in situ hybridization experiments were performed as already described [<xref rid="pgen-0020109-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> RS conceived and designed the experiments. MS and RS performed the experiments and analyzed the data. GS and RS contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. MS wrote the paper.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n104" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests.</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn id="n103" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>
<bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute, Center for Cancer Research.</p></fn></fn-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CRES</term><def><p>Center for Reproduction of Endangered Species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>FN</italic></term><def><p>fundamental number (number of autosomal chromosome arms)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mya</term><def><p>million years ago</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen-0020109-b001"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Molecular phylogenetics and the origins of placental mammals</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>409</volume>
<fpage>614</fpage>
<lpage>618</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11214319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b002"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Resolution of the early placental mammal radiation using Bayesian phylogenetics</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>294</volume>
<fpage>2348</fpage>
<lpage>2351</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b003"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Molecules consolidate the placental mammal tree</article-title>
<source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>430</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b004"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Molecular dating and biogeography of the early placental mammal radiation</article-title>
<source>J Hered</source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>212</fpage>
<lpage>219</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11396581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b005"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Influence of Tertiary paleoenvironmental changes on the diversification of South American mammals: A relaxed molecular clock study within Xenarthrans</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>11</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15115541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b006"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Catzeflis</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The evolution of armadillos, anteaters and sloths depicted by nuclear and mitochondrial phylogenies: Implications for the status of the enigmatic fossil Eurotamandua</article-title>
<source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>1605</fpage>
<lpage>1615</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b007"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Molecular phylogeny of living Xenarthrans and the impact of character and taxon sampling on the placental tree rooting</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1656</fpage>
<lpage>1671</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b008"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Molecular systematics of armadillos (Xenarthra, Dasypodidae): Contribution of maximum likelihood and Bayesian analyses of mitochondrial and nuclear genes</article-title>
<source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>261</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b009"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of 16S mitochrondrial DNA data in sloths and anteaters</article-title>
<source>Genet Mol Biol</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b010"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>HRJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>MELT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Chromosome study of anteaters (Myrmecophagidae, Xenarthra)&#x02014;A preliminary report</article-title>
<source>Genet Mol Biol</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>
<lpage>394</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b011"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Meritt</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benirschke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Chromosome studies in Edentata</article-title>
<source>Cytobios</source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>157</fpage>
<lpage>172</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">679723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b012"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seu&#x000e1;nez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Chromosome studies on <italic>Dasypus, Euphractus</italic> and <italic>Cabassous</italic> genera (Edentata: Dasypodidae)</article-title>
<source>Cytobios</source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>196</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1813217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b013"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobigny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Volobouev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Low rate of genomic repatterning in Xenarthra inferred from chromosome painting data</article-title>
<source>Chromosome Res</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>651</fpage>
<lpage>663</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b014"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Raudsepp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherthan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Emerging patterns of comparative genome organization in some mammalian species as revealed by Zoo-FISH</article-title>
<source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>577</fpage>
<lpage>589</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9647633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b015"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wienberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Froenicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Insights into mammalian genome organization and evolution by molecular cytogenetics</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Comparative genomics</source>
<publisher-loc>Boston/Dordrecht/London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>
<fpage>207</fpage>
<lpage>244</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b016"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Evolution of mammalian genome organization inferred from comparative gene mapping</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<comment>REVIEWS0005. E-pub 2001 Jun 5.</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b017"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Froenicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The origin of human Chromosome 1 and its homologs in placental mammals</article-title>
<source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1880</fpage>
<lpage>1888</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b018"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutrillaux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Reconstruction of the ancestral karyotype of Eutherian mammals</article-title>
<source>Chromosome Res</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>605</fpage>
<lpage>618</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14516069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b019"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkalaeva</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardini</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Reciprocal chromosome painting among human, aardvark, and elephant (superorder Afrotheria) reveals the likely Eutherian ancestral karyotype</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>1062</fpage>
<lpage>1066</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12552116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b020"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Froenicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wienberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Towards the delineation of the ancestral Eutherian genome organization: Comparative genome maps of human and the African elephant <italic>(Loxodonta africana)</italic> generated by chromosome painting</article-title>
<source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>270</volume>
<fpage>1331</fpage>
<lpage>1340</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b021"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svartman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A chromosome painting test of the basal Eutherian karyotype</article-title>
<source>Chromosome Res</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>53</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14984101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b022"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson-Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Cross-species chromosome painting in the golden mole and elephant-shrew: Support for the mammalian clades Afrotheria and Afroinsectiphillia but not Afroinsectivora</article-title>
<source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>271</volume>
<fpage>1477</fpage>
<lpage>1484</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b023"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutrillaux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic origin of human Chromosomes 7, 16, and 19 and their homologs in placental mammals</article-title>
<source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>644</fpage>
<lpage>651</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b024"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Consigliere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Chromosome painting reveals that galagos have highly derived karyotypes</article-title>
<source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>
<volume>117</volume>
<fpage>319</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11920367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b025"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Froenicke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Origins of primate chromosomes&#x02014;As delineated by Zoo-FISH and alignments of human and mouse draft genome sequences</article-title>
<source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>122</fpage>
<lpage>138</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15545724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b026"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Everts-van der Wind</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Dynamics of mammalian chromosome evolution inferred from multispecies comparative maps</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>309</volume>
<fpage>613</fpage>
<lpage>617</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0020109-b027"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seabright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>A rapid banding technique for human chromosomes</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>971</fpage>
<lpage>972</lpage>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>