<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">311</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-019-0311-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Traditional medicinal animal use by Xhosa and Sotho communities in the Western Cape Province, South Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9669-8797</contrib-id><name><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>Willem A.</given-names></name><address><email>17688132@sun.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>Alison J.</given-names></name><address><email>aleslie@sun.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name><address><email>anita@capeleopard.org.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2214 904X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11956.3a</institution-id><institution>Department of Conservation Ecology and Entomology, </institution><institution>University of Stellenbosch, </institution></institution-wrap>Matieland, Western Cape 7602 South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473441.1</institution-id><institution>The Cape Leopard Trust, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box 31139, Tokai, Cape Town, 7966 South Africa </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>34</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The use of animals and animal-derived materials in traditional medicine constitutes an important part of the belief systems of indigenous African cultures. It is believed to be rapidly expanding in South Africa, where traditional healers are estimated to outnumber western doctors by 2000:1 in some areas, with an overall clientele consisting of 60&#x02013;80% of South African citizens. Despite concerns about the impact of the trade in traditional medicine on biodiversity, there has been only limited research on this topic in South Africa.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Traditional Xhosa and Sotho healers operating from impoverished, rural communities in the Boland Region of the Western Cape Province were consulted to provide a comprehensive inventory of the number and frequency of animals used and sold. Species richness estimators, diversity indices, and a relative cultural importance (RCI) index were used to highlight species of concern and assess market dynamics.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 26 broad use categories for 12 types of animal parts or products from 71 species or morphospecies were recorded. The most commonly sold items were skin pieces, oil or fat, and bones. Results showed that leopard, chacma baboon, Cape porcupine, monitor lizard species, puff adder, African rock python, and black-backed jackal were the species most used in the traditional medicinal trade.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">This study extends existing knowledge on the trade of animals in South African healing practices and provides the first attempt in the Western Cape to quantify wildlife use for cultural traditions. The results have relevance for setting conservation priorities and may assist in effective policy development inclusive of ecological sustainability priorities, as well as cultural demands.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13002-019-0311-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ethnozoology</kwd><kwd>Ethnopharmacology;Informal settlements</kwd><kwd>Species accumulation curves</kwd><kwd>Xhosa medicine</kwd><kwd>Zootherapy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15">Zootherapy has existed in traditional folk pharmacopoeias throughout history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and remains an integral component in traditional medicinal practices and other cultural applications in contemporary landscapes worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], particularly in African [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], Asian [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and Latin American countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">Similarly in South Africa, the trade of, and dependence on, natural resources as traditional medicine amongst primarily indigenous African cultures is deemed to be pervasive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. African cultures and associated traditional healers in South Africa subscribe to a resolute belief that health and welfare issues are intimately connected with supernatural forces, social relationships, and ancestral relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Consequently, traditional healers are highly esteemed members of the community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] whose consultation is often preferred to those of Western doctors. Furthermore, the relatively few per capita Western doctors available in South Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] have resulted in a large proportion of the country&#x02019;s population being more dependent on traditional medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Estimations by several authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] suggest that between 60 and 80% of South African citizens have at some point either purchased traditional medicine or consulted with a traditional healer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This is particularly relevant to communities existing in poor, rural areas (&#x0003e;&#x02009;50% of the South African population) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] where little opportunity exists to consult with university-educated doctors, while traditional healers in comparison are far more accessible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">In the Western Cape Province (WCP), the use of animals in traditional medicine or cultural practice is largely dominated by Xhosa-speaking people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], who constitute the largest proportion of African ethnic groups in the province (24.7%, with Sotho-speaking people representing the second highest proportion at 1.1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Animal use in Xhosa traditional medicine was documented as early as the 1930s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], but the practice is certainly much older, since Xhosa communities had no contact with Western doctors and associated medical procedure prior to the 19th century [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Similar to other indigenous African cultures in South Africa, Xhosa and Sotho healing practices place an equal or greater value on the use of animal constituents and derivatives for the curing of non-medical ailments, such as protection against bad luck and witches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Other &#x02018;symbolic magical&#x02019; or &#x02018;magico-medical&#x02019; purposes include the protection against physical and spiritual enemies and entities, love charms and aphrodisiacs, increased intelligence, acquiring wealth and prosperity, and aiding pastoral enterprises [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">Despite its importance to indigenous communities in South Africa being widely acknowledged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], ethnozoological research has been largely subjected to paucity, especially compared to ethnobotanical research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The lack of ethnozoological studies in South Africa is likely due to its small claim on the greater materia medica of indigenous cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], as well as the popular association of ethnozoology with &#x02018;spiritual&#x02019; or &#x02018;magical&#x02019; components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and the Doctrine of Signatures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], withdrawing credibility from zootherapeutics as a realistic scientific pursuit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Despite research on ethnozoology in South Africa however being largely sporadic and subject to neglect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], there has been a recent upsurge in available information during the past few decades originating from Kwazulu-Natal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], the Faraday market in Johannesburg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and the Eastern Cape Province [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]&#x02014;subsequently greatly improving our understanding of the topic. A noticeable gap however still remains in the WCP amid the extensive and expanding demand for animal products for traditional uses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], exacerbated by the growing human population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], migratory influxes to the province [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and high levels of unemployment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">The aim of this study was thus to acquire information, inventory, and document the use of animal-derived materials by diviners, herbalists, and general animal parts traders (hereafter collectively referred to as traditional healers) operating from impoverished, rural communities in the Boland Region of the WCP, South Africa. A variety of quantitative approaches were employed to specifically explore the following: (1) vertebrate species incidence, richness, and diversity and (2) the species most valued by local African communities. This will provide novel insights into the extent and dynamics of the traditional healing enterprise, as well as the demand for vertebrate taxa, thus determining conservation priorities and enabling effective policy development inclusive of both ecological sustainability priorities as well as social demands.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par20">Research was undertaken in 17 townships and informal settlements in rural or peri-urban landscapes in the Boland Region (~&#x02009;4000&#x02009;km<sup>2</sup>), part of the WCP of South Africa (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The sampled sites were purposively chosen to be inclusive of all such residential communities in the study area with indigenous African people contributing to &#x0003e;&#x02009;20% of the overall population demographics. Large racial and ethnic diversity however still remained amongst sites, enabling the comparison of demographically heterogeneous and homogeneous settlements. The Boland Region consists of various protected areas enveloped by vast expansions of agriculturally transformed lands. The remaining natural habitats support low animal biomass due to the largely unpalatable and nutrient-deficient fynbos vegetation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. As a result, leopard (<italic>Panthera pardus</italic>), Cape mountain zebra (<italic>Equus zebra zebra</italic>), and bontebok (<italic>Damaliscus pygargus</italic>) are the only large mammal species that are able to persist without human intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The WCP however boasts high levels of endemism of mammal, amphibian, reptilian, and avifauna taxa (11&#x02013;54% endemism) and supports approximately 50% of all terrestrial vertebrate species found in South Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Data collection took place in the autumn (April to May) of 2018.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Sampled communities in the WCP of South Africa. The communities were Zweletemba (Z), Drommedaris (D), Mbekweni (Mb), Paarl SP (Pa), Kayamandi (K), Tjotjombeni (T), Goniwe Park (G), Sir Lowry&#x02019;s pass village (S), Nomzamo (N), Lwandle (L), Marikana (M), Rooidakkies (R), Siyanyazela (Si), Pineview (P), Snake Park (Sn), Botrivier SP (B), and Zwelihle (Zw)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2019_311_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par21">To gather information on the use of vertebrate species by traditional healers, semi-structured interviews were conducted with 36 respondents in townships and informal settlements (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17). Unlike the more obvious and prominent <italic>umuthi</italic> markets found in Johannesburg and Durban [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], traditional healing in the WCP is much more discreet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Consequently, identifying potential informants was achieved using a non-probability snowball sampling approach, i.e. community members were asked to locate neighbours fitting the criteria. Snowball sampling is an efficient manner of gathering information during purposive sampling in situations where there is no obvious information on the whereabouts of the population of interest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. All interviews were conducted in the home languages of informants, either isiXhosa (81%) or Sesotho (19%). Respondents ranged from 25 to 62&#x02009;years of age (median&#x02009;=&#x02009;37.5&#x02009;years) and comprised mostly males (78%). All respondents reportedly migrated from the Eastern Cape Province. Interviews ranged between 50&#x02009;min and 2&#x02009;h. The WCP hosts a great variety of species lineages, as well as many cryptic species (i.e. species that are hard to discern morphologically) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Animal identification cards were therefore used to facilitate memory recall and to eliminate the possibility of disparity in species names or the grouping of species as ethnospecies (i.e. a folk or common name liberally assigned to a number of closely related species) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Species parts or products were identified on site where possible.</p><p id="Par22">All interviews were conducted anonymously, and information was kept confidential. At least a certain degree of reluctance was expected in providing information on the use of animal species, especially those relating to the treatment of magico-medicinal ailments, as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, respondents were almost exclusively extremely forthcoming, inviting, and even excited to have their knowledge formally documented. Only one respondent refused to participate due to recent run-ins with law enforcement (non-response&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.7%), and uses for four species were not recorded (5.6%). Consent was obtained from each respondent for the use of their accounts prior to every interview, and ethical clearance was obtained from the Stellenbosch University ethics committee: humanities (reference: CEE-2018-6251) preceding the data collection phase of this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">Basic descriptive statistics were used to analyse the highest incidence of vertebrate species sold by traditional healers, as well as species sold that were of conservation concern. Species with the most uses as cited by traditional healers, the most prevalent animal parts or products, and their corresponding market values were also described.</p><p id="Par24">Sampling performance was evaluated by constructing rarefaction curves, where sampling size was deemed sufficient when the expected number of species, E(Sn), did not increase with the addition of more individuals to the sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. This is indicated by the &#x02018;levelling-off&#x02019; of E(Sn) on the rarefaction curve.</p><p id="Par25">Information regarding the number and frequency of species occurrence in the area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] was used to quantify the richness, diversity, and evenness or equitability of animals used and sold by traditional healers in the Boland Region. Observed species richness (S) may however be heavily dependent on sampling effort. Therefore, species richness estimation curves were used to measure and compare various estimators of species richness by adding unseen species to the observed S [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], facilitating improved interpretation of S outcomes, especially since samples varied in size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The performance of six non-parametric S estimators appropriate for incidence-based data (i.e. information on species frequencies), namely Chao 2, first-order jackknife (Jack 1), second-order jackknife (Jack 2), incidence-based coverage estimator (ICE), bootstrap (Boot), and Michaelis-Menten means (MMMeans), was calculated and compared. For each of the calculations, the sample order was randomised 100 times to compute mean statistics at each sample order, thereby generating smooth accumulation curves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Species diversity was expressed using the Shannon-Wiener index (H&#x02019;), the Simpson diversity index (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>), Hill&#x02019;s diversity numbers (N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>), and Fisher&#x02019;s alpha (&#x003b1;). Additionally, evenness was expressed with the Shannon index of evenness (J&#x02019;) and Hill&#x02019;s E5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">All values for indices and species-richness estimators were calculated using EstimateS software v9.1.0.</p><p id="Par27">The informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] was used to calculate the degree of socio-cultural coherence regarding animals being used within and amongst certain communities with respect to similar ailments. The method rests on the assumption that the greater the degree of group consensus regarding the use of ethnomedicinal species for treating certain conditions are, the greater the probability that the specific treatment is physiologically active or effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The formula in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] was used: F<sub>IC</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;(N<sub>ur</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;n<sub>t</sub>)/(n<sub>ur</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1), where N<sub>ur</sub> equals the number of use citations in each use category and n<sub>t</sub> equals the number of species used per use category. High values (close to 1) relate to a greater degree of informant consensus or homogeny on which animals are considered effective in the treating of a certain ailment. Conversely, low values (close to 0) indicate a high degree of variation in the number of different animals used to treat a particular ailment. F<sub>IC</sub> values were only calculated for use categories with &#x0003e;&#x02009;4 independent citations.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Species incidence and use prevalence</title><p id="Par28">The 71 vertebrate species or morphospecies cited by traditional healers in the sampled communities belonged to four classes and 20 orders (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The main orders were Carnivora (20 spp.), Artiodactyla (17 spp.), and Squamata (10 spp.).</p><p id="Par29">A total of 7 species and morphospecies were enumerated in &#x0003e;&#x02009;50% of sampled communities (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). These were chacma baboon (<italic>Papio ursinus</italic>, 82.4%), leopard (<italic>P. pardus</italic>, 82.4%), Cape porcupine (<italic>Hystrix africaeaustralis</italic>, 76.5%), puff adder (<italic>Bitis arietans</italic>, 76.5%), genet spp. (<italic>Genetta</italic> spp., 58.8%), black-backed jackal (<italic>Canis mesomelas</italic>, 52.9%), and monitor lizard spp. (<italic>Varanus</italic> spp., 52.9%). Of all vertebrate animal species listed, mammal taxa (73.2%) were far more prevalent than either reptile (18.3%) or bird (7.0%) taxa. Only one vertebrate fish species was recorded. No amphibian or invertebrate (marine or terrestrial) species were identified.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>High incidence species in sampled communities (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">Mammals</th><th colspan="2">Reptiles</th><th colspan="2">Birds</th></tr><tr><th>Common name</th><th>Samples (&#x0003e;&#x02009;30%)</th><th>Common name</th><th>Samples (&#x0003e;&#x02009;10%)</th><th>Common name</th><th>Samples (&#x0003e;&#x02009;10%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Chacma baboon</td><td>82.4</td><td>Puff adder</td><td>76.5</td><td>Owl spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>41.2</td></tr><tr><td>Leopard</td><td>82.4</td><td>Monitor lizard spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>52.9</td><td>Vulture spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>35.3</td></tr><tr><td>Cape porcupine</td><td>76.5</td><td>African rock python</td><td>41.2</td><td>Ostrich</td><td>17.7</td></tr><tr><td>Genet spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>58.8</td><td>Nile crocodile</td><td>29.4</td><td>Swallow spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>11.8</td></tr><tr><td>Black-backed jackal</td><td>52.9</td><td>Cape cobra</td><td>29.4</td><td>Cattle egret</td><td>11.8</td></tr><tr><td>Honey badger</td><td>47.1</td><td>Mamba spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>23.4</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Hare spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>47.1</td><td>Snake spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>17.7</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Cape clawless otter</td><td>41.2</td><td>Angulate tortoise</td><td>17.7</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>African buffalo</td><td>41.2</td><td>Rinkhals</td><td>11.8</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Cape fox</td><td>35.3</td><td>Southern rock agama</td><td>11.8</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Spiral-horned antelope spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>35.3</td><td>Girdled lizard spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>11.8</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Caracal</td><td>35.3</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Individuals not identifiable up to species level</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par30">Twelve species recorded (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) are listed of conservation concern by the IUCN Red List of threatened species (version 2017-3). Critically endangered (CR) and endangered (EN) species included several vulture species of the genus <italic>Gyps</italic>, tiger (<italic>Panthera tigris</italic>), and an unidentified rhinoceros species (either of the genus <italic>Diceros</italic> or <italic>Ceratotherium</italic>). Additionally, several <italic>Cordylus</italic> spp. (girdled lizard spp.) are near-threatened (NT). African striped weasel (<italic>Poecilogale albinucha</italic>) and Southern African hedgehog (<italic>Atelerix frontalis</italic>) are listed as near-threatened in the Endangered Wildlife Trust Mammal Red List. Nile crocodile (<italic>Crocodylus niloticus</italic>) and Eastern green mamba (<italic>Dendroaspis angusticeps</italic>) are listed as vulnerable (VU) in the SANBI Red List for reptiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Vertebrate species of conservation concern according to the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species (2001 categories, version 2017-3, global assessment) that were sold by traditional healers in the sampled market</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Species</th><th>Common name</th><th>IUCN category</th><th>Population trend</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Acinonyx jubatus</italic>
</td><td>Cheetah</td><td>VU</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Aonyx capensis</italic>
</td><td>Cape clawless otter</td><td>NT</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Equus zebra zebra</italic>
</td><td>Cape mountain zebra</td><td>VU</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Gyps</italic> spp.<sup>a</sup></td><td>Cape vulture</td><td>EN/CR</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Hippopotamus amphibius</italic>
</td><td>Hippopotamus</td><td>VU</td><td>Stable</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Hyaena brunnea</italic>
</td><td>Brown hyena</td><td>NT</td><td>Unknown</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Loxodonta africana</italic>
</td><td>African elephant</td><td>VU</td><td>Increasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Panthera leo</italic>
</td><td>Lion</td><td>VU</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Panthera pardus</italic>
</td><td>Leopard</td><td>VU</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Panthera tigris</italic>
<sup>b</sup>
</td><td>Tiger</td><td>EN</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Pelea capreolus</italic>
</td><td>Grey rhebok</td><td>NT</td><td>Decreasing</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Diceros/Ceratotherium</italic>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>Rhinoceros spp.</td><td>CR</td><td>Increasing</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Conservation status varies between species</p><p><sup>b</sup>Exotic species</p><p><sup>c</sup>Species unknown</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par31">The number of uses for each animal varied from one to 16 (median&#x02009;=&#x02009;2; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), with the most uses attributed to Cape porcupine (16 uses), leopard (15 uses), and chacma baboon (11 uses). Uses were not recorded for four species, namely Southern African hedgehog, whale spp. (Cetaceae), tiger, and girdled lizard spp.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The animal species with the most use categories attributed to them by traditional healers. Bars were divided to display uses relating to medical ailments, spiritual or magical purposes, and other uses (clothing, jewellery, status symbols, etc.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2019_311_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par32">A total of 716 vertebrate species parts or products were listed as being used in traditional medicinal practices in sampled communities (median&#x02009;=&#x02009;23, range&#x02009;=&#x02009;7&#x02013;34). These were subsequently grouped into 12 categories for analyses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Skin pieces and entire skins were the most prevalent form of animal constituents used or sold by traditional healers (258 items), followed by animal oil and subcutaneous fat (120 items). Animal bones (62 items), entire carcasses (56 items), and internal organs (46 items) were also highly prevalent, as well as assorted hooves, paws, and talons (44 items) and quills, feathers, fur, and scales (44 items).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Species parts and products most frequently sold by traditional healers in the sampled community. Bars were divided to present proportional incidence of mammal, reptile, and bird taxa</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2019_311_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">High market values were recorded for wildlife items sold by traditional healers in the Boland. Prices were however highly variable across items as well as amongst the same items sold by different healers, even for the same purpose (range: USD 1&#x02013;1566). The most expensive animal items were entire skins of leopard (median&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 881, range&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 392&#x02013;1566), bones of African buffalo (<italic>Syncerus caffer</italic>, median&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 646, range&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 627&#x02013;665), and bones of Cape fur seals (<italic>Arctocephalus pusillus</italic>, median&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 509, range&#x02009;=&#x02009;USD 392&#x02013;627).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Sampling performance</title><p id="Par34">Sample-based rarefaction curves were plotted for vertebrate animal taxa sold by traditional healers in the Boland Region, along with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). None of the samples truly reached an asymptote. However, they were all clearly approaching an asymptote as the rate at which new species were found gradually decreased. Therefore, the sampling size was said to be sufficient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Further sampling of traditional healers would thus not yield a significant number of novel, undiscovered species for any of the individual vertebrate classes. The rapid initial accumulation shown by reptiles and bird groups indicated that species were accumulating faster for comparatively small sample sizes. Species richness was correlated with the number of settlements in which the vertebrate class was found.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Rarefaction curves (solid lines) for vertebrate animals used by traditional healers in informal settlements in the Boland Region (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17), with 95% confidence intervals (dashed lines). Parentheses indicate sample sizes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2019_311_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Species richness, diversity, and evenness</title><p id="Par35">Species richness estimates and other summary values were calculated for three sets of data: the first containing information on all species recorded in the sampled communities, the second only mammal species, and the third only reptile species (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Bird taxa were excluded from analysis due to their relatively low incidence in the sampled community.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Species richness estimates and other values characterising the use of animals by traditional healers in the WCP</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>All species</th><th>Mammals</th><th>Reptiles</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Samples (<italic>n</italic>)</td><td>17</td><td>17</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Individuals (<italic>N</italic>)</td><td>450</td><td>365</td><td>67</td></tr><tr><td>Observed species richness</td><td>71</td><td>52</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Estimated species richness</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ICE</td><td>74.7</td><td>54.5</td><td>13.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Chao 2</td><td>73.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0</td><td>55.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.2</td><td>13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Jack 1</td><td>79.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1</td><td>58.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5</td><td>14.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Jack 2</td><td>78.3</td><td>61.5</td><td>14.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Bootstrap</td><td>75.5</td><td>55.8</td><td>14.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;MMMeans</td><td>85.8</td><td>61.1</td><td>14.5</td></tr><tr><td>Singletons<sup>1</sup></td><td>9</td><td>7</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Doubletons<sup>2</sup></td><td>13</td><td>6</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Bird taxa were excluded due to their relatively low incidence in the market</p><p><sup>1</sup>Number of species occurring only once across all samples</p><p><sup>2</sup>Number of species occurring only twice across all samples</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par36">All estimators appeared to approach an asymptote sooner than the observed species accumulation curve (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), indicating their usefulness as adequate species richness estimators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The MMMeans estimator understandably reached an asymptote first, given its asymptotic nature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The remaining estimators approached asymptotes in relative parallel to the observed species curve. The difference between the highest estimator (MMMeans) and lowest estimator (Chao 2) was 12.5 species. The observed species richness was 83% of the highest richness estimator. Plots of singletons and doubletons rose rapidly at the first samples and then levelled-off as sample size increased.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The comparative performance of six incidence-based species richness estimators (MMMeans, ICE, Jack 1, Jack 2, Bootstrap, and Chao 2), as well as the observed species accumulation curve, for all vertebrate species recorded (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;71). The cumulative numbers of singletons and doubletons were also plotted. Estimated species richness is indicated in brackets. Samples were randomised 100 times</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2019_311_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">The overall species diversity recorded (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) was relatively high (Shannon H&#x02019;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.79; Simpson&#x02019;s 1/&#x003bb;&#x02009;=&#x02009;28.55). The high diversity values relate to high levels of uncertainty, i.e. it would be difficult to correctly predict the identification of the next species found if sampling were to continue. Amongst taxonomic groups, mammals had comparatively higher diversity values (Shannon H&#x02019;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.47; Simpson&#x02019;s 1/&#x003bb;&#x02009;=&#x02009;20.96) than reptiles (Shannon H&#x02019;&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.02; Simpson&#x02019;s 1/&#x003bb;&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.59) and birds (Shannon H&#x02019;&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.47; Simpson&#x02019;s 1/&#x003bb;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.92), which was correlated with species richness between these groups. The low value for Fisher&#x02019;s alpha was expected due to the small number of species recorded compared to other ethnoecological studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], especially ethnobotanical surveys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Selected measures of diversity calculated for vertebrate taxa (together and separately) sold by traditional healers in informal settlements in the Boland Region</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Index/measure</th><th>Animals (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17)</th><th>Mammals (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;17)</th><th>Reptiles (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;16)</th><th>Birds (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;10)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Individuals</td><td>450</td><td>365</td><td>67</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>Species richness (S or N<sub>0</sub>)</td><td>71</td><td>52</td><td>13</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Mean S per community&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</td><td>18.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7</td><td>14.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.0</td><td>4.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.76</td><td>1.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.16</td></tr><tr><td>Shannon-Wiener index (H&#x02019;)</td><td>3.79</td><td>3.47</td><td>2.02</td><td>1.47</td></tr><tr><td>Simpson&#x02019;s (1/&#x003bb;)&#x02009;=&#x02009;Hill&#x02019;s N<sub>2</sub></td><td>28.55</td><td>20.96</td><td>7.32</td><td>3.92</td></tr><tr><td>Hill&#x02019;s N1 (e<sup>H&#x02019;</sup>)</td><td>44.26</td><td>32.37</td><td>7.54</td><td>4.35</td></tr><tr><td>Fisher&#x02019;s &#x003b1;</td><td>23.22</td><td>16.12</td><td>4.25</td><td>2.13</td></tr><tr><td>E1 (Shannon J&#x02019;)&#x02009;=&#x02009;(H&#x02019;/H&#x02019;<sub>max</sub>)<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.89</td><td>0.88</td><td>0.79</td><td>0.91</td></tr><tr><td>Evenness E5 (N2-1/N1-1)</td><td>0.64</td><td>0.64</td><td>0.97</td><td>0.87</td></tr><tr><td>Mean number shared species</td><td>6.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.28 (range 1&#x02013;14)</td><td>5.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.85 (range 1&#x02013;13)</td><td>1.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02 (range 0&#x02013;4)</td><td>0.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45 (range 0&#x02013;2)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>H&#x02019;<sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;ln(S)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par38">Shannon J&#x02019; evenness values were high overall (range&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.79&#x02013;0.91), indicating that most species were evenly dispersed throughout the sampled communities and that relatively few species were dominant. The low value for reptiles was likely due to the dominance of puff adder, monitor lizard spp., and African rock python. By comparison, E5 evenness values for all species and mammals were smaller (0.64 each), potentially as a result of the dominance of leopard and baboon in the samples. Overall, the high evenness values indicated that traditional healers in the Boland Region did not necessarily narrowly favour a few specific animal species, even though some species were more popular than others. Evenness values should be interpreted with caution since a scarcity of popular species during the time of sampling may have led to species being underreported.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Informant consensus factor</title><p id="Par39">The F<sub>ic</sub> analysis identified definite variations in the degree of heterogeneity and homogeneity in the selection of different animals to treat certain conditions by traditional healers operating in informal communities (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). The highest degree of informant consensus (i.e. high socio-cultural coherence) was for resolving court cases or reducing prison sentences (F<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.88) and for treating mental illnesses or improving cognitive abilities (F<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.85). Informants thus strongly agreed that black-backed jackal and Cape porcupine were superior animals for resolving court cases or reducing prison sentences, while mental illness or cognitive vigour was best treated with black-backed jackal, Cape fox (<italic>Vulpes chama</italic>), bat-eared fox (<italic>Otocyon megalotis</italic>), and leopard. The lowest degree of informant consensus (F<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00) was for treatments of cold or flu, headaches, kidney stones, and shingles, as well as for love charms and for protection against crime. All species mentioned by traditional healers for the treatment of these ailments were different from each other. Respondents exhibited comparatively lower consensus in the treatment of medical ailments (AverageF<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.31) compared to the treatment of spiritual or magical ailments (AverageF<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.36). Overall consensus for treating any ailment was however low (AverageF<sub>ic</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.34).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Socio-cultural coherence in the treatment of commonly cited medical ailments within and between sampled communities measured with the informant consensus factor (F<sub>ic</sub>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Ailment</th><th>N<sub>t</sub></th><th>N<sub>ur</sub></th><th>F<sub>ic</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Resolve court cases/reduce prison sentence (SM)</td><td>2</td><td>9</td><td>0.88</td></tr><tr><td>Mental illness treatment/improved cognitive ability (M)</td><td>4</td><td>21</td><td>0.85</td></tr><tr><td>Improved muscle development/physical appearance (M)</td><td>5</td><td>14</td><td>0.69</td></tr><tr><td>Stroke (M)</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>0.67</td></tr><tr><td>Protect against black magic/bad muti/idliso<sup>1</sup>/harm (SM)</td><td>6</td><td>12</td><td>0.55</td></tr><tr><td>Rituals/summon spirits (SM)</td><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>Spiritual protection: infants (SM)</td><td>3</td><td>5</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>Spiritual protection: individual (SM)</td><td>33</td><td>62</td><td>0.48</td></tr><tr><td>Spiritual protection: homestead (SM)</td><td>15</td><td>26</td><td>0.44</td></tr><tr><td>Predict future/enlightenment (SM)</td><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>0.43</td></tr><tr><td>Acquire wealth or good fortune (SM)</td><td>10</td><td>16</td><td>0.40</td></tr><tr><td>Fertility (M)</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>0.40</td></tr><tr><td>Protect livestock/crops (SM)</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>0.40</td></tr><tr><td>Epilepsy (M)</td><td>8</td><td>12</td><td>0.36</td></tr><tr><td>Elicit black magic/harm/idliso<sup>1</sup> to others (SM)</td><td>11</td><td>16</td><td>0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Ibekelo<sup>2</sup> (SM)</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Increased agricultural yield (SM)</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Paralysis (M)</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td>Exorcism (SM)</td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>0.20</td></tr><tr><td>Arthritis (M)</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>Cold/flu (M)</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Headaches (M)</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Kidney stones (M)</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Shingles (M)</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Love charms (SM)</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Protect against crime (SM)</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>Average</td><td>6.65</td><td>11.19</td><td>0.34</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>N</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub> number of species per use category, <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>ur</italic></sub> number of citations per use category. F<sub>ic</sub> values were only calculated for use categories with &#x0003e;&#x02009;3 citations. Ailments: <italic>M</italic> medicinal, <italic>SM</italic> spiritual/magical</p><p><sup>1</sup>Idliso (translates to &#x02018;African poison&#x02019;) refers to a cultural phenomenon in which black magic is used to poison the food of others, with the intention to induce serious illness, misfortune, or death</p><p><sup>2</sup>Ibekelo is a form of black magic poison that is placed on the walking path of the victim. It is believed that when the victim steps over it, he/she will become seriously ill. Illness is said to begin in the limbs, gradually moving upward</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par40">The use of vertebrate species in traditional medicine is a controversial subject that has raised many concerns regarding its impact on natural wildlife [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], and several statements have been made on the widespread abundance of traditional healers in South Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. This study not only substantiates those claims, but emphasises the previously undocumented relevance of the traditional medicinal trade in household businesses in the Boland Region of the WCP.</p><p id="Par41">This study recorded 71 vertebrate species and morphospecies being used in traditional medicinal practices, constituting <italic>c</italic>. 4.5% of all mammal, reptile, and bird fauna found in South Africa (1 488+ species, not including marine mammals). In accordance with previous South African ethnozoological inventories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], mammals were the most prominent taxonomic group (73%, 11 orders). Contrastingly, studies in Latin America have found traditional medicinal practices to place an equal or greater value on invertebrate, reptile, and bird taxa compared to mammal taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. The current study however recorded reptiles (18%, three orders) and birds (7%, five orders) to a far lesser extent. Additionally, a single shark morphospecies was recorded, and no amphibian or invertebrate (marine or terrestrial) species. Domestic animals are generally viewed as an unimportant source of medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and consequently, only three domestic species were recorded. The species most cited during ethnoecological inventories may however provide a false representation of the actual species abundance in the markets, especially when sampling only occurs in one season [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>Sampling performance and completeness of the dataset</title><p id="Par42">To evaluate sampling performance and completeness of the dataset, rarefaction curves were constructed, as well as other species accumulation curves based on a variety of species richness estimators. The rarefaction curves never truly reached an asymptote, as required to deduce sufficient sampling effort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. However, given the large area from which animals can be sourced, the relatively large study area, and the diversity of species sold in traditional medicine markets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], it is unlikely that a true asymptote will ever be reached [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Therefore, species richness estimators predicted that a number of species were not recorded in the study area, especially mammals, which had a greater number of singletons present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Based on the rate at which estimators reached an asymptote and their consensus with each other and other estimators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], the Jack 1, Jack 2, and MMMeans estimators were considered the best estimators. The MMMeans estimator predicted that 86 species could be identified by further surveying in the sampled communities (i.e. 15 new species), while the Jack 2 and Jack 1 estimators predicted that a further seven and eight species could be found, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Based on these estimators, the current study thus recorded 83&#x02013;91% of the possible species in traditional medicine in the Boland Region&#x02019;s communities, which is more than adequate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. However, since many species were classified as morphospecies where no distinction was made between species by traditional healers, species richness is likely to be higher than reported in this study. Furthermore, since data collection occurred over a relatively short time period, some homogeneity is expected in the species recorded, and more species could therefore likely be found in subsequent studies spanning different seasons. Nevertheless, the species accumulation curves were all approaching asymptotes or had levelled-off, from which can be concluded, in conjunction with the rarefaction curves, that sampling size was sufficient and further sampling would likely not yield significantly more species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Species&#x02019; uses</title><p id="Par43">Understanding the specific uses of species and the factors affecting medicine choices can shed light on whether or not alternative therapies can be realistically suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. In this study, specific uses attributed to individual species greatly varied between species, as well as between traditional healers within and between communities. The Cape porcupine, leopard, and chacma baboon were the most diversely utilised, with 16, 15, and 11 distinct uses being attributed to them, respectively. Concerns are therefore expressed towards the sustainability of these species by virtue of the number of uses attributed to them. Additionally, definite variations in the degree of heterogeneity and homogeneity in the selection of certain animals to treat certain conditions were observed. The ailments listed by traditional healers were grouped into 26 categories (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>), and the majority of these categories were found to relate to spiritual or magical ailments (58%), displaying a greater degree of socio-cultural coherence in the species used for treating these ailments as opposed to medical ailments. Overall, informant consensus for treating any ailment was however relatively low (0.34). It is unclear why these large discrepancies exist, but it undoubtedly decreases the validity of these treatments as viable solutions to medical afflictions. Beyond species inconsistencies, a plethora of animal parts and products are furthermore used for the treatment of various ailments. These include predominantly skin pieces, oils and fats, and animal bones. The low degree of socio-cultural coherence identified in this study is therefore actually much lower, and it would be of great conservation benefit to increase culturally sensitive educational programmes to promote the use of western medicine in the treatment of purely medical ailments. The majority of informants in this study were certified by traditional healer and herbalist associations, which urges them not to discourage the use of western medicine, but rather supplement its use with natural products. A dislike or antagonism towards western medicine is thus not prevalent in these communities as popularly believed. Although the demand for traditional medicine is frequently reported as growing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], it was evident in this study that many considered the use of traditional medicine as &#x02018;outdated&#x02019; and &#x02018;not part of their modern belief systems&#x02019;. As observed on more than one occasion, consumers of the trade travelled substantial distances to seek the help of traditional healers due to the fear of being judged or ridiculed in their respective communities. However, the majority of listed treatments are related to spiritual ailments, especially for the protection against evil spirits and demons, and can thus not realistically be scientifically screened or tested, inhibiting the ability to prescribe alternative medicines.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Species&#x02019; selection</title><p id="Par44">It would benefit conservation and educational programmes to understand the psychology underlying the selection of species for traditional medicine. For example, the highest degree of informant consensus in this study was observed for the treatment of mental health issues and improved cognitive function through the use of jackal and fox species. The use of these species is likely founded on the general cross-cultural recognition of the cunningness of these animals and their popular portrayal as sly and clever characters in folk tales and fables. The selection of species for use in traditional medicine however depends on various anthropological, behavioural, and phenotypic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], and it is not always easy to deduce the thinking pattern underlying the use of certain species. Nonetheless, morphology or &#x02018;signatures&#x02019; have been suggested on numerous occasions as having a substantial influence on the species chosen for medicinal purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. This study similarly found further evidence for these trends. For example, porcupine quills were used in preparing and administering medicine because the porcupine is known to largely feed on bulbs and tubers which are often employed in ethnobotanical medicine, cattle egret (<italic>Bubulcus ibis</italic>) were used to guard homesteads because they are seen &#x02018;guarding&#x02019; livestock as they characteristically walk alongside them, and rinkhals (<italic>Hemachatus haemachatus</italic>) were used to protect crops against hail since it is believed that the characteristic hood of the cobra can cover the crops. Furthermore, since traditional medicinal practitioners believe animal traits can be transferred from animals to people, antelopes and hares were often avoided because they were viewed as scared and weak animals, while apex predators such as leopard, lion, and crocodile are highly sought after to transfer properties of strength and dominance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Economic aspects of the trade</title><p id="Par45">Identifying the prices given to products may elucidate factors relating to consumer behaviour and preferences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], as well as local purchasing power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. The market value of items used and sold in the sampled community was highly variable, ranging from USD 1 (baboon oil) to USD 1566 (leopard skin). Leopard products were highly popular and were consistently the highest priced. Items from Cape fur seals, dolphin spp., vulture spp., aardwolf (<italic>Proteles cristata</italic>), and African buffalo were also abnormally expensive, likely due to the difficulty in obtaining these items. It is however worth noting that few items could be acquired for less than USD 40, and the majority exceeded USD 80. In some instances, traditional healers explained that expensive products and treatments are acquired in dividends, primarily divided into &#x02018;deposit&#x02019; payments and &#x02018;finalising&#x02019; payments. Others welcomed the outmoded form of bartering, for instance releasing a product in exchange for livestock (e.g. poultry, goats or cattle) or tools (e.g. grinding stones). Interestingly, one informant explains the considerable variation in prices by stating: &#x0201c;&#x02026;many of them [traditional healers] exploit customers to get money&#x02026; for example in asking R2 000 (USD 157) for a genet skin&#x02026; while others, like me, don&#x02019;t care about the money, but only the acknowledgement&#x02026; gratification from a higher deity is far greater than money&#x0201d; (translated from isiXhosa). This sheds light on the extent to which traditional healers are motivated by financial rewards, potentially also explaining why traditional healers in the sampled communities varied in their involvement in the industry, and their reliance on the income generated. For example, a number of informants had full-time jobs in a diversity of vocations, and only practiced healing on weekends, while others practiced healing full-time. There was also a great disparity in living conditions and dependency by other family members, all potentially influencing market prices. Although the motivations stated for becoming traditional healers were relatively coherent across informants (mostly through divine revelation), it is undeniable that some healers are at least partially driven by monetary requirements, fulfilled by the growing and lucrative traditional healing industry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. It is therefore not so farfetched to consider the possibility of &#x02018;fake traditional healers&#x02019;, intent on generating income through deceitful practice. In fact, one informant stated &#x0201c;we [the community] do not visit the hoaxes [fake healers], but rather travel to the Eastern Cape to see the real diviners&#x0201d; (translated from isiXhosa). Future policy interventions need to take these motivations into consideration and adjust their approaches to these separate groups accordingly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. For many traditional healers or general traders, selling traditional medicine is not their primary choice of occupation, but necessitated by a lack of broader education and skills, as well as job scarcity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Therefore, a real need exists to invest in the education of these communities to equip and enable them to pursue careers beyond their current prospects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Species&#x02019; diversity and evenness</title><p id="Par46">Overall, the species diversity in the sampled communities was relatively high, as observed in most ethnoecological studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Since uncertainty is synonymous with diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], the relatively high diversity values thus imply greater difficulty in correctly predicting the species found in a subsequent sample and indicate a low probability that two species picked at random from the sample belong to the same species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Within taxonomic groups, diversity was consistent with the species richness of those groups and the number of singletons recorded in those groups. Likewise, overall evenness values were relatively high, substantiating that most species were evenly dispersed throughout our sampled communities. Reptile taxa were however dominated by a few species, namely puff adder, monitor lizard spp., and African rock python, resulting in lower evenness values than other taxonomic groups. Traditional healers therefore did not narrowly favour a few specific animal species, but utilised a plethora of different species. However, despite high evenness values, it was apparent that the species sold varied between communities. The reasons for these discrepancies remain unclear; however, it is worth noting that the species sold in communities consisting of Sotho natives differed significantly from the species sold in Xhosa communities.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Sustainability of the trade</title><p id="Par47">Twelve species of conservation concern were recorded during this study (11 mammals, 1 bird), raising concerns about their continued existence alongside the rapidly expanding traditional healing market. The majority of species enumerated that were of conservation concern however occurred in small quantities, understandably considering their presumed scarcity. Leopard, lion (<italic>Panthera leo</italic>), Cape clawless otter (<italic>Aonyx capensis</italic>), vulture species, and brown hyena (<italic>Hyaena brunnea</italic>) were however found in high densities. Less attention is usually given to species not of immediate conservation concern. However, given the regional scarcity of many species abundant in other regions of Southern Africa (e.g. black-backed jackal, aardwolf, aardvark (<italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>), vulture spp., and monitor lizard spp.), the ecological sustainability of the use of these animals is also questionable. Indiscriminate harvesting of these species from likely standardised locals and protected areas, coupled with increased migration patterns into the WCP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], threatens conservation efforts and ultimately species survival.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Limitations and future research</title><p id="Par48">This study took the first step in improving the overall understanding of the requirements and demands associated with the traditional healer-belief system, but failed to identify and map the sources providing the animal material for traditional healers. Informants were generally reluctant in revealing their sources, as reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], only admitting that material is sourced locally as far as possible, and only imported from areas such as Johannesburg, Durban, and the Eastern Cape Province when they cannot be found locally. At least one informant reported that materials are sourced exclusively from outside of the WCP, and four respondents mentioned that local farm workers supply them with animal carcasses in exchange for monetary compensation. Another informant claimed to be part of a group of traditional healers that together employ the services of a local, licensed professional hunter. It seems, therefore, that although large quantities of animal material are sourced from outside of the WCP, the market inarguably places some measure of pressure on local wildlife populations. Furthermore, this study is limited by a lack of knowledge on the actual turnover of species, since the rate at which products are sold and replaced was not obtainable. The lack of knowledge on the source populations or localities for animal harvesting, and the specific demand for products, will hinder conservation efforts and effective mitigation development, such as the identification of target areas for restoration initiatives. It would thus be of great future benefit to identify sources of animal material to incorporate these into effective policing and development frameworks that promote wildlife conservation and welfare, while still ensuring access to wildlife and wildlife uses that are deemed culturally acceptable. Respondents to the study made no mention of items being exported to other regions. However, given the global relevance of the medicinal animal trade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], as well as the demand for African species&#x02019; products in other parts of the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>], future research may also benefit from identifying market influences beyond the scope of the current study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par49">Ethnozoological studies have the potential to make a valuable contribution to elucidating biodiversity demands globally, thereby guiding concomitant conservation efforts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. Additionally, studies of this nature effectively reveal human-related factors related to biodiversity decline and provide opportunity for involving local communities in conservation interventions. This study extends existing knowledge on the trade of whole animals and animal-derived products in South African traditional healing practices and provides the first quantification for the practices in the WCP. The species inventory provided here is comprehensive and will therefore provide valuable information to inform management decision-making. Considering all analyses employed in this study, we recommend future investigations and subsequent conservation interventions assign special attention to the following species: leopard, chacma baboon, Cape porcupine, monitor lizard spp., genet spp., puff adder, African rock python, vulture spp., and black-backed jackal. The pressures exerted on these species by traditional healing, as well as their importance in the trade, were highlighted. Of these species, those that are range-restricted, threatened, habitat-specific, or occurring in small population sizes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] are most at risk of localised extinctions. The newly described and significant threat that traditional medicine poses to leopard populations in the WCP cannot be overly emphasised. In contrast to similar studies in other parts of South Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], leopards in this study had the highest incidence amongst communities (82%), had the second most uses attributed to them (15 uses), and were considered important in the treatment of various ailments. These results, coupled with the severe reduction and isolation of leopard populations during the past few decades due to habitat fragmentation, reduced prey bases, and human-wildlife conflict [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>], present a potential threat to their continued existence. Finally, further concern stems from the increased probability of the spread of zoonoses amongst traditional healers and the users of the trade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>], often residing in close proximity to one another. Policymakers, conservationists, and managers are now thus faced with an immense challenge, namely to further assess the dynamic trade of animals for traditional medicine, and subsequently generate policies and interventions that balance socio-economic development and cultural requirements with the diverse demands of biodiversity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional file</title><sec id="Sec20"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13002_2019_311_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Complete list of recorded species and their respective uses. (DOCX 22 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CR</term><def><p id="Par5">Critically endangered</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EN</term><def><p id="Par6">Endangered</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>F<sub>IC</sub></term><def><p id="Par7">Informant consensus factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICE</term><def><p id="Par8">Incidence-based coverage estimator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MMMeans</term><def><p id="Par9">Michaelis-Menten means</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NT</term><def><p id="Par10">Near-threatened</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RCI</term><def><p id="Par11">Relative cultural importance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>S</term><def><p id="Par12">Species richness</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VU</term><def><p id="Par13">Vulnerable</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WCP</term><def><p id="Par14">Western Cape Province</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The financial help received through grants to the Cape Leopard Trust by the Wilderness Foundation Africa and the Hans Hoheisen Charitable Trust is highly acknowledged. The authors are also thankful to Ismail Wambi for field assistance, as well as to all participants in the study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>WAN designed the study, collected and analysed the data, and developed the manuscript. AJL and AW improved the manuscript and contributed to the project design. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Research partially funded through grants made to the Cape Leopard Trust by the Wilderness Foundation Africa and the Hans Hoheisen Charitable Trust.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The dataset supporting the conclusions of this article is included within the article (and its additional file).</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par50">Prior oral consent was obtained from all participants to the study, and ethics approval was secured from the Stellenbosch University ethics committee (Humanities): Reference: CEE-2018-6251.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par51">All authors gave consent for publication, and there was no use of personal data in the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par52">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional healing with animals (zootherapy): medieval to present-day Levantine practice</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(02)00377-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12576209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betlu</surname><given-names>ALS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge of zootherapeutic use among the Biate tribe of Dima Hasao District, Assam, Northeastern India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-56</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23938109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of &#x02018;African Chemists&#x02019; in the health care system of the Eastern Cape province of South Africa</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-9536(00)00050-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11077953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why study the use of animal products in traditional medicines?</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed.</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-1-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16270931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibbitts</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animals traded for traditional medicine at the Faraday market in South Africa: species diversity and conservation implications</article-title><source>J Zool</source><year>2011</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7998.2010.00784.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A picture of health? Animal use and the Faraday traditional medicine market, South Africa</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.12.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26727647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of animal products in traditional Chinese medicine: environmental impact and health hazards</article-title><source>Complement Ther Med.</source><year>2003</year><volume>2299</volume><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0965-2299(03)00055-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahawar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaroli</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional zootherapeutic studies in India: a review</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed.</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-4-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18634551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes-</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>NAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trade of medicinal animals in Brazil: current status and perspectives</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv.</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-013-0475-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The faunal drugstore: animal-based remedies used in traditional medicines in Latin America</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed.</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-7-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>ETF</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkwill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of incidence-based species richness estimators, species accumulation curves and similarity measures to appraise ethnobotanical inventories from South Africa</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2495</fpage><lpage>2513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-006-9026-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shackleton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will the real custodian of natural resource management please stand up</article-title><source>S Afr J Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>93</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berglund A-I. Zulu thought-patterns and symbolism. C. Hurst &#x00026; Co. Publishers; 1976.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bye</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The inappropriate use of traditional medicines in South Africa</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1991</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(91)90044-E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1795529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simelane</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><source>The traditional use of indigenous vertebrates</source><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on plant usage in Xhosa and Zulu medicine</article-title><source>Bothalia.</source><year>1989</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cunningham AB, Zondi AS. Use of animal parts for the commercial trade in traditional medicines: University of Natal, Institute of Natural Resources; 1991.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntuli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Diederichs</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavundla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economics of the traditional medicine trade in South Africa: health care delivery. South African Heal Rev</article-title><source>Health Systems Trust (HST)</source><year>2007</year><volume>2007</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>196</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mander M. Marketing of indigenous medicinal plants in South Africa: a case study in KwaZulu-Natal: FAO; 1998.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philander</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotany of Western Cape Rasta bush medicine</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2011.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22004893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics South Africa</collab></person-group><source>Statistical release (Revised) Census 2011</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>AJE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hockings</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Bush doctors and wild medicine&#x0201d;: the scale of trade in cape town&#x02019;s informal economy of wild-harvested medicine and traditional healing</article-title><source>Soc Nat Resour</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08941920.2013.861558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics South Africa</collab></person-group><source>Annual Report 2014 / 15</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cawston</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Native medicines in Natal</article-title><source>South African Med J</source><year>1933</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>371</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Merging pharmacopoeia: understanding the historical origins of incorporative pharmacopoeial processes among Xhosa healers in Southern Africa</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1991</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(91)90083-P</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1921420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anyinam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology and ethnomedicine: exploring links between current environmental crisis and indigenous medical practices</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0277-9536(94)E0098-D</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7899944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">White RM, Cocks M, Herbert DG, Hamer ML. Traditional medicines from forest animals. Indig For Woodlands South Africa People. Policy Pract. 2004:474&#x02013;7 University of Natal Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mkhize</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source>Invertebrate animals as a component of the traditional medicine trade in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>African Invertebr</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Council of the Natal Museum</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The doctrine of signatures in the medieval and Ottoman Levant</article-title><source>Vesalius.</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12422877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12422877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKean</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A directory of animal species used for traditional medicine in KwaZulu-Natal</article-title><source>Ezemvelo KZN Wildl Intern Report 41&#x02009;pp</source><year>1995</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derwent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twitchers bewitched. The use of birds in traditional healing</article-title><source>Africa Birds Bird.</source><year>1997</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ngwenya MP. Implications for the medicinal animal trade for nature conservation in KwaZulu-Natal. Unpubl Ezimvelo KZN Wildl Rep no NA/124/04. 2001;</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simelane</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerley</surname><given-names>GIH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation implications of the use of vertebrates by Xhosa traditional healers in South Africa</article-title><source>South African J Wildl Res delayed open access. Southern African Wildlife Management Association (SAWMA)</source><year>1998</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Cock</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Briers</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bark collecting at Tootabie Nature Reserve, eastern Cape, South Africa</article-title><source>South African J Bot</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0254-6299(16)30800-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hutchings A. Zulu medicinal plants: an inventory: University of Natal press; 1996.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittemyer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>ACO</given-names></name><name><surname>Brashares</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerated human population growth at protected area edges. Science (80- )</article-title><source>Ame Assoc Adv Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>126</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics South Africa</collab></person-group><source>Annual Report 2016-2017</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>du P BJ, du Toit JG</collab></person-group><source>Game ranch management</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>South Africa Van Schaik</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Turner AA. Western Cape Province state of biodiversity: Cape Nature Scientific Services; 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkwill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>ETF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muthi traders on the Witwatersrand, South Africa-an urban mosaic</article-title><source>South African J Bot</source><year>1997</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0254-6299(15)30789-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Research methods in anthropology: qualitative and quantitative approaches (Altamira, Oxford)</source><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumby</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Benitez-Capistros</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Derrick</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A methodological guide to using and reporting on interviews in conservation science research</article-title><source>Methods Ecol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Handling of nonresponse error in the Journal of International Agricultural and Extension Education</article-title><source>J Int Agric Ext Educ.</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamashiro</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o-Filho</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of plant uses in two Cai&#x000e7;ara communities from the Atlantic Forest coast, Brazil</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008920301824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of ecological methods in ethnobotany: diversity indices</article-title><source>Econ Bot. Springer</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>280</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02907333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>ETF</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkwill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of diversity indices to appraise plant availability in the traditional medicinal markets of Johannesburg, South Africa</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2971</fpage><lpage>3001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-004-0256-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating terrestrial biodiversity through extrapolation</article-title><source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B</source><year>1994</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1994.0091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7972351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotelli</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying biodiversity: procedures and pitfalls in the measurement and comparison of species richness</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1461-0248.2001.00230.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating species richness: the second-order jackknife reconsidered</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1991</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1941127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ludwig JA, Reynolds JF. Statistical ecology: a primer in methods and computing: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons; 1988.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trotter RT, Logan MH. Informant consensus: a new approach for identifying potentially effective medicinal plants. Plants Indig Med diet Biobehav approaches. 1986:91.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From cnidarians to mammals: the use of animals as remedies in fishing communities in NE Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16621379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sticher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants in Mexico: Healers&#x02019; consensus and cultural importance</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0277-9536(98)00181-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9877354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bates MF, Branch WR, Bauer AM, Burger M, Marais J, Alesander GJ, et al. Atlas and red list of the reptiles of South Africa, Lesotho and Swaziland: South African National Biodiversity Institute; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>KL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>van Belle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Simberloff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Explicit calculation of the rarefaction diversity measurement and the determination of sufficient sample size</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1975</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1934716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toti</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A structured inventory of Appalachian grass bald and heath bald spider assemblages and a test of species richness estimator performance</article-title><source>J Arachnol</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1636/0161-8202(2000)028[0329:ASIOAG]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magurran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Measuring biological diversity</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing, UK</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of fauna in the traditional medicine of native Toba (qom) from the Argentine Gran Chaco region: an ethnozoological and conservationist approach</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv.</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Petersen LM, Moll EJ, Collins R, Hockings MT. Development of a compendium of local, wild-harvested species used in the informal economy trade, Cape Town, South Africa. Ecol Soc. JSTOR; 2012;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>Felipe Silva</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>Ulysses Paulino</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>Henrique Douglas Melo</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>Walt&#x000e9;cio de Oliveira</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R&#x000f4;mulo Romeu da N&#x000f3;brega</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Trade in Medicinal Animals in Northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/126938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>AAF</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal-based folk remedies sold in public markets in Crato and Juazeiro do Norte, Cear&#x000e1;, Brazil</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med.</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-9-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19144128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallaher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance indices in ethnobotany</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17348/era.5.0.201-218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nekaris</surname><given-names>KAI</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional use of slow lorises Nycticebus bengalensis and N. pygmaeus in Cambodia: an impediment to their conservation</article-title><source>Endanger Species Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/esr00285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruyns</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risks to birds traded for African traditional medicine: a quantitative assessment</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e105397</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25162700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pujol J. Natur Africa. Jean Pujol Natural Healers Foundation; 1990.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandita</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is &#x0201c;the doctrine of signatures&#x0201d; signature sequences designed by god?</article-title><source>Int J Sci Res Publ.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>572</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A stated preference investigation into the Chinese demand for farmed vs. wild bear bile</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e21243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21799733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perception, price and preference: Consumption and protection of wild animals used in traditional medicine</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0145901</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26930487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanach</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Matema</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matema</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mupamhadzi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Muvengwi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Dynamics and underlying causes of illegal bushmeat trade in Zimbabwe</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Oryx</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williams VL. Hawkers of health: an investigation of the Faraday Street traditional medicine market in Johannesburg, Gauteng. Plant Ecol Conserv Ser. 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krebs CJ. Ecological methodology: Harper &#x00026; Row New York; 1989.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alves RRN, Rosa IL, Albuquerque UP, Cunningham AB. Medicine from the wild: an overview of the use and trade of animal products in traditional medicines. Anim Tradit Folk Med. 2013:25&#x02013;42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warchol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transnational illegal wildlife trade</article-title><source>Crim Justice Stud.</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08884310420001679334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between fauna and people and the role of ethnozoology in animal conservation</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv.</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nowell K, Jackson P. Wild cats: status survey and conservation action plan: IUCN Gland; 1996.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zigouris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Setting conservation and research priorities for larger African carnivores</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wildlife Conservation Society</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fa</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bushmeat and human health: assessing evidence in tropical and sub-tropical forests the</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv.</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seimenis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The spread of zoonoses and other infectious diseases through the international trade of animals and animal products</article-title><source>Vet Ital.</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20411486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20411486</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>