<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-17683</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Systematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Taxonomy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phylogeny and Taxonomy of the Round-Eared Sengis or Elephant-Shrews, Genus <italic>Macroscelides</italic> (Mammalia, Afrotheria, Macroscelidea)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Taxonomic Revision of <italic>Macroscelides</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dumbacher</surname><given-names>John P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>Galen B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>Hanneline A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eiseb</surname><given-names>Seth J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Vertebrate Zoology and Anthropology, California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, University of California, Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Botany and Zoology, University of Stellenbosch, Matieland, South Africa</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>National Museum of Namibia, Windhoek, Namibia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Steinke</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Biodiversity Insitute of Ontario - University of Guelph, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>jdumbacher@calacademy.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JPD GBR HAS. Performed the experiments: JPD HAS GBR. Analyzed the data: JPD GBR HAS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JPD GBR SE. Wrote the paper: JPD GBR HAS SE.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e32410</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Dumbacher et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The round-eared sengis or elephant-shrews (genus <italic>Macroscelides</italic>) exhibit striking pelage variation throughout their ranges. Over ten taxonomic names have been proposed to describe this variation, but currently only two taxa are recognized (<italic>M. proboscideus proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>). Here, we review the taxonomic history of <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, and we use data on the geographic distribution, morphology, and mitochondrial DNA sequence to evaluate the current taxonomy. Our data support only two taxa that correspond to the currently recognized subspecies <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. Mitochondrial haplotypes of these two taxa are reciprocally monophyletic with over 13&#x00025; uncorrected sequence divergence between them. PCA analysis of 14 morphological characters (mostly cranial) grouped the two taxa into non-overlapping clusters, and body mass alone is a relatively reliable distinguishing character throughout much of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> range. Although fieldworkers were unable to find sympatric populations, the two taxa were found within 50 km of each other, and genetic analysis showed no evidence of gene flow. Based upon corroborating genetic data, morphological data, near sympatry with no evidence of gene flow, and differences in habitat use, we elevate these two forms to full species.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Systematists agree that the sengis or elephant-shrews represent a monophyletic family (Macroscelididae) and order (Macroscelidea) of endemic African mammals <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, with a highly distinctive evolutionary history and ecology <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. However, the taxonomic placement of the order has proven difficult to resolve because many aspects of their morphology are unique and not similar to most other mammals <xref rid="pone.0032410-Patterson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Seiffert1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In the 1990s, analyses of proteins and DNA indicated that the sengis were most likely part of a relatively ancient radiation of African mammals that included several seemingly improbable clades. Now, the molecular evidence is overwhelmingly supportive of Afrotheria <xref rid="pone.0032410-Springer1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, which includes the long-recognized Paenungulata (elephants, hyraxes, and sea cows) along with the tenrecs and golden moles (order Afrosoricida), the aardvark (order Tubulidentata), and sengis (order Macroscelidea). The morphological evidence for the Afrotheria, however, continues to be weak <xref rid="pone.0032410-Seiffert1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, which is likely related to the approximately 105 million years that have passed since the isolation and divergence of the various afrotheres in Africa <xref rid="pone.0032410-Hedges1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p><p>The first sengi was discovered by Western scientists at the turn of the 18<sup>th</sup> C., and subsequently dozens of forms were described. The taxonomy and distribution of the various extant sengi species was reviewed and revised by Corbet and Hanks in their seminal monograph <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Currently, biologists recognize only 17 extant species in the order Macroscelidea <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. The forest-dwelling giant sengis (subfamily Rhynchocyoninae with a single genus <italic>Rhynchocyon</italic>) includes four relatively distinct species. The soft-furred sengis (subfamily Macroscelidinae) mostly occur in arid habitats and include three genera (the monospecific <italic>Macroscelides</italic> and <italic>Petrodromus</italic>, and 11 species of <italic>Elephantulus</italic>).</p><p>One of the main taxonomic challenges has been resolving the sometimes minor and often cryptic phenotypic cranial and pelage differences among the many described forms. The availability of molecular techniques has changed this by clarifying taxonomic relationships that were not previously recognized, especially in the genus <italic>Elephantulus</italic> that contains morphologically similar species (e.g., <italic>E. pilicaudus</italic> from the Nama-Karoo in South Africa; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>). However, genetic analyses have not yet been applied to many of the various forms of <italic>Rhynchocyon</italic>, which tend to be more easily distinguished morphologically (e.g., the recently described gray-faced sengi <italic>Rhynchocyon udzungwensis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Rovero1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rovero2" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>).</p><p>Here, we focus on members of the genus <italic>Macroscelides</italic> (round-eared sengis, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), which are small (body weight 35&#x02013;50 g, head and body length 104&#x02013;115 mm) compared to species in the other three sengi genera <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. They show little to no sexual dimorphism with respect to weight or external body measures <xref rid="pone.0032410-Skinner1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Also, <italic>Macroscelides</italic> has a distinctively large head (due to remarkably large auditory bullae), with short and rounded ears <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, and relatively long, dense, and soft fur. Similar to other sengi genera, <italic>Macroscelides</italic> has large eyes, a long flexible nose, a mouse-like tail, and long spindly legs that are associated with a swift saltatorial gait <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. <italic>Macroscelides</italic> is crepuscular, with an omnivorous diet <xref rid="pone.0032410-Kerley1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> dominated by invertebrate prey. Like other members of the subfamily Macroscelidinae, <italic>Macroscelides</italic> produces small litters of highly precocial neonates and does not build or use a nest, but rather shelters in shallow burrows, among boulders, or at the bases of bushes <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sauer1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. <italic>Macroscelides</italic> is monogamous <xref rid="pone.0032410-Schubert1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and can occupy home ranges of up to a square kilometer <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sauer1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. <italic>Macroscelides</italic> is distributed from northwestern Namibia south through eastern South Africa, and occurs in extreme southwestern Botswana (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0032410-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>
<italic>Macroscelides</italic> from Namibia and South Africa.</title><p>A (top). <italic>Macroscelides proboscideus flavicaudatus</italic> captured in the Namib Desert at Wlotzkasbaken, Namibia, on 25 May 2000 (photo by GBR). B (bottom). <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> captured in the Nama-Karoo at Loxton Commonage, Northern Cape, South Africa, on 21 March 2007 (Photo courtesy of Chris and Mathilde Stuart). Note the light coloration of the animal from the Namib Desert compared to the specimen from the Nama-Karoo.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032410.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone-0032410-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Map of southern Africa, showing the range of <italic>Macroscelides</italic>.</title><p>Localities of specimens used in our analyses are shown (see legend and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). The Okahandja and Isabis localities (square and star symbols in central Namibia) of <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> are of questionable validity (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>), so we have not included them when calculating the distribution polygon. The arrow points to the area of potential overlap of <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, between specimen localities on Gorassis (triangle) and Zwartmodder (circle) farms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032410.g002"/></fig><p>
<italic>Macroscelides</italic> is currently treated as a monotypic genus, although this masks a more complicated taxonomic history: In the 19<sup>th</sup> century, four species of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> were described: <italic>Sorex proboscideus</italic> (Shaw 1800) <xref rid="pone.0032410-Shaw1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>; <italic>Macroscelides typus</italic> Smith 1829 <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, which was renamed <italic>Macroscelides typicus</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smith2" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>; <italic>Rhinomys jaculus</italic> (Lichtenstein 1831) <xref rid="pone.0032410-Lichtenstein1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>; and <italic>Macroscelides melanotis</italic> Ogilby 1838 <xref rid="pone.0032410-Ogilby1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Roberts <xref rid="pone.0032410-Roberts1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> revised the genus, recognizing <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> (with nine subspecies) and <italic>M. melanotis</italic>. Subsequently, Lundholm <xref rid="pone.0032410-Lundholm1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> described a new (tenth) subspecies, <italic>M. proboscideus flavicaudatus</italic> from western Namibia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t001">Table 1</xref>). Corbet and Hanks <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> only recognized a single species (<italic>M. proboscideus</italic>) with two subspecies, <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> from western Namibia and <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> from South Africa and southern Namibia, which is larger with darker pelage. Corbet and Hanks <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> suspected the variation in pelage coloration was clinal, with differences presumably being adaptations to local habitats; <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> being adapted to finer light-colored substrates, while <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> being adapted to darker substrates and more complex shaded habitats. Similar geographic variation in coloration has been described for <italic>Elephantulus rufescens</italic> in East Africa <xref rid="pone.0032410-Kingdon1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0032410-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Named taxa of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> in chronological order with contemporary descriptions of type localities <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Roberts1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032410-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0032410.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type Locality</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Sorex proboscideus</italic> Shaw, 1800</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cape of Good Hope (&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Roodewal, Oudtshoorn Division, Western Cape)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typus</italic> A. Smith, 1829</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interior of South Africa (&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Roodewal, Oudtshoorn Division, Western Cape)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Rhinomys jaculus</italic> Lichtenstein, 1831</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East coast South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides melanotis</italic> Ogilby, 1838</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Damaraland, Namibia</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus</italic> A. Smith 1838</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correct spelling of M. typus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus hewitti</italic> Roberts, 1929</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cradock, Eastern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus chiversi</italic> Roberts,1933</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 km N. Upington, Northern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus langi</italic> Roberts, 1933</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vlermuisklip, Van Rhynsdorp District, Western Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus ausensis</italic> Roberts, 1938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 km N. Aus, Namibia</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus brandvleinsis</italic> Roberts, 1938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brandvlei, Great Bushmanland, Northern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus calvinensis</italic> Roberts, 1938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 km E. Calvinia, Northern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus harei</italic> Roberts, 1938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brospan, mid-way between Brandvlei and Van Wyk's Blei, Great Bushmanland, Northern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides typicus isabellinus</italic> Shortridge &#x00026; Carter, 1938</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Port Nolloth, Northern Cape, South Africa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus proboscideus</italic> Allen, 1939</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cape of Good Hope</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus flavicaudatus</italic> Lundholm, 1955</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 km from mouth Omaruru River, Namibia</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Note that <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> is a synonym of <italic>Sorex proboscideus</italic>, but both are listed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>While carrying out research on the behavioral ecology of sengis in Namibia <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun2" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, GBR and colleague Michael Griffin encountered several <italic>Macroscelides</italic> specimens from northern Namibia having darker pelage than expected, and contrasting with nearby lighter representatives of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. Additionally, other oddly colored specimens were found in the collection of the National Museum of Namibia, such as a grayish specimen (NMN 2539) from a farm (Otmarsbaum 120) near Warmbad in south central Namibia (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>). Concurrent with the fieldwork by GBR, HS began examining genetic variation in several southern African sengis, including <italic>Macroscelides</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit3" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>; we agreed to combine our efforts to explore the taxonomy of the genus.</p><p>With a larger and more diverse series of specimens than were available to Corbet and Hanks <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, we suspected that the size and light/dark distinction between <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> was not strictly clinal, and thus deserved greater attention. Based on our preliminary observations of sengis from northern Namibia that superficially resembled <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>, we hypothesized that they were either indeed closely related to <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> from South Africa (and thus represented a remarkable range extension), or they were a genetic cluster that had a unique biogeographic history (a new taxon), or that the difference in pelage color would represent adaptation to local substrates with only minor genetic differentiation (e.g., Corbet and Hanks' <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> suggestion of a cline).</p><p>To resolve these observations and hypotheses, we examined the phenotypic and mitochondrial DNA variation in the genus from the extremes of its distribution, including the morphological range of color and size differences. We included localities that provided previously named taxa, and the area where hybrid forms or clinal variation was most likely to occur. In this paper, we present our results and revise the current taxonomy for the genus <italic>Macroscelides</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All field procedures involving live animals met the standards for the ethical and humane treatment of animals of the American Society of Mammalogists <xref rid="pone.0032410-Gannon1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Vouchered animals were euthanized using cervical dislocation, as approved by the 2000 American Veterinary Medical Association guidelines <xref rid="pone.0032410-Amass1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. All fieldwork was performed under Research/Collecting Permit number 1177/2007 issued by the Namibian Ministry of Environment and Tourism (NMET) to JPD, and permit number 1131/2007 to GBR. Materials were legally exported under NMET export permit number 63501 to GBR.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Distribution</title><p>We used localities of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> (N&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;118) gleaned from museum collections, published papers, reports, and personal communications with biologists in the field <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun3" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. We then constructed a distribution polygon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) using the localized convex hull (LoCoH) method <xref rid="pone.0032410-Getz1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Getz2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. After applying several different K values (number of nearest neighbor hulls), we subjectively rejected those distributions with strange fragmentation and perimeters, and chose the polygon in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, which has a K value of 20. To reduce visual clutter, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Figure 2</xref> shows only the localities of specimens that we used in our genetic and morphological analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>), and thus many localities are not shown and some polygon corners do not include the symbol that defines them.</p><p>The latitude and longitude (presented throughout as decimal degrees south and east for all locations) for most of the voucher specimens originally analyzed and reported by HS <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> were based on the nearest town to the recorded collection location. We have georeferenced all specimens using locations from specimen labels or museum catalogs to better estimate their collection locality (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>), resulting in greater accuracy in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Figure 2</xref>. For specimens that we collected, we georeferenced them in the field using handheld GPS units. Specimens in museum collections that contained only farm names were given the locality of the centroid of the farm shape, with the farm shape as the error. Some localities were estimated by locating the position (town or village) in the program Google Earth 5.1, and obtaining a fix. All latitude and longitude coordinates use the map datum WGS84.</p><p>We were suspicious of the collection locality for a pair of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> specimens labeled as &#x0201c;Okahandja, Namibia&#x0201d; from the Ditsong National Museum of Natural History (Transvaal Museum) in Pretoria, South Africa, and collected in 1950 by Walter Hoesch. Because there is no past or present farm with this name in Namibia that we are aware of, we assume that this location refers to the major town with this name. HS amplified archival tissue from one of these specimens (TM10213) and found it to be <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>. As this would be an exceptional record for this taxon, we wanted to critically evaluate its validity. The habitat near Okahandja town is unusual for this species, it being too mesic and lacking the gravel plains that <italic>Macroscelides</italic> typically occupies. In addition, the town is approximately 325 km north of the nearest other <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> vouchered specimen location. Recent small mammal collectors (SJE pers. obs.; C. Coetzee and M. Griffin, pers. comm.) have not captured <italic>Macroscelides</italic> near Okahandja. The Ditsong museum accession numbers indicate that the specimens were accessioned out of collection order (Teresa Kearney, pers. comm.) and entered into the collection with rodents that Hoesh collected on Farm Isabis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), some 70 km west of Rehoboth. Farm Isabis is considerably closer to the known distribution of <italic>Macroscelides</italic>. Although it is possible that Hoesch mislabeled specimens that were actually collected on Farm Isabis, his list of field numbers, dates, and locations do not support this. Adding to the confusion, none of his four publications on mammals in Namibia, which include information on sengis and their distributions, make reference to the Okahandja <italic>Macroscelides</italic> specimens <xref rid="pone.0032410-Hoesch1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Hoesch2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Hoesch3" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Hoesch4" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. In further trying to resolve the collection locality of these two <italic>Macroscelides</italic> specimens, we discovered that Hoesch lost ownership of his farm northeast of Okahandja during the Great Depression and spent the rest of his career living on other farms, tutoring farm children and collecting and selling biological specimens to museums <xref rid="pone.0032410-Anonymous1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. All these circumstances suggest that his sengi specimens may have been collected nearly anywhere in central Namibia. Because of the confusion over the locality of Hoesch's Okahandja specimens, we have not included them in our geographical analyses, however their location would be a significant range extension for <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>, if the Okahandja location could be confirmed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Specimen collection in the field</title><p>To augment specimens already available to us from museum collections, in June 2007 GBR and JPD visited Namibia to collect additional material. Our choice of trapping locations was based on the proximity of the two subspecies of <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, where we wanted to search for a contact zone or hybrid zone. We successfully captured sengis on Zwartmodder Farm (&#x02212;24.9136&#x000b0;, 16.2703&#x000b0;) near the town of Maltahohe, and on Gorassis Farm (&#x02212;24.9112&#x000b0;, 16.2701&#x000b0;) in the NamibRand Nature Reserve (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). These two farms are about 50 km apart, and portions of the intervening gravel plains habitat appeared suitable for <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, so we trapped on Keerveeder Farm (&#x02212;24.9489&#x000b0;, 16.0394&#x000b0;) and Toekoms Research Station (&#x02212;25.0357&#x000b0;, 16.0951&#x000b0;). Keerveeder is located roughly 22 km southwest from Zwartmodder Farm and Toekoms is approximately 35 kilometers northeast from Gorassis Farm.</p><p>We used folding aluminum Sherman live traps (8&#x000d7;9&#x000d7;23 cm) baited with a dry mixture of rolled oats, peanut butter, and Marmite (a savory yeast spread). Traps were set in transects of varying lengths with 10&#x02013;20 m trap spacing. We activated the traps in late afternoon and checked them early the next morning to avoid the heat of the day. Voucher specimens were prepared as standard museum study skins with associated cranial and postcranial material, and fresh muscle and liver were preserved in 95&#x00025; ethanol in the field and frozen upon return to USA.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Genetic analyses</title><p>Our final genetic sample included a total of 78 <italic>Macroscelides</italic> individuals and one outgroup taxon, of which 43 were represented by tissues taken from dried museum specimens, and 35 from fresh preserved tissue (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>). Sampling localities were distributed throughout the range of the genus in Namibia and South Africa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). We had more samples of <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> than <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, in part because of the difference in the extent of their distributions and in historical collecting. DNA sequences from 56 of our specimens (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>) were included in a phylogeographic study of <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> GenBank accession numbers EF141697&#x02013;EF141822).</p><p>Total genomic DNA was extracted from alcohol-preserved frozen tissue, using a commercial DNA extraction kit (DNeasy Tissue Kit, Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA). DNA from museum specimens (&#x0003c;60 years old, hereafter called archival DNA) was extracted from traditional study skins and preferentially clipped from the lip or belly skin. In some cases, tissue remnants were taken from within the skull cavity of skulls housed in museum collections. Archival DNA extractions and PCR setup were done in a dedicated &#x0201c;ancient DNA&#x0201d; facility separated from other DNA labs and all post-PCR material <xref rid="pone.0032410-Wandeler1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Some archival samples were extracted and amplified in the laboratory of JPD at California Academy of Sciences, and some by HS in the Evolutionary Genomics laboratory of T. J. Robinson and B. van Vuuren at Stellenbosch University. Extractions followed phenol/chloroform separation, and DNA was rinsed and concentrated using gravity-assisted dialysis in centricon spin columns. Extraction and PCR controls were included in all PCR experiments to test for contamination. For archival DNA, at least two independent PCR reactions were run to confirm consistent and repeatable results. See Smit <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> and Dumbacher et al. <xref rid="pone.0032410-Dumbacher1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Dumbacher2" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> for details on the laboratory extraction procedures used.</p><p>For PCR reactions, we used manufacturer's buffer (1&#x000d7;) as well as final concentrations of 1 &#x000b5;M primers, 1.2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.25 mM dNTPs, and 0.8 units Taq polymerase in 25 &#x000b5;l reactions in 0.2 ml tubes. Bovine serum albumin (final concentration from 0.8 to 3 mg/ml) was routinely added to amplifications to counteract PCR inhibitors present in the archival DNA samples. Amplifications used a thermal profile involving an initial denaturation step of 3&#x02013;10 min at 95&#x000b0;C followed by 35 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 50&#x000b0;C for 30 s and 72&#x000b0;C for 60 s. Amplifications were completed with a final 5 to 7 min extension step at 72&#x000b0;C. Primers were specially designed to amplify most of the mitochondrial protein coding Cytochrome <italic>b</italic> (Cyt <italic>b</italic>) gene and a fragment of the hypervariable Control Region [CR]. Primer sequences are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t002">Table 2</xref>. Extracts made from fresh DNA could be amplified using longer pieces. Cyt <italic>b</italic> primers MPL1-MPH3 (1034 base pairs) and F14164-R15181 (a 1016 base pair segment) were used to amplify roughly the same region of Cyt <italic>b</italic>. Degraded DNA, as found in extracts made from museum voucher specimens, required shorter amplifications, and were primed with MPL1-MPH1 (301 bases), MPL2-MPH2 (432 bases), and MPL3-MPH3 (302 bases), in three separate amplifications <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. CR sequences were amplified with MPN1-MPD1 (338 bases) <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Sequencing reactions were performed using BigDye chemistry (version 3; Applied Biosystems) and analyzed on a 3100 ABI automated sequencer. Electropherograms of the raw sequences were examined and edited with Sequencher software version 4.8 through 4.10 (Gene Codes Corporation). Consensus sequences were created for each individual, aligned with Sequencher, and exported as Nexus files for further analysis.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0032410-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Primers used for PCR experiments.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032410-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0032410.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Name</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Sequence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target Gene</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F14164</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GAAAARYCATCGTTGTAHTTCAACTA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Springer2" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R15181</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ACWGGTTGDCCDCCRATTCAKGT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Springer2" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPL1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AATCACACCCATTACTCAAAA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPL2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TATCTACTACGGCTCCTA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPL3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AGACCCAGACAATTATA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPH1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GGCTACTCCGATGTTT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPH2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GTATAATTGTCTGGGTCT</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPH3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTAGGATTAATAKGAARTA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPN1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CCACCATCAGCACCCAA</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPD1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GTATAGTTCCGGTATAGAAACCCC</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Individuals of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> were found to have two distinct copies of the Cyt <italic>b</italic> gene. To determine which was most likely the orthologous functional mitochondrial copy, we used the following techniques: 1) we searched for stop codons or frame-shift mutations that indicate a non-functional paralog, 2) we examined chromatograms for double bases that might indicate the presence of a nuclear paralog with two different alleles in a heterozygous individual, 3) we examined rates of evolution at codon positions to check whether third positions evolved most rapidly and second positions were highly conserved, as would be expected in a functional gene under selection, 4) we examined whether one gene copy had significantly slower or faster substitution rates that may indicate a nuclear paralog <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sorenson1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, using a Chi-squared test for significant differences in rates, and finally 5) we attempted longer PCR reactions using the most upstream Cyt <italic>b</italic> primers (MPL1 and F14164) and the most distant CR primer (MPD1), to amplify the largest fragment possible, and potentially identify pseudogene copies that are often smaller or that have insertions, deletions, or other problems. Because we had no evidence of any duplication in the CR region, we expected that amplifying from Cyt <italic>b</italic> through CR should also yield a single amplification product. The overall length of this amplification product was expected to be approximately 1250 bases.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Mitochondrial DNA data analyses</title><p>DNA sequences were imported into PAUP&#x0002a; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Swofford1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, and we used jModeltest <xref rid="pone.0032410-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Posada1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> to determine the best fit model of evolution using the Akaike Information Criterion corrected for small samples (AICc). Site-specific rate models were compared with the best-performing model from jModeltest using AICc. Maximum likelihood (ML) searches were run in PAUP&#x0002a;4b10 for unix using the successive iterations technique to estimate model parameters, then estimate the likelihood tree, re-estimate parameters, and so on until the parameters and tree no longer change between iterations. To estimate the support for various nodes in the tree, we used both ML fast-addition bootstrap analyses in PAUP&#x0002a; and a Bayesian approach using the program MrBayes 3.1 <xref rid="pone.0032410-Huelsenbeck1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> run on an x-serve cluster.</p><p>Phylogenetic relationships and reciprocally-monophyletic taxonomic status were established for <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. Intra- and inter-population divergences (uncorrected p-distances) as well as the number of variable and parsimony-informative sites were calculated using PAUP&#x0002a; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Swofford1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Morphological comparisons</title><p>We used 14 morphological measurements in a principal components analysis to determine if there were morphological differences among taxa. Using dial calipers calibrated to 0.1 mm, we took the following measurements in the field from captured specimens: tail length (excluding terminal hairs, from distal tip of tail to the base of the tail held at vertical right angle to dorsal aspect of head and body) and hind foot (typically the right foot from the hind edge of heel to the distal tip of the longest claw). For existing museum specimens, we took these measurements from museum tags. The following measurements were taken from prepared skulls using handheld dial calipers calibrated to 0.1 mm (for bilateral elements, the right side was used if present, and the left side was used if the right was damaged or absent, and followed the guidelines and landmarks recommended in DeBlase and Martin <xref rid="pone.0032410-DeBlase1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>): greatest length of skull (from the most anterior part of the rostrum to the posterior most point on the skull), greatest zygomatic breadth, least interorbital breadth, greatest breadth of braincase, height of rostrum (taken at the suture between the premaxilla and maxilla), width of bulla, greatest alveolar length of upper toothrow (including canine and incisors), greatest breadth of palate, greatest height of skull, greatest alveolar length of mandibular tooth row, height of the mandible, and greatest length of the mandible. We excluded young individuals identified by incomplete eruption of the last molars (M2) from the maxilla. Individuals with missing measurements (usually because of incomplete data on museum tags or missing or broken skull elements) also were excluded from the analysis. We analyzed the resulting data using principle components analysis and canonical linear discriminant analysis (STATA for MacIntosh, version 10.0, StataCorp, College Station, Texas).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Specimen collection in the field</title><p>At Zwartmodder Farm, during 172 trap nights, we captured four <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>, 12 <italic>Elephantulus intufi</italic>, and 41 rodents. At Gorassis Farm, we had 145 trap nights and captured six <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, two <italic>Elephantulus rupestris</italic>, and 19 rodents. <italic>Macroscelides</italic> were captured on relatively flat gravel plains with some structure and cover provided by small washes and scattered fist-sized rocks and cinderblock-sized boulders. Vegetation was sparse and included widely spaced dry bunch grasses and small shrubs less than 30 cm high. The gravel plains were often separated by more sandy areas or rock outcrops and mountains, which were not occupied by <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, but rather the bushveld sengi (<italic>E. intufi</italic>) or western rock sengi (<italic>E. rupestris</italic>), respectively. <italic>Macroscelides</italic> was only trapped on one transect at Zwartmodder Farm, and here it occurred with the bushveld sengi (<italic>E. intufi</italic>), which is normally associated with relatively flat sandy substrates that support sparse to dense bush cover. At this Zwartmodder site, gravel and sandy substrates occurred close together and resulted in captures of both species within ca. 30 m of each other.</p><p>We found no <italic>Macroscelides</italic> on farms between the Zwartmodder and Gorassis sites. In 315 trap-nights on Keerveeder Farm and Toekoms Research Station, we captured no <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, five <italic>Elephantulus rupestris</italic>, and 87 rodents. Thus, we found no evidence of hybrid or sympatric populations between the closest populations of the two <italic>Macroscelides</italic> taxa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Sequence analyses and phylogenetics</title><p>Sequences for Cyt <italic>b</italic> were obtained to complement previous work done by HS and others <xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit4" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> and already on GenBank (accession numbers EF141757&#x02013;EF141822). Cyt <italic>b</italic> proved problematic in <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, and we often recovered double sequences using shorter amplifications with primers MPL1-MPH1, MPL2-MPH2, and MPL3-MPH3, and sometimes with longer reactions using MPL1-MPH3. Using fresh tissue samples and long PCR reactions, we obtained clean unambiguous sequences using primers F14164-R15181 and sometimes using MPL1-MPH3. The haplotype sequences from each primer set differed by up to 0.078 (HKY85 distance, average distance 0.073 between fragments from F14164-R15181 and MPL1-MPH3 amplifications). A preliminary gene tree clearly suggested a sequence duplication in the <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> lineage, and efforts were made to determine whether one represented a nuclear pseudogene. Neither copy contained stop codons or frame-shift mutations that sometimes indicate a paralogous pseudogene. Neither copy appeared to have double bases that might indicate the presence of two different alleles in a nuclear paralog. Patterns of codon usage were analyzed and showed that in both copies, third positions evolved most rapidly and second positions were highly conserved. Because nuclear DNA has slower mutation rates, copies with unusually slow evolutionary rates may indicate a nuclear paralog <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sorenson1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Although the MPL1-MPH3 copy evolved more slowly than the F14164-R15181 copy, branch lengths were not significantly shorter as to indicate a nuclear copy. We then used a PCR approach using the most upstream Cyt <italic>b</italic> primers (MPL1 and F14164) and the most distant CR primer (MPD1). Only F14164-MPD1 gave an amplification product. When sequenced, it corresponded with the F14164-R15181 copy, and the CR portion also corresponded perfectly with the other MPN1-MPD1-primed CR sequences. Thus, we eliminated the other copy from further analysis, and proceeded with the F14164-R15181 copy. We cannot conclude with certainty that the other copy is a nuclear pseuedogene; it is possible that this is a gene copy found in the mitochondrion.</p><p>Cyt <italic>b</italic> sequences obtained from <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> museum specimens were amplified in short segments, approximately 300&#x02013;400 bases. Each individual sequence clustered with one of the two <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> gene copies, confirming their correct taxonomic identification. For the purpose of the phylogenetic analyses, we used only the mitochondrial coding sequence, as identified by clustering with the F14164-R15181 copy in preliminary phylogenetic analsyes, and eliminated Cyt <italic>b</italic> sequences clustering with the duplicate Cyt <italic>b</italic> copy. This created gaps in the data matrix for these archival DNA samples, but avoided the possibility of creating chimeric sequences that used portions of each gene copy.</p><p>For an outgroup to <italic>Macroscelides</italic>, we used the only complete mitochondrial genome available from this order. The sequences are from an unidentified species of <italic>Elephantulus</italic> (GenBank number AB096867.1, <italic>Elephantulus</italic> sp.) <xref rid="pone.0032410-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. For Cyt <italic>b</italic> and CR, this genome most closely matches <italic>Elephantulus myurus</italic> sequences (98&#x00025;&#x02013;99&#x00025; similar) with which is it likely conspecific.</p><p>Using the AICc, jModeltest indicated a TIM2&#x0002b;I&#x0002b;G model of evolution with a model weight of 0.90. We additionally explored a TIM2&#x0002b;site specific rate model using the three codon positions of Cyt <italic>b</italic> and a fourth site for CR (SSR4). The site-specific rate model significantly outperformed all other models and received the model weight of 0.999. We used successive approximations of tree shape and parameters in PAUP&#x0002a; to find a single maximum likelihood estimate phylogeny given the TIM2&#x0002b;SSR4 models of evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Parameter estimates for this search are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t003">Table 3</xref>. The program MrBayes was run for ten million generations using the same TIM2&#x0002b;SSR4 model of sequence evolution, sampling every 1000 generations. We confirmed that the potential scale reduction factor (<italic>PSRF</italic>) converged to one for all parameters. For analyses, the results of the first three million generations were discarded as burn-in. The resulting tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) and parameter values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t003">Table 3</xref>) were similar to the maximum likelihood analysis run by PAUP&#x0002a;. The Bayesian posterior probabilities were calculated from the program MrBayes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g003">Figure 3</xref>. For both gene regions, <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> each formed well-supported clades that were reciprocally monophyletic.</p><fig id="pone-0032410-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Molecular phylogeny of <italic>Macroscelides</italic>.</title><p>Branch support is shown as Bayesian posterior probabilities (&#x000d7;100) followed by bootstrap values in 1000 fast-addition likelihood tree searches. Only Bayesian posteriors greater than 95 and bootstrap support greater than 70 are reported.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032410.g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0032410-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Parameter estimates from phylogenetic analyses.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032410-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0032410.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum likelihood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (MrBayes)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x00025; credible interval</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;Ln(likelihood)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4947.80616</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5126.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Base frequencies:</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308362</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304453</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28376&#x02013;0.325386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306745</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313918</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294273&#x02013;0.333866</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10933</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10606</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092488&#x02013;0.120346</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275564</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275569</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257436&#x02013;0.294444</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate matrix R:</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54978</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070678</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051396&#x02013;0.091749</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54285</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283505</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23189&#x02013;0.338771</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54978</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114535</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089641&#x02013;0.143007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053364</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027305&#x02013;0.086909</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3631</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387983</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339399&#x02013;0.438247</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089936</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052845&#x02013;0.135436</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Relative Site Rates:</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyt b position1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39758</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383505</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300655&#x02013;0.477924</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyt b position 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11616</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114631</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074023&#x02013;0.163621</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyt b position 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59399</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.645424</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.474685&#x02013;2.813977</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cont. Region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90202</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868631</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741192&#x02013;1.002187</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The greatest genetic distances for Cyt <italic>b</italic> within a <italic>Macroscelides</italic> subspecies were less than 2.0&#x00025; uncorrected <italic>p</italic>-distance (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t004">Table 4</xref>). The greatest distances within <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> were about 1.8&#x00025; between individuals from among the most southern populations from Laingsburg in the Western Cape and the most northern populations from Maltahohe District and Bethanie District, in southern Namibia. Within <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> maximum pairwise distances were similar at 1.7&#x00025;, and some of the greatest distances represent intrapopulation variation in the region near Gai-As, in the Khorixas District of the Kunene Region in northern Namibia.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0032410-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Summary of uncorrected p-distances within and between <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> based on combined data from the Cyt <italic>b</italic> gene and CR.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032410-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0032410.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncorrected p-distance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>M. p. flavicaudatus - M. p. proboscideus</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean distance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007742989</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009703737</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132743109</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std Deviation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004407687</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003252365</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003004266</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max distance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01684039</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01790324</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14120071</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min distance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12287391</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The differences between <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> were quite large. The minimum genetic divergence between <italic>M. p flavicaudatus</italic> and <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> was greater than 12&#x00025;, and some haplotypes differed as much as 14&#x00025; (uncorrected <italic>p</italic> distance). These are certainly underestimates of total divergence, as saturation and multiple substitutions are likely at these divergences. HKY85-corrected pairwise differences range from 13.7&#x00025; to 16&#x00025;. These differences suggest that the two taxa have been separated genetically for a significant period of time.</p><p>We examined the two copies of Cyt <italic>b</italic> within <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. As mentioned earlier, neither gene copies contained any frame shift mutations or stop codons that could indicate a pseudogene, and codon substitution patterns matched those of coding regions under selection (third positions evolved most rapidly and second positions were most conserved). Pairwise genetic distances between the two different gene copies of Cyt <italic>b</italic> within <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> ranged from 6.2&#x00025; to 7.3&#x00025;, and averaged 7.0&#x00025;. The duplication appears to have evolved after the split with <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>, as the distances were much less than the pairwise distance between the two subspecies, and the gene copy was never obtained from any <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> individual.</p><p>We confirmed the taxonomic identities of the two most geographically extreme specimens of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> collected from northern Namibia. These included the northern most location in Namibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g002">Fig. 2</xref>; NMN1454, a specimen with incomplete genetic data and thus not included in the complete phylogenetic analyses) and the specimen from nearest the coast (TM10499, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032410.s001">Table S1</xref>). For NMN1454, the Cyt <italic>b</italic> fragments, the Cyt <italic>b</italic> copy, and the CR sequences all clustered with <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. From the coastal specimen (TM10499), which is the type for <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, we only succeeded in sequencing CR, and this gene nested within the <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> clade. In addition, these two specimens both show the typical light-colored pelage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). This confirmed that <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> is the appropriate available name for this taxon and that it included all of the putative <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> specimens that we examined.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Morphological principal component analysis</title><p>Our final complete matrix of morphological data consisted of 31 specimens for 14 characters. We performed a principal components analysis on these data, and principal components axis 1 (PC1) explained 49.65&#x00025; of the variation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t005">Table 5</xref>). All but one variable had positive loadings in PC1, and 7 variables had loadings greater than 0.3. PC2 explained an additional 15.22&#x00025; of the variation. There is no overlap between the two taxa when plotted by PC1 and PC2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g004">Fig. 4</xref>), clearly demonstrating their separation in morphospace. The canonical linear discriminant analysis was significant (canonical correlation coefficient&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.9735, F&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;20.741, df1&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;14, df2&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;16, p&#x0003c;0.0001), and the primary canonical function properly classified each individual to taxon with 100&#x00025; accuracy. Thus, the morphological differences between these two taxonomic groups were significant and useful for distinguishing the taxa from each other.</p><fig id="pone-0032410-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Graphical representation of morphological multivariate analysis.</title><p>PC1 and PC2 are principal component axes. The numeral 1 denotes <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> individuals, and 2 denotes <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> individuals. The diagonal line highlights the graph region between the two putative species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032410.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0032410-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Summary of morphological Principal Component Analysis.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0032410-t005-5" xlink:href="pone.0032410.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC4</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tail</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0878</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4452</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1115</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hind Foot</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0541</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5612</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1826</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2495</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of skull</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3451</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1925</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0271</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zygomatic breadth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3506</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0264</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0463</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0565</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interorbital width</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0669</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0378</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1183</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breadth of braincase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2428</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.2888</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0173</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of rostrum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0618</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3637</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width of bulla</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4636</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1275</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper tooth row</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3614</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0414</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0593</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0362</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breadth of palate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2834</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1547</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0258</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of skull</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3526</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0544</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0067</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1398</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular tooth row</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3328</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0571</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0552</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0945</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of mandible</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0456</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0534</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of Mandible</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3617</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0174</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0495</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0827</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC Axis summary</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eigenvalue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of variation explained</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative proportion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.759</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.828</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Body mass was missing from many specimens, and this prohibited its inclusion in the principal component analysis. Nonetheless, we were interested in whether body mass was a useful character for determining the taxonomic status. We eliminated obvious immature individuals and performed a simple two-sample t-test with unequal variances. <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> (mean mass 31.5 g) was significantly lighter (p&#x0003c;0.01) than <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> (mean 39.0 g), although the overall ranges did overlap (<italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, 22&#x02013;46 g, n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;18; <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>, 31&#x02013;47 g, n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;13).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Distribution</title><p>The flat to gently sloping gravel plain habitats where we captured <italic>Macroscelides</italic> were consistent with reports in the literature on their habitat <xref rid="pone.0032410-Kerley1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sauer1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Schubert1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> that suggest <italic>Macroscelides</italic> is a habitat specialist (see Rathbun <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> for a summary of habitat associations for different sengi species). The elevation range for the two subspecies are similar: <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> occurs from sea level in the central Namib to 1400 m in southern Namibia, and <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> occurs from sea level in the Succulent Karoo to 1400 m in the Nama Karoo of South Africa. However, several habitat features appear to be distinctive for each <italic>Macroscelides</italic> taxon. Habitats where <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> occurs are &#x0201c;desert&#x0201d;, which includes the Namib and Pro Namib biomes <xref rid="pone.0032410-Mendelsohn1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Coetzee1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, and are warmer than in the Karoo, largely because of the buffering effects of the ocean. Namib average yearly temperatures are 17&#x02013;21&#x000b0;C. Namib rainfall is remarkably lower than in the Karoo, with average annual rainfall of about 15&#x02013;27 mm <xref rid="pone.0032410-Desmet1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. In contrast, the gravel plains where <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> occurs are &#x0201c;semi-desert&#x0201d; in both the Succulent Karoo and the western Nama Karoo biomes <xref rid="pone.0032410-Skinner1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. The average annual temperatures in the Karoo are about 15&#x02013;19&#x000b0;C. Snow can accumulate on the ground for a few days in some areas. The average annual rainfall is about 66&#x02013;200 mm. Another distinctive difference between the two distributions, which is related to the different climatic regimes, is the dominant vegetation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Surface vegetation in the Pro Namib and Namib Desert is very sparse, in some areas being dominated only by lichens that are supported by coastal fog, while in other areas sparse bunch grasses dominate in years with sufficient rainfall. Bushes of any size are highly dispersed, if present at all. In some Namib Desert habitats, where the gravel substrate is relatively coarse, <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> sometimes constructs and maintains distinctly straight paths between boulders <xref rid="pone.0032410-Sauer1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> or rocky areas <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, which are used for shelter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). In comparison, on gravel plains in the Karoo, bunch grasses and forbs can be seasonally common between scattered small (up to ca. 1 m high) bushes and bunch grasses. In addition, we found no evidence of distinctive sengi paths in <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> habitat during our 2007 fieldwork, and we are not aware that paths have been documented for this taxon elsewhere.</p><fig id="pone-0032410-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032410.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Typical <italic>Macroscelides</italic> gravel plain habitats in the central part of the range of each taxon.</title><p>A (top). Capture site of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032410-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) in the Namib Desert near Wlotzkasbaken, Namibia (10 m elevation). Note coastal fog in distance and virtual lack of significant vegetation, except for lichens. Sengi trail is visible through center of image to rocky area in distance (Photo by GBR, 25 May 2000). B (bottom). Capture site of <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> in the Nama Karoo 40 km east of Loxton, South Africa (elevation 1364 m). Note dominance of bushes compared to the Namib Desert habitat (Photo Chris and Mathilde Stuart, 27 December 2009).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0032410.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Taxonomy</title><p>Our data support the taxonomic distinction of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> and <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>. These two taxa form reciprocally monophyletic groups in phylogenetic analyses of mitochondrial loci. Many widely recognized full species do not achieve reciprocal monophyly <xref rid="pone.0032410-Kizirian1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, and so it may be a conservative criterion. Reciprocal monophyly may be misleading in small populations where gene sorting occurs rapidly despite little divergence, but this is certainly not the case for <italic>Macroscelides</italic>. There is significant haplotype diversity within each taxon, and the diversity is widespread.</p><p>Furthermore, mitochondrial haplotypes have diverged significantly between the two taxa with average total uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence of 13.3&#x00025; (Cyt <italic>b</italic> only: average&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;13.7&#x00025;, range 12.4&#x02013;14.9&#x00025;; CR only: average&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;12.4&#x00025;, range 11.5&#x02013;13.6&#x00025;). This suggests that they have been evolving independently for a long time. In comparison to other groups of mammals, most species have less than 8&#x00025; sequence divergence among Cyt <italic>b</italic> haplotypes <xref rid="pone.0032410-Baker1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Bradley1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref> and COI haplotypes <xref rid="pone.0032410-Borisenko1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Clare1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Bannikova1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, with the exception of taxa thought to contain cryptic species or having multiple distinct genetic lineages.</p><p>Despite the large genetic distances, mitochondrial reciprocal monophyly, and significant multivariate morphological differences, we found no single diagnostic morphological character to distinguish the taxa. This is not unusual for members of the subfamily Macroscelidinae, as demonstrated by cryptic species in the genus <italic>Elephantulus</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0032410-Smit5" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, and is further discussed by Rathbun <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Initially, we hypothesized that pelage color might be diagnostic because <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> is generally much lighter in color than <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic>. Although this is indeed the case over much of the distribution of the genus, after examining specimens at the National Museum in Windhoek, Namibia, we confirmed that there is variation in pelage darkness in both taxa, but that specimens from the Zwartmodder and Gorassis area do not show the dark/light distinction found in much of the main part of the distribution of the two taxa. Similarly, <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> generally weighs more than <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>, but there is variation resulting in overlapping weight ranges. Specimens from the Zwartmodder and Gorassis area largely conform to the general weight distinction, and <italic>M. p flavicaudatus</italic> is significantly smaller (24&#x02013;29.5 g) than <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> (34&#x02013;42 g) in this vicinity.</p><p>Our dataset offers no support for any of the other named <italic>Macroscelides</italic> taxa in the literature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0032410-t001">Table 1</xref>). Indeed, our data support the general conclusion of Corbet and Hanks <xref rid="pone.0032410-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, that there are only two valid <italic>Macroscelides</italic> taxa: <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> and <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic>. While their assessment was based on a very limited number of <italic>M. p. flavicaudatus</italic> specimens, our analyses include significant samples of both forms.</p><p>Although the mitochondria strongly support the two currently recognized taxa, the molecular data come entirely from a single linkage group (mitochondrial DNA), and thus should be corroborated by future studies using nuclear loci. In certain cases mitochondrial phylogenies may differ from overall species phylogenies <xref rid="pone.0032410-Edwards1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Ballard1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, so it will be important to examine nuclear gene phylogenies.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Elevation to full species</title><p>Biological species &#x0201c;are groups of actually (or potentially) interbreeding natural populations which are reproductively isolated from other such groups&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Mayr1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. We searched for direct evidence of genetic mixing (hybrid forms or genetic introgression) or the absence of it (sympatric occurrence of both taxa) in the two subspecies of <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> by collecting in the potential overlap region between Zwartmodder Farm and Gorassis Farm in Namibia. Despite our efforts, we were unable to find any populations of <italic>Macroscelides</italic> between these localities. Furthermore, we genetically sampled the Zwartmodder and Gorassis populations and found no evidence of genetic mixing. We believe that the available evidence is consistent with the biological species concept, as well as the phylogenetic species concept (&#x0201c;the smallest diagnosable cluster of individual organisms within which there is a parental pattern of ancestry and descent&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Cracraft1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>) and the genetic species concept (&#x0201c;a group of genetically compatible interbreeding natural populations that is genetically isolated from other such groups&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Baker1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032410-Bradley1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>). We therefore recommend elevating the two subspecies to full species status:</p><p>
<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus</italic> (Shaw 1800:536) with the type locality of &#x0201c;Cape of Good Hope&#x0201d; limited by Roberts (1951) to Roodeval, Oudtshoorn division, southwestern Cape Province.</p><p>
<italic>Macroscelides flavicaudatus</italic> (<italic>Macroscelides proboscideus flavicaudatus</italic>) Lundholm 1955:285, with the type locality of 6 miles (9.6 km) from the mouth of the Omaruru River, South West Africa (Namibia).</p><p>In the past, the generally accepted common name for <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> has been the &#x0201c;round-eared sengi&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0032410-Rathbun1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. We recommend the following common names for the new taxa. &#x0201c;Round-eared sengi&#x0201d; should now refer to the genus, which is no longer monospecific. The two new species names should include &#x0201c;round-eared&#x0201d;, so that they are clearly distinguished from sengis in other genera, plus the name of the region where each species occurs. Thus <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> is the &#x0201c;Karoo round-eared sengi&#x0201d; (or elephant-shrew) and <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> is the &#x0201c;Namib round-eared sengi&#x0201d; (or elephant-shrew).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Species Traits and Conclusions</title><p>The two <italic>Macroscelides</italic> species diverged in mitochondrial haplotypes by an average of 13.3&#x00025;, which is remarkable for two taxa that are morphologically so similar. Also, we found no evidence of <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> haplotypes in <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> populations, or visa versa. The two species appear to be allopatric, with about 50 km of separation in a very small area of their distribution, centered at latitude &#x02212;25.0735 and longitude 16.1137 in Namibia. However, if additional collecting is done around this area, we suspect that <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> range will extend tens of kilometers to the southwest into suitable habitat in the Namib Desert, and similarly <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> will extend to the northeast into the Pro-Namib and Nama-Karoo. Both species occupy gravel plains, but <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> habitat in the Namib Desert and Pro-Namib tends to be much less vegetated than the Pro-Namib and Nama-Karoo gravel plains further inland, where <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> occurs. Although we have found no single morphological character that clearly distinguishes the two species throughout their ranges, in most areas the dorsal pelage of <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> tends to be a light buff color, whereas that of <italic>M. proboscideus</italic> is darker, usually being various shades of brown-gray. The body mass of the two species is also distinctive in most parts of their distribution, with the two often being separated at about 30&#x02013;35 g. Interestingly, the largest <italic>M. flavicaudatus</italic> individuals were found far north of <italic>M. proboscideus</italic>, and where the two species are found nearby, they differ significantly in size. The result is that over most of the distribution of the genus, the two species are relatively easily distinguished by a combination of their location, pelage coloration, and weight.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032410.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>List of <italic>Macroscelides proboscideus flavicaudatus</italic> and <italic>M. p. proboscideus</italic> specimens used in molecular and morphological cranial analyses.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0032410.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Mike Griffin for guidance in focusing our efforts to appropriate localities in Namibia, and for initial specimen collection. John Irish was invaluable in assisting us in finding historical farm (known elsewhere as ranch) names, and providing centroid coordinates of farm properties. We greatly appreciate the hospitality and logistical support of Danica Shaw and staff of the NamibRand Nature Reserve. Similarly, we are indebted to Susan and Anton Horn of Zwartmodder Farm, and J. Albi Bruekner of Gorassis Farm, for their gracious hospitality. Paula Jenkins and Louise Tomsett provided GBR access to the collection of sengis at The Natural History Museum in London, as did Teresa Kearney at the Ditsong National Museum of Natural History in Pretoria. We appreciate Moe Flannery's help with import permits and cataloging specimens at CAS, and Tiffany Bozic for assistance with fieldwork. Assistance with laboratory work at CAS was provided by Monica McDonald, Amber Bifolk, Carmen DeLeon, and Zach Hanna. James Patton and Patricia Holroyd provided useful insights into cranial morphology. We thank the Namibia Ministry of Environment and Tourism for supporting our work with research and export permits.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>Funding was provided by the California Academy of Sciences in-house funds and Department of Ornithology and Mammalogy gift funds (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.calacademy.org/">http://www.calacademy.org/</ext-link>). Those who provided the funds to the academy or allocated the funds to the authors' department had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0032410-Corbet1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbet</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1968</year>
<article-title>A revision of the elephant-shrews, Family Macroscelididae.</article-title>
<source>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Zoology</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<lpage>111</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Rathbun1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Why is there discordant diversity in sengi (Mammalia: Afrotheria: Macroscelidea) taxonomy and ecology?</article-title>
<source>African Journal of Ecology</source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>13</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Patterson1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1965</year>
<article-title>The fossil elephant shrews (Family Macroscelididae).</article-title>
<source>Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University</source>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>
<lpage>336</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Seiffert1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seiffert</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A new estimate of afrotherian phylogeny based on simultaneous analysis of genomic, morphological, and fossil evidence.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evoultionary Biology</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>224</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Springer1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Molecules consolidate the placental mammal tree.</article-title>
<source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>430</fpage>
<lpage>438</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Hedges1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Afrotheria: Plate tectonics meets genomics.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>2</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smit1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen van Vuuren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A new species of elephant-shrew (Afrotheria: Macroscelidea: <italic>Elephantulus</italic>) from South Africa.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Mammalogy</source>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>1257</fpage>
<lpage>1269</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Rovero1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rovero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A potentially new giant sengi (elephant-shrew) from the Udzungwa Mountains, Tanzania.</article-title>
<source>Journal of East African Natural History</source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>111</fpage>
<lpage>115</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Rovero2"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rovero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A new species of giant sengi or elephant-shrew (genus <italic>Rhynchocyon</italic>) highlights the exceptional biodiversity of the Udzungwa Mountains of Tanzania.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Zoology, London</source>
<volume>274</volume>
<fpage>126</fpage>
<lpage>133</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Skinner1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chimimba</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<source>The Mammals of the Southern African Subregion, 3rd edition</source>
<publisher-loc>Cape Town, South Africa</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Kerley1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerley</surname><given-names>GIH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The round-eared elephant-shrew <italic>Macroscelides proboscideus</italic> (Macroscelidea) as an omnivore.</article-title>
<source>Mammal Review</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>
<lpage>44</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Sauer1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>EGF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>Zum sozialverhalten der kurzohrigen elefantenspitzmaus, <italic>Macrocelides proboscideus</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Zeitschrift fur Saugetierkunde</source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>97</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Schubert1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schradin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodel</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Male mate guarding in a socially monogamous mammal, the round-eared sengi: on costs and trade-offs.</article-title>
<source>Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology</source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>257</fpage>
<lpage>264</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Shaw1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1800</year>
<source>General zoology or systematic natural history. Vol. I. Part 2. Mammalia</source>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Printed for G. Kearsley</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smith1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1829</year>
<article-title>Contributions to the natural history of South Africa.</article-title>
<source>Zoological Journal of London</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>433</fpage>
<lpage>444</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smith2"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1838</year>
<source>Illustrations of the zoology of South Africa, consisting chiefly of figures and descriptions of the objects of natural history collected during an expedition into the interior of South Africa, in the years 1834, 1835, and 1836. Mammalia - Plate X</source>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Smith, Elder, and Company</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Lichtenstein1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1831</year>
<source>Darstellung neuer oder wenig bekannter Saugethiere</source>
<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Luderitz</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Ogilby1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogilby</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1838</year>
<article-title>A selection of the Mammalia procured by Captain Alexander during his recent journey into the country of the Damaras on the south west coast of Africa.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London</source>
<volume>1838</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Roberts1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1951</year>
<source>The mammals of South Africa</source>
<publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Central News Agency</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Lundholm1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lundholm</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>
<article-title>Descriptions of new mammals.</article-title>
<source>Annals of the Transvaal Museum</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>279</fpage>
<lpage>303</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Kingdon1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1974</year>
<source>East African Mammals; An Atlas of Evolution in Africa</source>
<publisher-loc>New York, New York</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Rathbun2"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Social structure of the bushveld sengi (<italic>Elephantulus intufi</italic>) in Namibia and the evolution of monogamy in the Macroscelidea.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Zoology, London</source>
<volume>269</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>
<lpage>399</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smit2"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen van Vuuren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Vicariance and the endemic Cape rock sengi (<italic>Elephantulus edwardii</italic>): are these two linked?</article-title>
<source>Afrotherian Conservation - Newsletter of the IUCN-SCC Afrotheria Specialist Group</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smit3"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Vuuren</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Coalescence methods reveal the impact of vicariance on the spatial genetic structure of <italic>Elephantulus edwardii</italic> (Afrotheria, Macroscelidea).</article-title>
<source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>2680</fpage>
<lpage>2692</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17594439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smit4"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Vuuren</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Relative importance of habitat connectivity in shaping the genetic profiles of two southern African elephant-shrews.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Biogeography</source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>857</fpage>
<lpage>864</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Gannon1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Guidelines of the American Society of Mammalogists for the use of wild mammals in research.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Mammalogy</source>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>809</fpage>
<lpage>823</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Amass1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amass</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaver</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennet</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>2000 Report of the AVMA panel on euthanasia.</article-title>
<source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<volume>218</volume>
<fpage>669</fpage>
<lpage>696</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11280396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Rathbun3"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ny&#x000e1;ri</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>
<italic>Macroscelides</italic> location data.</article-title>
<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/bmammals/eshrews/distribution.php">http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/bmammals/eshrews/distribution.php</ext-link>. Accessed 1 February 2010</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Getz1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortmann-Roe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>LoCoH: Nonparameteric kernel methods for constructing home ranges and utilization distributions.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>e207</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Getz2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmers</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A local nearest-neighbor convex-hull construction of home ranges and utilization distributions.</article-title>
<source>Ecography</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>489</fpage>
<lpage>505</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Hoesch1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>
<article-title>Das problem der Farbubereinstimmung von Korperfabre und Untergrund.</article-title>
<source>Bonner Zoologische Beitrage</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Hoesch2"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1959</year>
<article-title>Zur Jugendentwicklung der Macroscelididae.</article-title>
<source>Bonner Zoologische Beitraege</source>
<volume>3/4</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>
<lpage>265</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Hoesch3"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1959</year>
<article-title>Elefanten-Spitzmause in Freiheit und in Gefangenschaft.</article-title>
<source>Natur und Volk</source>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>53</fpage>
<lpage>59</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Hoesch4"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>von Lehmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>
<article-title>Zur Saugetier-Fauna Sudwestafrikas.</article-title>
<source>Bonner Zoologische Beitraege</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>8</fpage>
<lpage>57</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Anonymous1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anonymous</surname></name></person-group>
<year>1961</year>
<article-title>Walter Hoesch.</article-title>
<source>Journal Ornithology</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>490</fpage>
<lpage>495</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Wandeler1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wandeler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeck</surname><given-names>PEA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Back to the future: museum specimens in population genetics.</article-title>
<source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>634</fpage>
<lpage>642</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17988758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Dumbacher1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumbacher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic evidence for colour pattern convergence in toxic pitohuis: Mullerian mimicry in birds?</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London - Series B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>1971</fpage>
<lpage>1976</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11571042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Dumbacher2"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumbacher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Phylogeny of the owlet-nightjars (Aves: Aegothelidae) based on mitochondrial DNA sequence.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>540</fpage>
<lpage>549</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14615192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Sorenson1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorenson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Multiple independent transpositions of mitochondrial DNA control region sequences to the nucleus.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>15239</fpage>
<lpage>15243</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Swofford1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<source>Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (&#x0002a;and Other Methods). 4. ed</source>
<publisher-loc>Sunderland, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Guindon1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood.</article-title>
<source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>696</fpage>
<lpage>704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Posada1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>jModeltest: Phylogenetic model averaging.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1253</fpage>
<lpage>1256</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Huelsenbeck1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees.</article-title>
<source>BioInformatics</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>754</fpage>
<lpage>755</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-DeBlase1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeBlase</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<source>A Manual of Mammalogy with Keys to the Families of the World</source>
<publisher-loc>Dubuque, Iowa</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>William C. Brown Co. Publishers</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Murata1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Afrotherian phylogeny as inferred from complete mitochondrial genomes.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>253</fpage>
<lpage>260</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Mendelsohn1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendelsohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<source>Chapter 4: Plants and animals. Atlas of Namibia: A portrait of the Land and Its People</source>
<publisher-loc>Cape Town, South Africa</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Ministry of Environment and Tourism</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Coetzee1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1969</year>
<article-title>The distribution of mammals in the Namib Desert and adjoining inland escarpment.</article-title>
<source>Scientific Papers of the Namib Desert Research Station</source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>36</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Desmet1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desmet</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The climate of the Karoo &#x02013; a functional approach.</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>WRJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Milton</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>The Karoo &#x02013; Ecological Patterns and Processes</source>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Kizirian1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kizirian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The criterion of reciprocal monophyly and classification of nested diversity at the species level.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>1072</fpage>
<lpage>1076</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15288076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Baker1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Speciation in mammals and the genetic species concept.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Mammalogy</source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>643</fpage>
<lpage>662</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19890476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Bradley1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>A test of the genetic species concept: cytochrome-b sequences and mammals.</article-title>
<source>Journal of Mammalogy</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>960</fpage>
<lpage>973</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Borisenko1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borisenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanner</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>DNA barcoding in surveys of small mammal communities: a field study in Suriname.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>471</fpage>
<lpage>479</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21585824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Clare1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Eger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>DNA barcoding of Neotropical bats: species identification and discovery within Guyana.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>184</fpage>
<lpage>190</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Bannikova1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bannikova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Borisenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedev</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozhnov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Mitochondrial diversity of the white-toothed shrews (Mammalia, Eulipotyphla, Crocidura) in Vietnam.</article-title>
<source>Zootaxa</source>
<volume>2812</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>20</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Francis1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Borisenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Eger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The Role of DNA Barcodes in Understanding and Conservation of Mammal Diversity in Southeast Asia.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e12575</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20838635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Smit5"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<source>Phylogeography of three southern African endemic elephant-shrews and a supermatrix approach to the Macroscelidea [Ph.D.]</source>
<publisher-loc>Matieland, South Africa</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Stellenbosch University</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Edwards1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Calkins</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Speciation in birds: Genes, geography, and sexual selection.</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>6550</fpage>
<lpage>6557</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15851678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Ballard1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>JWO</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The incomplete natural history of mitochondria.</article-title>
<source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>729</fpage>
<lpage>744</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Mayr1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Linsley</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Usinger</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1953</year>
<source>Methods and Principles of Systematic Zoology</source>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Cracraft1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cracraft</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Species concepts and speciation analysis.</article-title>
<source>Current Ornithology</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>187</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0032410-Springer2"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrine</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Additional support for Afrotheria and Paenungulata, the performance of mitochondrial versus nuclear genes, and the impact of data partitions with heterogeneous base compounds.</article-title>
<source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12078646</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>