<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Evolutionary Studies</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Paleontology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Triassic pentadactyl tracks from the Los Menucos Group (R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Patagonia Argentina): possible constraints on the autopodial posture of Gondwanan trackmakers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Citton</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><email>pcitton@unrn.edu.ar</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>Ignacio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Valais</surname><given-names>Silvina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000f3;nsole-Gonella</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (CONICET)</institution>, <city>Buenos Aires</city>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Instituto de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Paleobiolog&#x000ed;a y Geolog&#x000ed;a (IIPG), Universidad Nacional de R&#x000ed;o Negro</institution>, <city> General Roca</city>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Instituto Superior de Correlaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica (INSUGEO), Universidad Nacional de Tucum&#x000e1;n</institution>, <city>Tucum&#x000e1;n</city>, <country> Argentina</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>De Baets</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2018-08-07"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e5358</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-19"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-07-11"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2018 Citton et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Citton et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/5358"/><abstract><p>The Los Menucos locality in Patagonia, Argentina, bears a well-known ichnofauna mostly documented by small therapsid footprints. Within this ichnofauna, large pentadactyl footprints are also represented but to date were relatively underinvestigated. These footprints are here analyzed and discussed based on palaeobiological indications (i.e., trackmaker identification). High resolution digital photogrammetry method was performed to achieve a more objective representation of footprint three-dimensional morphologies. The footprints under study are compared with <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> from the Upper Triassic lower Elliot Formation (Stormberg Group) of the Karoo Basin (Lesotho, southern Africa). Some track features suggest a therapsid-grade synapsid as the potential trackmaker, to be sought among anomodont dicynodonts (probably Kannemeyeriiformes). While the interpretation of limb posture in the producer of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks from the Los Menucos locality agrees with those described from the dicynodont body fossil record, the autopodial posture does not completely agree. The relative distance between the impression of the digital (ungual) bases and the distal edge of the pad trace characterizing the studied tracks likely indicates a subunguligrade foot posture (i.e., standing on the last and penultimate phalanges) in static stance, but plantiportal (i.e., the whole foot skeleton and related soft tissues are weight-bearing) during the dynamics of locomotion. The reconstructed posture might have implied an arched configuration of the articulated metapodials and at least of the proximal phalanges, as well as little movement capabilities of the metapodials. Usually, a subunguligrade-plantiportal autopod has been described for gigantic animals (over six hundreds kilograms of body weight) to obtain an efficient management of body weight. Nevertheless, this kind of autopod is described here for large but not gigantic animals, as the putative trackmakers of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> were. This attribution implies that such an autopodial structure was promoted independently from the body size in the putative trackmakers. From an evolutionary point of view, subunguligrade-plantiportal autopods not necessarily must be related with an increase in body size, but rather the increase in body size requires a subunguligrade or unguligrade, plantiportal foot. Chronostratigraphically, <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> was reported from Upper Triassic deposits of South Africa and United States, and from late Middle Triassic and Upper Triassic deposits of Argentina. Based on the stratigraphic distribution of the ichnogenus currently accepted, a Late Triassic age is here proposed for the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>-bearing levels of the Los Menucos Group.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd><italic>Pentasauropus</italic></kwd><kwd>Tracks</kwd><kwd>Therapsids</kwd><kwd>Dicynodonts</kwd><kwd>Triassic</kwd><kwd>Gondwana</kwd><kwd>Los Menucos</kwd><kwd>Patagonia</kwd><kwd>Trackmakers</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Paleontological Society International Research Program</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>CONICET to Silvina de Valais</funding-source><award-id>PIP 2015-2017 576</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was made possible by financial support from the Paleontological Society International Research Program, Sepkoski Grants &#x02013;2017 to Paolo Citton and PIP 2015-2017 576 from CONICET to Silvina de Valais. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Tetrapod tracks are valuable fossils which inform us about the anatomy (e.g.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Carpenter, 1992</xref>), functional adaptations (e.g.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Baird, 1980</xref>), motion (e.g.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Avanzini, Pi&#x000f1;uela &#x00026; Garc&#x000ed;a-Ramos, 2011</xref>) and ethology (e.g.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">Lockley et al., 2016</xref>) of extinct animals, greatly expanding the potential of information that is often precluded from the body-fossil record. The detailed analysis of tetrapod footprints is therefore significant for integrating and revising data derived from the tetrapod body-fossil record.</p><p>The scientific study of tetrapod footprints in Argentina is relatively recent compared to that of Europe (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Duncan, 1831</xref>; <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Kaup, 1835a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Kaup, 1835b</xref>) and North America (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Hitchcock, 1836</xref>), dating back to the first half of the twentieth century (<xref rid="ref-124" ref-type="bibr">Von Huene, 1931</xref>). One of the most important contribution to tetrapod ichnology in Argentina is that of <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela (1964)</xref>, who devoted himself to the study of Triassic and Jurassic tetrapod tracks from Patagonia. Later, other contributions focused on important Triassic ichnofaunas from other regions of Argentina have been published (e.g.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-113" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1966</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Bonaparte, 1966</xref>; <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Leonardi, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais, 2006</xref>). Among the Triassic vertebrate ichnological record, the Los Menucos ichnofauna, which is dominated by small therapsid footprints, was repeatedly studied (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela, 1964</xref>; <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela, 1975</xref>; <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="ref-83" ref-type="bibr">Leonardi &#x00026; De Oliveira, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Leonardi, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich &#x00026; Marsicano, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">de Valais, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez &#x00026; de Valais, 2014</xref>). The bulk of this ichnofauna was originally attributed to different ichnotaxa by <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela (1964)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Casamiquela (1975)</xref>, but after the revision made by <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais (2006)</xref>, most of the ichnogenera erected by Casamiquela are considered synonymous with <italic>Dicynodontipus</italic>. Moreover, an indetermined chirotheroid track (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">de Valais, 2008</xref>), a single track referred to as <italic>Rhynchosauroides</italic>, and large pentadactyl footprints mentioned as <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> sp. (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al., 2008</xref>) have also been reported from the Los Menucos area. From the same locality, several slabs with pentadactyl tracks comparable to those described by <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al. (2008)</xref> were collected many years ago but remained unpublished until now.</p><p>An ichnological analysis based on this material is here proposed and discussed in terms of the palaeobiology, identity and autopodial anatomy of the trackmaker. Besides, a brief discussion of the chronostratigraphy of this record is provided.</p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><p>The present study is based on the direct examination of track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-1 with three pes-manus couples, two of which incomplete (concave epireliefs, i.e.,&#x000a0;negative relief), MPCA 27029-2 with a single left pes-manus couple (convex hyporeliefs, i.e.,&#x000a0;positive relief), MPCA 27029-3 with two pes-manus couples and an incomplete pes (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-4 with a single pes-manus couple (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-5 with a single track (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-9 with five pes-manus couples, three of which incomplete (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-16 with three pes-manus couples, one of which incomplete, and five incomplete tracks (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-21 with two pes-manus couples and four tracks (convex hyporeliefs), MPCA 27029-33 with two pes-manus couples (convex hyporeliefs), MMLM 1 with two pes-manus couples (convex hyporeliefs), MMLM 2 with two incomplete pes-manus couples (convex hyporeliefs), and MMLM 075-1 (ex MRPV 1987P.V.06 <italic>in</italic>
<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al., 2008</xref>, hereafter MMLM 075-1) with two incomplete pes-manus couples (concave epireliefs). Except for the specimen MMLM 075-1, the material under study was to date unpublished. A few other slabs, both with and without label, are stored at the MPCA but were not considered in this study due to poor preservation of the tracks. In total, about 60 footprints were analyzed. For each slab, tracks were numbered using Arabic numerals and, when referring to single tracks in the text, they are indicated as /number following the slab label (e.g.,&#x000a0;MPCA 27029-1/4 where MPCA 27029-1 and number 4 indicate slab and single track, respectively). The studied material mainly consists of isolated sets or incomplete trackways.</p><p>The provenance of the track-bearing slabs can be traced back to the Felipe Curuil ex quarry, Yancaqueo farm, east of the town of Los Menucos (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al., 2008</xref>), but the exact stratigraphic repositioning of the material is currently prevented and inherent data are lacking in the literature.</p><sec><title>Microfacies characterization</title><p>Two thin sections were obtained from the slab MPCA 27029-19 (its footprints are poorly preserved and not included in this study), both parallel and perpendicular to the trampled surface. For the description of the thin sections, <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie, Donaldson &#x00026; Guilford (1982)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref-115" ref-type="bibr">Scasso &#x00026; Limarino (1997)</xref> were taken as a reference. Thin sections are presently stored at the MPCA and labelled as MPCA 27029/19.1 (parallel to the trampled surface) and MPCA 27029/19.2 (perpendicular to the trampled surface).</p></sec><sec><title>Measurements</title><p>Measurements related to trackmaker body dimension were obtained from slabs MPCA 27029-1, MPCA 27029-9, MPCA 27029-16 and MPCA 27029-21. From single tracks, which are mainly represented by digit traces, measurements of footprint width were taken. Also, track features and differential depth of impressions in some cases allowed to recognize the footprint identity, the side of the trackway when incompletely preserved, or tracks belonging to different trackways (e.g.,&#x000a0;MMLM 075-1), and element orientations. Track measurements were performed according to guidelines introduced by <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">Leonardi (1987)</xref>. Track outlines were represented through interpretive drawings.</p></sec><sec><title>Digital models</title><p>High-resolution digital photogrammetry was undertaken to achieve a more objective representation of track three-dimensional morphology, according to a recently described standard protocol for ichnological studies (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Falkingham et al., 2018</xref>). To model the studied specimens, the software package Agisoft PhotoScan Pro (Educational License), which enables creating 3D textured meshes by means of semi-automatic processing of images (<xref rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr">Mallison &#x00026; Wings, 2014</xref>), was used.</p><p>The images selected for the photogrammetric process were acquired using a Nikon Coolpix P520 camera with 4.3&#x02013;7.6 focal length, resolution 4,896 &#x000d7;&#x000a0;3,672 and pixel size ranging from 1.25 &#x000d7;&#x000a0;1.25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m and 1.27 &#x000d7;&#x000a0;1.27&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Main processing parameters are reported in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In order to correctly scale the calculated model, a metric reference marker was applied on the surface. Three-dimensional models were converted to colour topographic profiles using the software Paraview (version 5.4.1).</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Photogrammetric report.</title><p>Main processing parameters of the photogrammetric models (from Agisoft Photoscan Professional reports).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g013"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3D model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of images</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camera altitude (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground resolution (mm/pix)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMS reprojection error</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean key point size (pix)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scale bars total error (m)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145637 (0.595447 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99373</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000211567</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211741 (0.749639 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000120665</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221627 (0.663238 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1918</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000101555</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0753</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225287 (0.695116 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000145928</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186287 (0.548475 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41294</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000125956</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206052 (0.638116 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27202</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000154204</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254353 (0.874324 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000179922</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273984 (0.529254 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28824</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000184177</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25616 (0.993387 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90857</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000121254</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 075-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196238 (0.739726 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000118491</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222075 (0.673395 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00332392</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0949</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.234591 (0.852769 pix)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99994e&#x02013;05</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Geological Setting</title><p>Continental deposits of Triassic age in Argentina were accumulated in different basins in western and northwestern regions (Mendoza, San Juan, San Luis and La Rioja provinces) as well as in Patagonia (northern sector of the Santa Cruz province and R&#x000ed;o Negro provinces). These elongated, narrow rift basins with prevalent NW-SE and NNW-SSE trends were developed during Permian and Triassic periods and are related with the breakup of the western margin of south-west Gondwana (<xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr">Kokogian et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Franzese &#x00026; Spalletti, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Barredo et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>The Triassic tetrapod track record of southern South America is exclusive to three basins, namely the Ischigualasto-Villa Uni&#x000f3;n Basin (San Juan and La Rioja provinces), the Cuyo Basin (Mendoza and San Juan provinces) and the Los Menucos basin (R&#x000ed;o Negro province) (e.g., <xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">Melchor, Genise &#x00026; Poir&#x000e9;, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">de Valais, 2008</xref> and references therein). According to <xref rid="ref-118" ref-type="bibr">Spalletti (1999)</xref>, in the northern basins (i.e., Ischigualasto-Villa Uni&#x000f3;n and Cuyo) the sedimentation encompasses the Lower to Upper Triassic, while in the Los Menucos Basin the sedimentation took place in the Late Triassic, based on the age of volcanic activity in north-central Patagonia.</p><p>After the works of <xref rid="ref-119" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic (1967)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-122" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic et al. (1968)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-120" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic &#x00026; Methol (1972)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-121" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic &#x00026; Methol (1980)</xref>, the Los Menucos Group (also as &#x02018;Complejo Los Menucos&#x02019;&#x02014;Los Menucos Complex <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Cucchi, Busteros &#x00026; Lema, 2001</xref>) was established by <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg (2001)</xref> to indicate dacitic to rhyolitic ignimbrites, mesosilicic lavas and subordinate Triassic sedimentary rocks exposed around Los Menucos town, in the north-western sector of the North Patagonian Massif (R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig.&#x000a0;1A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The Los Menucos area.</title><p>(A) Location map and geological sketch of Los Menucos area (from <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg (2005)</xref>, redrawn and slightly modified). White star indicates Estancia Yancaqueo, from which the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> footprints come. (B) Simplified stratigraphic section of the Los Menucos Group (from <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg (2005)</xref>, redrawn and slightly modified). Dashed lines with quotation marks indicate the possible position of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>-bearing strata.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g001"/></fig><p>Within the Los Menucos Group, two lithostratigraphic units were defined, namely the Vera Formation at the base and the Sierra Colorada Formation on top (<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>, and references therein; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The Vera Formation, from which tetrapod tracks are historically reported, is mainly composed of volcanic and continental deposits laid down inside small basins bordered by regional and local faults with strike NE-SW, E-W and NW-SE (<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>). The Vera Formation is mainly represented by brownish to yellowish conglomerates, white to greenish sandstones and reddish brown to red pelites, with which volcanic ashes, tuffs and tuffites, dacitic pyroclastic flow products and volcanic breccias are intercalated (<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>). Sedimentation took place mainly in alluvial plain, floodplain, ephemeral river and small lacustrine palaeoenvironments (<xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>), under seasonal climate condition with alternating periods of dry and wet conditions (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Gallego, 2010</xref>). Sedimentary and volcaniclastic levels within the Vera Formation are characterized by a very rich palaeoflora, the so-called &#x0201c;<italic>Dicroidium -</italic> type flora&#x0201d; (<xref rid="ref-119" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic, 1967</xref>; <xref rid="ref-120" ref-type="bibr">Stipanicic &#x00026; Methol, 1972</xref>; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Artabe, 1985a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Artabe, 1985b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>) and by an abundant tetrapod ichnofauna, preserved on sandstones with poorly sorted grains and with a variable content of tuffaceous breccias (<xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais, 2006</xref>). Finds of skeletal fauna are scarce and are so only represented by remains of an amiiform fish (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Bogan, Taverne &#x00026; Agnolin, 2013</xref>).</p><p>The Sierra Colorada Formation is essentially made of ignimbritic volcanic rocks (<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg, 2005</xref>), dated at 222&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2 Ma with the Rb/Sr isochron method (Norian, Late Triassic; <xref rid="ref-107" ref-type="bibr">Rapela et al., 1996</xref>) and at 206.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2 Ma with the Ar/Ar method (Rhaetian, Late Triassic; <xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">Lema et al., 2008</xref>). These datations do not radiometrically constrain the base of the Vera Formation, for which a Late Triassic age was historically proposed on the basis of the &#x0201c;<italic>Dicroidium</italic>-type flora&#x0201d; and the tetrapod ichnofauna.</p><p>More recent results indicated an age of 257 &#x000b1; 2 Ma (Wuchiapingian, Late Permian) for a rhyolitic ignimbrite, 252 &#x000b1; 2 Ma (Changhsingian, Late Permian) for an andesite, and 248 &#x000b1; 2 Ma (Olenekian, Early Triassic) for a dacitic ignimbrite (<xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Luppo et al., 2017</xref>) of the Los Menucos Group. These new data predate the main volcanic activity to an about a 10 Ma period between the Late Permian and the Early Triassic, making the lower part of the Los Menucos Group coeval with the La Esperanza Plutono-Volcanic Complex (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Gonz&#x000e1;lez et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Luppo et al., 2017</xref>).</p><sec><title>Sedimentological observations</title><p>Track-bearing slabs consist of yellowish to greenish, medium to mainly coarse grained and poorly sorted volcaniclastic sandstone lacking of sedimentary structures in hand samples, neither on the surface or cross-section.</p><p>The observed texture ranges from inequigranular/equigranular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2B</xref>) to predominantly equigranular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Phenocrysts, mainly subhedral and anhedral, range in dimension from 0.5 mm to 1.5 mm and show in one case incipient orientation. Phenocrysts are represented mainly by plagioclase, quartz, alkaline feldspar, biotite, amphibole (hornblende), orthopyroxene (enstatite) and calcite floating in a mafic, glassy&#x000a0;matrix.</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Thin sections (MPCA 27029/19.1 and MPCA 27029/19.2) of track-bearing slab MPCA 27029-19.</title><p>Inequigranular, epiclastic texture with anhedral and subhedral phenocrysts at the base (A) and middle portion (B) of the track-bearing slab MPCA 27029-19. (C, D) Equigranular less epiclastic texture indicating a minor sedimentary reworking of the trampled surface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g002"/></fig><p>The dominant epiclastic texture observed at the base of the trampled surface (thin section MPCA 27029/19.2), mainly represented by fragments of quartz and some lithics displaying attrition and rounded to sub-angular shape, suggesting sedimentary reworking of an original tuff of probable dacitic composition. The texture observed in the thin section MPCA 27029/19.1 instead indicates a limited sedimentary reworking (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2D</xref>). In section, a faint normal gradation can be observed most likely indicating short sedimentation events; on the whole, the track-bearing slabs can be related to a proximal fluvial environment.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Track Record</title><sec><title>Track preservation</title><p>Specimen MMLM 075-1 is composed of four slabs, two as negative (concave) relief, labeled as MMLM 075-1/1a, /2 and /3a, and two as their positive (convex) filling, labeled as MMLM 075-1/1b and 3/b. There are no evidences of any layer between the concave and the convex reliefs and the shape of both concave epireliefs and convex hyporeliefs are exactly complementary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). Therefore, and taking into account that the tracks preserved similarly (i.e., sub-circular/sub-ovoidal to pointed digit impressions; roughly sub-circular to elliptical pad tracks; very thin displacement rims in the pad and well-marked in the digit impressions; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9</xref>), in our opinion the concave epireliefs are true tracks (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Marty, Falkingham &#x00026; Richter, 2016</xref>) and the convex hyporeliefs are their natural casts (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Marty, Falkingham &#x00026; Richter, 2016</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Tracks mode of preservation.</title><p>Convex hyporeliefs (A, C) fitting with concave epireliefs (B, D) preserved on slab MMLM 075-1 (true tracks and natural casts, respectively).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g003"/></fig><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-1; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-2; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E). In (A)&#x02013;(D), footprint 2 and 5, note the non-impressed area between the sole pad trace and the base of digit traces. In (E)&#x02013;(H) note the displacement areas behind digit traces, interpreted as the result of the thrust of digit pushing the sediment backwardly.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g004"/></fig><p>In general, the tracks studied here are moderately well preserved (grade 1 <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Belvedere &#x00026; Farlow, 2016</xref>), and the true tracks are not elite tracks (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr">Lockley, 1991</xref>). In addition, they are not modified true tracks (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Marty, Falkingham &#x00026; Richter, 2016</xref>) because they lack evidence of physiochemical (e.g., weathering) and/or biological influences after they were made. Thereby, the shape of these tracks is mainly conditioned by the substrate consistency (grain size and water content). Recently, <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Falk et al. (2017)</xref> performed neoichnological experiments that compared the shape of tracks impressed in three different sediments (fine, medium and coarse sand) with different moisture contents (wet, moist and dry). They concluded that wet and dry coarse sediments preserve tracks without fine details, but moisture coarse sediment might preserve the overall track shape and details as claw impessions. As has been previously commented, the tracking surface is a medium to coarse sandstone, and tracks have depth digit impressions with extruded rims.</p><p>Therefore, and according to the <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Falk et al. (2017)</xref>&#x02019;s experiments, the trackmakers most likely walked on humid, not waterlogged nor dry, coarse sediments with a moderately plastic behaviour, able to record the main anatomical features of the autopods.</p></sec><sec><title>Track description</title><p>The material are manus and pes tracks with very low dimensional heteropody (i.e., condition in which the autopods are dimensionally and morphologically different), mainly preserved as tetradactyl impressions, although pentadactyl tracks are also present (MPCA 27029-1/4/6, MPCA 27029-2/2, MPCA 27029-4/2, MPCA 27029-16/10, MPCA 27029-33/2, MMLM 075-1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8</xref>), as well as tridactyl ones displaying only the central digits (MPCA 27029-9/2, MPCA 27029-16/8, MPCA 27029-21/3, MMLM 1/1, MMLM 2/3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6G</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9</xref>). Morphologically, manus and pes tracks are strongly symmetrical. Digit traces are commonly arranged to shape an arcuate pattern that is convex anteriorly, according to which the digit III trace (the central one) or digit III and IV traces are the most projecting. Variability affecting the number of digits can occur on the same slab (e.g., MPCA 27029-21, MMLM 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Figs. 7E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9H</xref> ). In the material under study the degree of curvature of the arcuate pattern is variable and appears more pronounced in some smaller tracks (e.g., MPCA 27029-16/7/9/10; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Figs. 7A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7D</xref>) than in larger ones (e.g., MPCA 27029-1/4, MMLM 075-1, MMLM 2/2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9H</xref>). In the smaller tracks (e.g., MPCA27029-16, interpreted as left by a juvenile individual), the morphology of digit traces, their relative spacing and orientation, as well as the position of pes and manus impression is comparable with that of the larger tracks. When present, also the sole pad trace resembles that observed in the footprints of larger dimension. Thus, apart from the degree of curvature, the general morphology remains consistent despite dimensional differences (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7D</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-3; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-4; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E). Note the digit trailing marks slightly affecting the digit traces of footprint 2 in (A)&#x02013;(D), which are absent in footprints showed in (E)&#x02013;(H) where digit traces are roughly sub-circular in morphology.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g005"/></fig><fig id="fig-6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-6</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-5; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-9; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g006"/></fig><fig id="fig-7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-7</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-16 produced by a juvenile trackmaker; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-21; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E). The general morphology and structure of footprints 6&#x02013;10 in (A)&#x02013;(D), left by a juvenile trackmaker, is identical to that characterizing larger footprints even when preserved only as digit traces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g007"/></fig><fig id="fig-8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-8</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MPCA 27029-33; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MMLM 075-1; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E). In (E)&#x02013;(H) note the long and sharp digit trailing marks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g008"/></fig><fig id="fig-9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-9</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Photos, three-dimensional models and interpretative drawings of the studied material.</title><p>(A) Track-bearing slabs MMLM 1; (B) solid three-dimensional model of (A); (C) colour topographic profile and (D) interpretative drawing of (A). (E) Track-bearing slabs MMLM 2; (F) solid three-dimensional model of (E); (G) colour topographic profile and (H) interpretative drawing of (E). In (A)&#x02013;(D) note the long and sharp digit trailing marks affecting footprints 2 and 4, resembling those of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">Figs. 8E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8H</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g009"/></fig><p>Digit traces can be characterized by a sub-circular/sub-ovoidal morphology (e.g., MPCA 27029-9, MPCA 27029-16, MPCA 27029-21; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7</xref>), while in other cases they are markedly pointed (e.g., MPCA 27029-2, MPCA 27029-4, MPCA 27029-5, MPCA 27029-33; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8D</xref>). These two morphologies can co-exist on the same slab and within the same set or trackway, thus pertaining to the spectrum of internal variability of the material under study. When pointed, the most medial digit traces (i.e., digit I or II imprints and, to a lesser extent, digit III and IV imprints), both of manus and pes tracks, can be affected by drag marks. These extramorphological features (see <xref rid="ref-105" ref-type="bibr">Peabody, 1948</xref>) qualitatively range from weakly hinted and short (e.g., MPCA 27029-1/6, MPCA 27029-2/1, MPCA 27029-3/1/2, MPCA 27029-4/2, MPCA 27029-5, MPCA 27029-9/4/6; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6</xref>) to highly sharp and long (e.g., MMLM 075-1, MMLM 1 and MMLM 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">Figs.&#x000a0;8E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9D</xref>).</p><p>Central digits are commonly the most deeply and uniformly impressed, both in manus and pes tracks (e.g., MPCA 27029-4, MPCA 27029-5, MMLM 1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Figs. 5F</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9C</xref>). When a certain degree of variability is observed, digit III and IV imprints are the most deeply imprinted (e.g., MPCA 27029-1, MPCA 27029-3, MPCA 27029-16; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs.&#x000a0;4B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7C</xref>), followed by digit II and I imprints. The digit V trace, when preserved, is shorter and closer to the pad trace than the other digit traces and is only faintly imprinted (e.g., MMLM 075-1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">Figs. 8E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8H</xref>; but see MPCA 27029&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;16&#x02215;9&#x02215;10 for a different configuration of the digit depth of impression, most likely due to the reaction of the substrate and water content of the sediments at the time of impression, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Figs. 7B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7C</xref>).</p><p>Behind the digit traces, a roughly sub-circular to elliptical sole pad trace can be preserved (e.g., MPCA 27029-1/2/4/5/6, MPCA 27029-5, MPCA 27029-16/10, MMLM 075-1, MMLM 1/2/4, MMLM 2/1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9</xref>). The sole pad trace lies at a short distance from the base of the central digit traces and commonly approximates the most medial and lateral digit imprints (e.g., MPCA 27029-1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4D</xref>). Commonly, the sole pad trace is separated from central digit traces ahead by a non-impressed area, which appears as a groove or as a ridge depending on the mode of preservation, tapering towards the most medial and lateral digit imprints. This should not be confused with displacement areas of similar morphology, which are instead related to digit traces (i.e., thrust of digit pushing the sediment backwardly; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-10">Fig. 10</xref>), where this area is not impressed (e.g., MPCA 27029-2, MPCA 27029-3/1/4, MPCA 27029-4, MPCA 27029-9/3/5, MPCA 27029-21/4, MPCA 27029-33/1/2/3, MMLM 2/3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9H</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-10</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Morphological and extramorphological features identified on the studied material.</title><p>(A) Manus track MPCA 27029/2 and (B) interpretative drawing. (C) Pes track MPCA 27029-1/5 and (D) interpretative drawing. Extramorphological features are in blue and grey; morphological features are in black.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g010"/></fig><p>The sole pad trace is more deeply impressed in its central portion; depth of impression slightly decreases toward the lateral and distal portion (i.e., close to the non-impressed area behind digit traces, MPCA 27029-1, MMLM 075-1, MMLM 1; &#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8F</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9B</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-9">9C</xref>).</p><p>When possible, we tried to define the orientation of the footprint axis with respect to the trackway midline. The axis of pes tracks is in some cases rotated inwardly with respect to the trackway midline but it can also be parallel to the trackway midline (e.g., MPCA 27029-9, 27029-16), while manus tracks show a wider range of variability, being both inwardly and outwardly rotated with respect to the hypothetical trackway midline (e.g., MPCA 27029-1 and MMLM2, respectively). When possible, measurements and ratios were taken; measurements were performed taking into account digit III as the homologous point, both for manus and pes tracks. Results are reported in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. In general, footprints are wider than long with oblique pace length ranging between 60% and 80% of the stride length. Pace angulation ranges from 70&#x000b0; to 101&#x000b0;. Gleno acetabular distances, measured considering an amble gait (other gaits are reported in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>), indicate trackmakers with trunk length approximately of 37.4 cm (MPCA 27029-16), 63.1 cm (MPCA 27029-9) and 91.6 cm (MPCA 27029-1). The proximal margin of the digit traces lies at less than 3 cm from the distal margin of the sole trace (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Mean measurements (in cm) of track and trackway parameters.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g014"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fw</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mpl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ppl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mpa</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ppa</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Msl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETW/SL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psl/GAD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6<break/>12.8<break/>8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3<break/>12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2<break/>33.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7<break/>40.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101&#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99&#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2 (a)<break/>47.8 (b)<break/>91.6 (c)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7<break/>13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7<break/>14.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6<break/>13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4<break/>10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0<break/>32.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0 (a)<break/>46.9 (b)<break/>63.1 (c)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1<break/>7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0<break/>15.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0 (a)<break/>33.1 (b)<break/>37.4 (c)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0<break/>34.0<break/>34.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#x000b0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5<break/>41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCA 27029-33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4<break/>12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 075-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2<break/>11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6<break/>9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2<break/>10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5<break/>14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMLM 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2<break/>11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> ETW</term><def><p>external trackway width</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Fl</term><def><p>footprint length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Fw</term><def><p>footprint width</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GAD</term><def><p>gleno-acetabular distance: (a), &#x02018;primitive&#x02019; alternate pace (the trunk length of the producer is underestimated); (b) alternate pace; (c) amble (a, b, c, considering primary overlap <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">Leonardi, 1987</xref>)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ITW</term><def><p>internal trackway width</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Mpa</term><def><p>manus pace angulation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Mpl</term><def><p>manus pace length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Msl</term><def><p>manus stride length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Ppa</term><def><p>pes pace angulation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Ppl</term><def><p>pes pace length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Psl</term><def><p>pes stride length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Psl/GAD</term><def><p>pes stride length/gleno-acetabular distance ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ETW/SL</term><def><p>external trackway width/stride length ratio</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Sole pad-ungual trace distance.</title><p>Distance (in cm) between the distal margin of the sole pad trace and the proximal margin of the digit traces in complete <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> footprints. The measurements most likely indicate a raised and inclined position of the metapodial elements of fore and hind foot in the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g015"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit I</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit II</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit III</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit IV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit V</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MPCA 27029-1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MPCA 27029-5</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MPCA 27029-16</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MMLM 075-1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MMLM 1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MMLM 2</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><sec><title>Remarks</title><p>The footprints from the Los Menucos ichnosite are characterized by having the following features: homopodic manus and pes tracks with low dimensional heteropody, up to five digit imprints aligned, forming an anteriorly convex arch, a sole pad trace more impressed centrally or centro-laterally. On the basis of these general features, the specimens from Los Menucos are tentatively referred to as <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>.</p><p>The ichnogenus <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1970</xref>) was established on the basis of material collected and described years before (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1955</xref>) from the Upper Triassic lower Elliot Formation (Stormberg Group) of the Karoo Basin of Lesotho (Southern Africa). Five ichnospecies were originally included in the ichnogenus, namely <italic>Pentasauropus erectus</italic>, <italic>Pentasauropus incredibilis</italic>, <italic>Pentasauropus maphutsengi</italic>, <italic>Pentasauropus morobongensis</italic> and <italic>Pentasauropus motlejoi</italic>, which remained unchanged in the subsequent formal listing (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1970</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1972</xref>). Material from the Ellenberger collection referred to this ichnogenus is housed at the University of Montpellier (France) and represented by six casts originally mentioned as <italic>Pentasauropus incredibilis</italic> (LES 054 1-3, LES 054 4), <italic>Pentasauropus morobongensis</italic> (LES 005) <italic>Tetrasauropus gigas</italic> (LES 038), plus some missing specimens (see <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia, 2007</xref>, and reference therein for a complete assessment of inventory numbers).</p><p>After the original and subsequent publications of <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger (1955)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger (1970)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger (1972)</xref>, the ichnogenus was considered as valid by <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">Olsen &#x00026; Galton (1984)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">Lockley &#x00026; Meyer (2000)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Bordy, Abrahams &#x00026; Sciscio (2017)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Hunt, Lucas &#x00026; Klein (2018)</xref>. <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</xref> emended the diagnosis of the ichnogenus to appoint the type ichnospecies and considered the five ichnospecies as synonyms of <italic>Pentasauropus incredibilis</italic>. Differences in track pattern were considered as originated by dimensional constraints and/or behavioural factors, and the main footprint characteristics (e.g., number and arrangement of digits, heteropody) do not justify an ichnospecies separation (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia, 2007</xref>). Moreover, agreeing with <xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">Lockley &#x00026; Meyer (2000)</xref>, the same authors assigned tracks originally referred to as <italic>Tetrasauropus gigas</italic> to <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>.</p><p>In agreement with the emended ichnogeneric diagnosis by <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</xref>, the arcuate pattern of manus and pes tracks derived from the five equally spaced claw or ungual traces (those of imprints of digit II, III and IV are the largest). In other cases a roughly rounded sole pad is observed behind claw or ungual traces (LES 053 A, B, C in <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1972</xref>, pl. IV and V, and LES 038). According to <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</xref>, the axis of the pes impressions is always inwardly rotated, while that of the manus impression can range from slightly inwardly rotated (LES 052 B and LES 053 A) to slightly outwardly rotated (LES 038 and LES 052 A). Although long and complete trackways are not represented, this feature seems to characterize also the studied material based on the reconstruction of an hypothetical midline (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs. 4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4D</xref>, footprints 4 and 6; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Figs. 5A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5D</xref>, footprint 2). In some cases (e.g., MPCA 27029-9 and MPCA 27029-21, <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) short stride length in relation to overall footprint dimension could indicate a primary overstepping. However, in our opinion this trackway characteristic cannot be ensured on the basis of the material under study and most probably, taking into account the complexity of the dynamic of locomotion, cannot be inferred only from the stride lengths and footprint dimensions. Thus, for the time being, we prefer not to stress the interpretation about the overstepping. Additionally, overprinting in the studied material is absent; in some cases (e.g., MPCA 27029-3 and MPCA 27029-33, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Figs. 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-8">8B</xref>) interferences indicate that the hind print in the set was left after the fore print. For these cases, overstepping is not sustainable.</p><p>Outside of the Southern Africa, tracks tentatively referred to the ichnogenus were reported from Upper Triassic Chinle Group of Utah (<xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">Lockley &#x00026; Hunt, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Hunt-Foster et al., 2016</xref>) and Colorado (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Gaston et al., 2003</xref>, Fig. 12B), both USA. Moreover, tracks possibly referable to <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> were found in the Gettysburg Shale of the Gettysburg Basin of the Newark Supergroup (Baird pers. comm in <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">Olsen &#x00026; Galton, 1984</xref>). In Argentina, apart from the report from the Triassic Vera Formation (R&#x000ed;o Negro province, <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich et al., 2008</xref>), tracks referred to as <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> were described from the Carnian Portezuelo Formation (&#x02018;Type Q2&#x02019; <italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr">Marsicano &#x00026; Barredo, 2004</xref>). In addition, tracks with similar morphology to <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> were also reported from the Middle Triassic Cerro de Las Cabras Formation (Mendoza province, as cf. <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> in <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">de Valais, Melchor &#x00026; Bellosi, 2006</xref>) and from the Portezuelo Formation (San Juan province) as &#x02018;huellas cuadr&#x000fa;pedas tipo C&#x02019; (i.e., quadrupedal tracks type C; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">de Valais, 2008</xref>) but, for the time being, this material remains in open nomenclature.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Zoological attribution</title><p>Several attempts to identify the trackmaker of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> have been made. The ichnogenus was originally attributed to amphibians, basal melanorosaurid, ornithischian, anapsid and basal sauropod (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger &#x00026; Ellenberger, 1958</xref>: p. 67; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1970</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1972</xref>). Moreover, <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Haubold (1974)</xref>; <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Haubold (1984)</xref> referred <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> to a sauropod or therapsid trackmaker. A dicynodont was also proposed as producer by <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">Olsen &#x00026; Galton (1984)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, Anderson &#x00026; Cruickshank (1998)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">Lockley &#x00026; Meyer (2000)</xref>. <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Galton &#x00026; Heerden Van (1998)</xref> attributed <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> to large anomodont dicynodonts. <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Orazi Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</xref> accepted the attribution to a dicynodont, observing a good match between the skeletal autopodia of Triassic dicynodonts and the structure of digital impressions of the manus and pes, apart from the strong homopody and the limb posture (see also <xref rid="ref-125" ref-type="bibr">Walter, 1986</xref>). Recently, the kannemeyeriiform dicynodont <italic>Pentasaurus goggai</italic> from the lower Elliot Formation of South Africa has been referred as probable trackmaker of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks from the same lithostratigraphic unit (<xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Kammerer, 2018</xref>).</p><p>The studied material from the Los Menucos locality presents some features that allow corroboration of the therapsid interpretations about trackmaker identity. At the same time, constraining the identity of the putative trackmaker opens the way for new inferences about the posture of the autopodia.</p><p>Limb posture kept by <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmakers during the step cycle can be tentatively inferred from the trackway pattern (<xref rid="ref-105" ref-type="bibr">Peabody, 1948</xref>; <xref rid="ref-106" ref-type="bibr">Peabody, 1959</xref>; <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">Kubo &#x00026; Benton, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Kubo &#x00026; Ozaki, 2009</xref>), even if this interpretation is often far from being simple and linear (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Crompton &#x00026; Jenkins Jr, 1973</xref>). For example, it must be noted that non therapsid-synapsids with sprawling posture could have left trackways in which the left and right tracks lie near to the axial midline (i.e., narrow internal trackway width mirroring a semi-erect to erect posture of the trackmaker) by adopting side to side flexion of the trunk (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Hopson, 2015</xref>). The same was described for a therapsid trackway by <xref rid="ref-117" ref-type="bibr">Smith (1993)</xref>. Some degree of lateral undulation of the vertebral column causing swing of the hips has been also described on the basis of skeletal remains (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2006</xref>: p. 1305). However, in sprawling trackmakers adopting trunk flexion and producing narrow trackways, tracks are mainly inwardly oriented with respect to the trackway midline (see <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Hopson, 2015</xref>: Fig 8.1). In the studied material, the orientation of footprint axis (passing through digit III) is parallel to the travel direction. This feature, combined with the extremely narrow internal trackway width measured from pes tracks (see <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Figs.&#x000a0;4A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6E</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6H</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7D</xref>), allow to exclude a sprawling posture and most likely indicate a semi-erect posture for the trackmaker hind limbs. A lateral trunk undulation during the step cycle could have been also adopted by the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker and it would account for the variable pace angulation measured in manus tracks, possibly coupled with low trackmaker velocity.</p><p>A more upright posture with respect to that of non-therapsid synapsids is also indirectly sustained by the symmetry of manus and pes tracks. This feature mirrors a symmetry of the trackmaker&#x02019;s autopods, a feature combined with the acquisition of upright posture and limbs parallel to the sagittal plane of the trackmaker during locomotion (<xref rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1956</xref>; <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Hopson, 1995</xref>).</p><p>Number of digit imprints, symmetry of manus and pes track, and the morphology of unguals enable us to corroborate previous interpretations and suggest a dicynodont as the most probable trackmaker of <italic>Pentasauropus.</italic> Also the limb posture as supposed from tracks sufficiently matches those discussed for Triassic dicynodonts by <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch (2006)</xref>.</p><p><italic>Pentasauropus</italic> producers, based on the type specimens, were characterized by a very low dimensional heteropody and morphological homopody. Thus, mainly based on these characters, a quite confident match can be found, among dicynodonts, with Kannemeyeriiformes (see, for example, the descriptions and reconstructions of the autopods of <italic>Dinodontosaurus</italic> by <xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">Morato</xref> (<xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>: Fig. 30), <italic>Tetragonias njalilus</italic> by <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Cruickshank</xref> (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>: Fig. 17) and by <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch</xref> (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>: Fig. 9). Kannemeyeriiform manual and pedal skeletal elements are in fact generally homomorphic and conservative into the clade, as recently stated by <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Kammerer (2018)</xref>. Variation in manus morphology among kannemeyeriiforms is only limited to minor differences in ungual shape (<xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr">Lucas, 2002</xref>). Digit traces are here considered roughly compatible with broad ungual phalanges characterized by rounded tips but the exact shape cannot be determined. The morphological variability of ungual traces most likely relates to substrate conditions at the time of impression and, as discussed below, from the dynamics of the locomotion of the producers.</p><p>Among the other possible producers already mentioned in the literature, are excluded: (i) an amphibian trackmaker, because of the pentadactyl manus and general morphology; (ii) an anapsid trackmaker for the trackway configuration and footprint axis orientation; (iii) a sauropodomorph and sauropod trackmaker for the trackway configuration, footprint axis orientation and morphological homopody.</p><p>The posture of the autopodia of the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker that can be inferred from the ichnological material differs from that inferable from the description by <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Cruickshank (1967)</xref>. In those <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks that show an impression of the sole or palm, a negligible distance between the distal margin of the sole/palm pad trace and the proximal margin of the central digit traces, further reducing towards digits I and V, was observed (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This feature most likely indicates that not all of the foot bones contacted the ground during locomotion, at the same time constraining the orientation of metapodial and basipodial elements, and also that of the more proximal phalanges, in the articulated autopod. Thus, the reconstruction proposed here contemplates an inclined position of pedal and manual elements in the autopods of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> producers. The sub-circular to elliptical pad trace behind the digit traces is consequently considered compatible with an extended fleshy pad below the basipodials and likely metapodials of the autopods of the producer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">Fig. 11</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-11</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption><title>Limb and autopod posture in the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker.</title><p>Simplified reconstruction of limb posture in back (A) and lateral (B) views. Simplified reconstruction of zeugopodials and hind autopod in lateral (C) and bottom (D) views. In colour the possible extension of the fleshy cushion on which the basipodials rested, ensuring support during locomotion. See the supplementary video to get a more complete view of the reconstruction. Artwork by Fabio Manucci.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g011"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>The autopod posture of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker</title><p>Compared to the ichnogenus <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>, tracks from Los Menucos Group have allowed us to verify previous ichnological interpretations based on the reference material from Lesotho and have enabled us to corroborate the identification of a putative trackmaker and its limb posture. Moreover, the studied material sheds light on the trackmaker autopod posture. The smaller tracks (e.g., MPCA27029-16) are here interpreted to have been left by a juvenile trackmaker and allowed to appreciate that track morphology and structure are uniform in different ontogenetic stages of the same type of producer.</p><p>Number of digit imprints, symmetry of manus and pes track, morphology of ungual traces, limb posture and morphologically homopodic manus and pes tracks indicate the producer of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> to be sought among dicynodonts of the clade Kannemeyeriiformes (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2009</xref>). Within this panorama and accepting the proposed palaeozoological attribution, <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks represent a valuable datum, further enriching the dicynodont record of the Triassic of Argentina (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Cox, 1962</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Bonaparte, 1969</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Bonaparte, 1971</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Bonaparte, 1981</xref>; <xref rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr">Lucas, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr">Lucas, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr">Lucas, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-109" ref-type="bibr">Rogers et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-126" ref-type="bibr">Zavattieri &#x00026; Arcucci, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Domnanovich &#x00026; Marsicano, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Abdala et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr">Mancuso et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The studied tracks enabled us to improve the knowledge of the therapsid faunas from south-western Gondwana, especially about their locomotion and functionality of fore and hind autopods. The inferred limb posture of the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker finds a match with the osteological data provided by the therapsid record (e.g., <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">King, 1981a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2006</xref>) and allows to corroborate interpretations derived from body-fossils. Meristic and qualitative track characteristics and trackway parameters, if jointly considered, suggest that the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker had a semi-erect to erect posture, especially the hind limbs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">Figs. 11A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">11B</xref>).</p><p>Contrarily to what was stated about therapsid posture in the past (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Charig, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Bonaparte, 1982</xref>), therapsid-grade limb osteology was characterized by several important modifications, which indicate a more parasagittal stance of the limbs (<xref rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1956</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Boonstra, 1967</xref>; <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Jenkins Jr, 1971</xref>), especially if compared with the prevalent sprawling posture of non-therapsid synapsids (<xref rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1956</xref>; <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Hopson, 2015</xref>). Modifications of the scapula and the glenoid have allowed the elbow to rotate inwardly, bringing the humerus closer to the sagittal plane (<xref rid="ref-125" ref-type="bibr">Walter, 1986</xref>). The iliac blade was expanded anteriorly and allowed the insertion of a larger iliofemoralis muscle (i.e., the muscle that allows movement of the femur with respect to the hip), enabling femoral retraction (<xref rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1956</xref>; <xref rid="ref-125" ref-type="bibr">Walter, 1986</xref>). Moreover, the femoral head folded medially and enabled a more parasagittal position of the propodial (<xref rid="ref-111" ref-type="bibr">Romer, 1922</xref>; <xref rid="ref-125" ref-type="bibr">Walter, 1986</xref>).</p><p>Concerning the dynamics of locomotion in non-mammalian therapsids, <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Kemp (1978)</xref> proposed a dual-gait condition, intermediate between the plesiomorphic gait of amniotes (<xref rid="ref-123" ref-type="bibr">Sumida &#x00026; Modesto, 2001</xref>) and the mammalian erect gait, based on the therocephalian <italic>Regisaurus jacobi</italic>. This condition has proved to be not possible for derived dicynodonts, such as <italic>Kingoria nowacki</italic> (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">King, 1985</xref>) and for kannemeyeriiformes dicynodonts, all characterized by an ankle joint inhibiting extensive rotational movements needed for dual-gait locomotion (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2006</xref>). In dicynodonts, the forelimb step cycle was performed in an abducted (i.e., sprawling) posture, whereas the hind limb step cycle passed from a primitive abducted posture in earlier members, such as <italic>Robertia broomiana</italic> (see <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">King, 1981b</xref>) to an adducted (i.e., erect) posture in more derived taxa (<xref rid="ref-125" ref-type="bibr">Walter, 1986</xref>), such as <italic>Dicynodon trigonocephalus</italic> and <italic>Tetragonias njalilus</italic> (e.g., <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">King, 1981a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Fr&#x000f6;bisch, 2006</xref>).</p><p>The autopod posture proposed for the studied tracks quite differ from the information and reconstructions derived from the body-fossil record. As stated before, the alleged autopodial structure inferred from <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks is dictated by the relative distance between the proximal portion of digital (ungual) traces and the distal edge of the sub-circular pad trace, which has been inferred to relate to a fleshy pad behind the basipodial. The observed track morphology seems to imply that, except for acropodial and the fleshy pad, no other bony elements of the producer&#x02019;s autopods were imprinted on the substrate, indicating that they were likely raised in position. Such a configuration is considered valid for the foot bones in a static-state and would fall at least within a subunguligrade posture, implying that the phalanges were the only bony pedal elements contacting the ground in a static stance. However, if the three-dimensional footprint morphology is considered (i.e., ungual traces and pad trace behind them) concurrently with spatial data regarding pad trace/digit trace distance (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), it is evident that the unguals were not the only pedal elements performing the cycle of locomotion. Thus, the foot cannot be regarded as subunguligrade from a dynamic point of view. During locomotion, the body weight of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> producers was not carried only by phalanges but, most likely, the entire foot supported the load (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">Figs. 11</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-12">12</xref>). The fleshy pad behind the basipodials actively contacted the ground most likely during the touch-down and weight-bearing phase, as was already inferred from footprint depth of impression in other producers (e.g., <xref rid="ref-110" ref-type="bibr">Romano, Citton &#x00026; Nicosia, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Citton et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, from a functional standpoint, the autopod posture of the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker can be regarded as plantiportal (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">Michilsens et al., 2009</xref>) and it is considered to have been maintained during different gaits. Such a posture could have been accompanied by an arched configuration of the articulated metapodials and at least of the proximal phalanges (<xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;mmell &#x00026; Frey, 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">Figs. 11C</xref>&#x02013; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-11">11D</xref>). Metacarpals forming an arched configuration when articulated were described in a specimen of <italic>Tetragonias njalilus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Cruickshank, 1967</xref>), and this kind of configuration could have been accompanied by little movement capabilities (<xref rid="ref-114" ref-type="bibr">Rubidge &#x00026; Hopson, 1996</xref>) of the metapodials and could have dictated the observed relative position of the ungual traces. A manual/pedal structure like the one here hypothesized could have maintained a large surface in contact with the ground by means of cartilaginous elements and fleshy cushions on which the basipodials rested, ensuring a supportive role of the whole autopods during the cycle of locomotion and particularly during the maximum load. Digit traces were formed by phalanges deeply penetrating into the substrate during the final weight-bearing phase, kick-off and thrust. This could explain the different depth of the impression that is observed in completely preserved tracks. Among digits the series II-IV, and with a lesser extent digit I, played a major role in performing the end of the cycle of locomotion. Drag traces affecting the most medial digits could be formed during the recovery of the autopod at the end of the step.</p><fig id="fig-12" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/fig-12</object-id><label>Figure 12</label><caption><title>Speculative <italic>in vivo</italic> reconstruction (based on <italic>Dinodontosaurus</italic>) of a kannemeyeriiformes dicynodont, a most probable producer of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks<italic>.</italic></title><p>Reconstruction in back (A) and lateral (B) view of the trackmaker walking in amble gait. See the supplementary video to get a more complete view of the reconstruction. Artwork by Fabio Manucci.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-g012"/></fig><p>A functionally plantiportal posture has been described in several mammals regardless of body-weight (e.g., South-American coati, aardvark, armadillo, coypu, among others; see <xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">Michilsens et al., 2009</xref>) but also can represent a functional strategy, co-occurring with a graviportal structure of the limbs. A subunguligrade-plantiportal foot implies a complex set of associated characters in the autopodial anatomy of the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> producer. Body mass of taxa similar to the alleged producer of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> have been estimated to be 23&#x02013;32 kg (based on a juvenile individual of <italic>Dinodontosaurus</italic>; see <xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">Morato, 2006</xref>), 170 kg (based on an adult specimen of <italic>Dinodontosaurus brevirostris</italic>; see <xref rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr">Mancuso et al., 2014</xref>) up to 362 kg (based on an adult individual of <italic>Dinodontosaurus platyceps</italic>; see <xref rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr">Mancuso et al., 2014</xref>). The subunguligrade-plantiportal autopod posture was most likely promoted in these dicynodonts and in the putative producer of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> regardless of the body-dimension. Thus, this character not necessarily implies an increase in body size but it is a pre-requisite for those lineages which experienced an increase in body-dimension.</p></sec><sec><title>The Vera Formation and the track record: chronostratigraphical observations</title><p>As before stated, <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> or <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>-like footprints were reported to date mainly from Upper Triassic units. In Argentina, <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> tracks were reported both from Upper Triassic unit (e.g., Portezuelo Formation) and from late Middle Triassic unit (Cerro de Las Cabras Formation). In Lesotho (Southern Africa), <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> was reported from the lower Elliot Formation (Stormberg Group), which lies above the Carnian Molteno Formation. The lower Elliot Formation was considered Upper Triassic by <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger (1970)</xref>, Norian-Rhaetian by <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">Olsen &#x00026; Galton (1984)</xref> and Norian by <xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">Knoll (2004)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-92" ref-type="bibr">Lucas &#x00026; Hancox (2001)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr">Lucas (2018)</xref>, based on fossil remains, both bones and trace fossils. Recently, the Elliot Formation (lower and upper) was discussed by means of magnetostratigraphy, and fixed as Upper Triassic - Lower Jurassic by <xref rid="ref-116" ref-type="bibr">Sciscio et al. (2017)</xref>. The same authors confirmed a Norian-Rhaetian age for the lower Elliot Formation and correlated the unit with the Los Colorados Formation in the Ischigualasto-Villa Union Basin of Argentina (<xref rid="ref-116" ref-type="bibr">Sciscio et al., 2017</xref>). A Late Triassic age of <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>-bearing levels of the Vera Formation (most probably the upper portion of this lithostratigraphic unit) is here accepted based on the currently shared distribution of the ichnogenus.</p><p>At the same time, the recent datations provided by <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Luppo et al. (2017)</xref> contrast with the Late Triassic age historically proposed for the whole Vera Formation and in particular for the deposits bearing the &#x02018;<italic>Dicroidium</italic>&#x02019; flora and the ichnogenus <italic>Dicynodontipus</italic>. On the basis of the new isotopic ages, <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Luppo et al. (2017)</xref> concluded that at least some of the levels bearing the &#x02018;<italic>Dicroidium</italic>&#x02019;-type flora (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Artabe, 1985a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Artabe, 1985b</xref>) are intercalated between deposits dated 252 &#x000b1; 2 Ma (Changhsingian, Late Permian) and 248 &#x000b1; 2 Ma (Olenekian, Early Triassic). These authors also suggested that the stratigraphic position of the deposits exposed in the Tchering quarry, west of Los Menucos town, where <italic>Dicynodontipus</italic> (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Melchor &#x00026; de Valais, 2006</xref>) come from, is not yet completely clear. Nevertheless, this quarry is spatially close to the outcrops where geochronological data were provided by <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">Luppo et al. (2017)</xref>. On the other hand, the Yancaqueo farm from which the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> footprints come, is located east of Los Menucos town and lacks detailed geochronological and geological studies.</p><p>Thus, taking into account these new data and the chronostratigraphical distribution of <italic>Dicynodontipus</italic> (e.g., <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Haubold, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Ceoloni et al., 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-108" ref-type="bibr">Retallack, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">De Klerk, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">Marsicano et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Hunt &#x00026; Lucas, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Klein &#x00026; Lucas, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Costa da Silva, Sedor &#x00026; Sequeira Fernandes, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Fichter &#x00026; Kunz, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Francischini et al., 2018</xref>), the historically proposed Late Triassic age for the the strata of the Vera Formation bearing <italic>Dicynodontipus</italic> (most likely the lower portion of the unit) is here questioned.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Large pentadactyl tracks from the Upper Triassic Vera Formation of the Los Menucos Group (R&#x000ed;o Negro province, North Patagonia, Argentina) were studied and discussed in terms of palaeobiological attribution.</p><p>The tracks are currently referred to as <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Ellenberger, 1970</xref>), an ichnotaxon established from the Upper Triassic lower Elliot Formation (Stormberg Group) of Karoo Basin (Lesotho, Southern Africa).</p><p>Material under study allowed us to more effectively appreciate ichnotaxon variability and proved to be significant for a better definition of the locomotor dynamics of the producer and particularly of its foot anatomy.</p><p>Track and trackway parameters indicate a dicynodont as the most probable producer, and a relationship with the South-American members of the clade Kannemeyeriiformes is proposed.</p><p>An affinity between the Gondwanan therapsid ichnofauna and that from South Africa is evident, as well as functional features of the autopods of the producer are considered significantly similar and may be related to the same autopodial anatomy shared by the clade.</p><p>The autopod posture for the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker has been interpreted as subunguligrade in static posture and plantiportal during locomotion. A large pad of connective tissue behind the basipodials and partially metapodials can be proposed for the heavy-footed producers of <italic>Pentasauropus.</italic> The cushion allowed to decrease the stress transferred to the bones and spread it on a larger area during the touch-down and weight-bearing phase of the locomotion cycle.</p><p>Finally, a Late Triassic age for the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic>-bearing levels of the Vera Formation is accepted, based on the age of other lithostratigraphic units bearing <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> in South Africa and United States. At the same time, a detailed stratigraphic study of the lower strata of the Vera Formation, bearing-<italic>Dicynodontipus</italic>, is needed to corroborate palaeontological and geochronological data and to account the validity of the Vera Formation as lithostratigraphic unit.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5358/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Limb and autopod posture in the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker</title><p>Simplified and <italic>in vivo</italic> speculative reconstruction (based on <italic>Dinodontosaurus</italic>) showing the semi erect posture of fore and hind limbs and the subunguligrade plantiportal posture of the autopods in the <italic>Pentasauropus</italic> trackmaker. In colour the possible extension of the fleshy cushion on which the basipodials rested, ensuring support during locomotion. Artwork by Fabio Manucci.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5358-s001.mp4"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>I. Cerda and C. Mu&#x000f1;&#x000f3;z of the Museo Provincial Carlos Ameghino (Cipolletti, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina), D. Ramos and S. Mercado of the Museo Municipal de Los Menucos (Los Menucos, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina) and R. Rial of the Museo Provincial Mar&#x000ed;a In&#x000e9;s Kopp (Valcheta, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina) are kindly acknowledged for having made access to Los Menucos material possible and for their assistance during museum operations. U.&#x000a0;Nicosia is warmly thanked for having reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript. C.F. Kammerer is sincerely thanked for having discussed some aspects of the autopod osteology in kannemeyeriiformes. S. Lucas, H. Klein, P. Dentzien-Dias and the Academic Editor K. De Baets are acknowledged for having provided revisions that significantly improved the manuscript. F. Manucci is thanked for having performed the&#x000a0;artworks.</p></ack><glossary content-type="abbreviations" id="glossary-1"><title>Institutional abbreviations</title><def-list id="dl2"><def-item><term> LES</term><def><p>Laboratoire de Pal&#x000e9;ontologie, Institut de Sciences de l&#x02019;Evolution of the University of Montpellier II collection, Montpellier, France</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MPCA</term><def><p>Museo Provincial Carlos Ameghino, Cipolletti, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MMLM</term><def><p>Museo Municipal de Los Menucos, Los Menucos, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MMLM (ex MRPV)</term><def><p>Museo Provincial Mar&#x000ed;a In&#x000e9;s Kopp, Valcheta, R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Paolo Citton</xref>, <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Ignacio D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez</xref>, <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Silvina de Valais</xref> and <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Carlos C&#x000f3;nsole-Gonella</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>Citton, Paolo; D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez, Ignacio; de Valais, Silvina; C&#x000f3;nsole-Gonella, Carlos (2018): Pentadactyl tracks from Los Menucos (Patagonia Argentina). figshare. Fileset. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5931715">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5931715</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Abdala et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Swart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Strengthening Western Gondwanan correlations: a Brazilian Dicynodont (Synapsida, Anomodontia) in the Middle Triassic of Namibia</article-title><source>Gondwana Research</source><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2012.07.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Anderson, Anderson &#x00026; Cruickshank (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>ARI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Late Triassic ecosystems of the Molteno/Lower Elliot biome of Southern Africa</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Artabe (1985a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985a</year><article-title>Estudio sistem&#x000e1;tico de la tafoflora tri&#x000e1;sica de Los Menucos, provincia de R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina. Parte I</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Artabe (1985b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985b</year><article-title>Estudio sistem&#x000e1;tico de la tafoflora tri&#x000e1;sica de Los Menucos, provincia de R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina. Parte II</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>22</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>212</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Avanzini, Pi&#x000f1;uela &#x00026; Garc&#x000ed;a-Ramos (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avanzini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi&#x000f1;uela</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Ramos</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Late Jurassic footprints reveal walking kinematics of theropod dinosaurs</article-title><source>Lethaia</source><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1502-3931.2011.00276.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Baird (1980)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>A prosauropod dinosaur trackway from the Navajo Sandstone (Lower Jurassic) of Arizona</article-title><source>Aspect of vertebrate history: essay in honor of Harris Colbert</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-loc>Flagstaff</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Flagstaff Museum of Northern Arizona Press</publisher-name><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>230</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Barredo et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barredo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chemale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottone</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Tectono&#x02014;sequence stratigraphy and U&#x02014;Pb zircon ages of the Rinc&#x000f3;n Blanco depocenter, northern Cuyo rift, Argentina</article-title><source>Gondwana Research</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2011.05.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Belvedere &#x00026; Farlow (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belvedere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>A numerical scale for quantifying the quality of preservation of vertebrate tracks</article-title><source>Dinosaur tracks: the next steps</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Falkingham</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Bogan, Taverne &#x00026; Agnolin (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taverne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnolin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>First Triassic and oldest record of a South American amiiform fish: <italic>Caturus</italic> sp. from the Los Menucos Group (lower Upper Triassic), R&#x000ed;o Negro province, Argentina</article-title><source>Geologica Belgica</source><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Bonaparte (1966)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaparte</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1966</year><article-title>Cronolog&#x000ed;a de algunas formaciones tri&#x000e1;sicas argentinas</article-title><source>Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Bonaparte (1969)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaparte</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1969</year><article-title>Dos nuevas faunas de reptiles tri&#x000e1;sicos de Argentina</article-title><conf-name>First Gondwana symposium, Mar del Plata 1967</conf-name><conf-loc>Paris</conf-loc><conf-sponsor>UNESCO</conf-sponsor><comment>Abstract book, 283&#x02013;306</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Bonaparte (1971)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaparte</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>Annotated list of the South American Triassic tetrapods</article-title><conf-name>Symposium on Gondwana stratigraphy. Proceedings and papers, Pretoria, vol. 2</conf-name><conf-loc>Cape Town and Johannesburg</conf-loc><conf-sponsor>Council of Scientific and Industrial Research</conf-sponsor><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>682</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Bonaparte (1981)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaparte</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Nota sobre una nueva fauna del Triasico Inferior del Sur de Mendoza, Argentina, correspondiente a la zona de <italic>Lystrosaurus</italic> (Dicynodontia-Proterosuchia)</article-title><conf-name>Congreso Latino-Americano de Paleontologia</conf-name><comment>Abstract book, 277&#x02013;288</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Bonaparte (1982)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaparte</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><article-title>Faunal replacement in the Triassic of South America</article-title><source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02724634.1982.10011938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Boonstra (1967)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boonstra</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year><article-title>An early stage in the evolution of the mammalian quadrupedal walking gait</article-title><source>Annals of the South African Museum</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Bordy, Abrahams &#x00026; Sciscio (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bordy</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrahams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciscio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>The Subeng vertebrate tracks: stratigraphy, sedimentology and a digital archive of a historic Upper Triassic palaeosurface (lower Elliot Formation), Leribe, Lesotho (southern Africa)</article-title><source>Bollettino della Societ&#x000e0; Paleontologica Italiana</source><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4435/BSPI.2017.12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Carpenter (1992)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Behavior of hadrosaurs as interpreted from footprints in the &#x0201c;Mesaverde&#x0201d; Group (Campanian) of Colorado, Utah, and Wyoming</article-title><source>Contributions to Geology, University of Wyoming</source><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Casamiquela (1964)</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casamiquela</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1964</year><article-title>Estudios icnol&#x000f3;gicos</article-title><source>Problemas y m&#x000e9;todos de la icnolog&#x000ed;a con aplicaci&#x000f3;n al estudio de pisadas mesozoicas (Reptilia, Mammalia) de la Patagonia</source><institution>Talleres Gr&#x000e1;ficos Colegio Industrial P&#x000ed;o IX, Buenos Aires</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Casamiquela (1975)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casamiquela</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><article-title>Nuevo material y reinterpretaci&#x000f3;n de las icnitas mesozoicas (Neotri&#x000e1;sicas) de Los Menucos, Provincia de Rio Negro (Patagonia)</article-title><conf-name>1&#x000b0; Congreso Argentino de Paleontologia y Biostratigrafia, Tucum&#x000e1;n, Argentina 1974</conf-name><conf-loc>Tucuman</conf-loc><conf-sponsor>Asociaci&#x000f3;n Paleontol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</conf-sponsor><comment>Abstract book, 555&#x02013;580</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Casamiquela (1987)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casamiquela</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Novedades en icnolog&#x000ed;a de vertebrados en la Argentina</article-title><conf-name>10&#x000b0; Congreso Brasileiro de Paleontologia, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</conf-name><comment>Abstract book 1, 445&#x02013;456</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Ceoloni et&#x000a0;al. (1988)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceoloni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>New late permian tetrapod footprints from Southern Alps</article-title><source>Memorie della Societ&#x000e0; Geologica Italiana</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>65</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Charig (1980)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charig</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>Differentiation of lineages among Mesozoic tetrapods</article-title><source>M&#x000e9;moires de la Soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; G&#x000e9;ologique de France NS</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Citton et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Citton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carluccio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolosi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Re-evaluation of <italic>Chelichnus tazelw&#x000fc;rmi</italic>, a non mammalian therapsid-grade track from the Upper Permian Arenaria di Val Gardena</article-title><source>Historical Biology</source><volume>2017</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><comment>In Press</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08912963.2017.1370586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Costa&#x000a0;da Silva, Sedor &#x00026; Sequeira&#x000a0;Fernandes (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa&#x000a0;da Silva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedor</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sequeira&#x000a0;Fernandes</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Fossil footprints from the Late Permian of Brazil: an example of hidden biodiversity</article-title><source>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsames.2012.05.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Cox (1962)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1962</year><article-title>Preliminary diagnosis of <italic>Ischigualastia</italic>, a new genus of dicynodont from Argentina</article-title><source>Breviora</source><volume>156</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Crompton &#x00026; Jenkins&#x000a0;Jr (1973)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins&#x000a0;Jr</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>Mammals from reptiles: a review of mammalian origins</article-title><source>Annual Review of Earth Planetary Science</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ea.01.050173.001023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Cruickshank (1967)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>ARI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year><article-title>A new dicynodont genus from the Manda formation of Tanzania (Tanganyika)</article-title><source>Journal of Zoology</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7998.1967.tb04059.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Cucchi, Busteros &#x00026; Lema (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cucchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Busteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Hoja Geol&#x000f3;gica 4169&#x02014;II, Los Menucos, Provincia de R&#x000ed;o Negro</article-title><source>IGRM-SEGE-MAR Bolet&#x000ed;n</source><volume>265</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>De&#x000a0;Klerk (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Klerk</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A dicynodont trackway from the <italic>Cistecephalus</italic> Assemblage Zone in the Karoo, east of Graaff-Reinet, South Africa</article-title><source>Palaeontologia Africana</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>de&#x000a0;Valais (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Valais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Icnolog&#x000ed;a de tetr&#x000e1;podos tri&#x000e1;sicos y jur&#x000e1;sicos de Argentina: aportes al origen de las aves y los mam&#x000ed;feros</article-title><source>D Phil Thesis</source><institution>Universidad de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>de&#x000a0;Valais, Melchor &#x00026; Bellosi (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Valais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Melchor</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellosi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>New large vertebrate footprints from the Cerro de Las Cabras Formation (Middle Triassic), Mendoza province</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>43</volume><issue>suppl.</issue><fpage>34R</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Castanera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasca</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Canudo</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>A reappraisal of the Middle Triassic chirotheriid <italic>Chirotherium ibericus</italic> Nav&#x000e1;s, 1906 (Iberian Range NE Spain), with comments on the Triassic tetrapod track biochronology of the Iberian Peninsula</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e1044</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26137425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez &#x00026; De&#x000a0;Valais (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Valais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Estudio de la variabilidad en la conservaci&#x000f3;n de huellas de tetr&#x000e1;podos del Tri&#x000e1;sico Superior de Los Menucos, R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>52</volume><issue>suppl. 1</issue><fpage>8</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Domnanovich &#x00026; Marsicano (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domnanovich</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Tetrapod footprints from the Triassic of Patagonia: reappraisal of the evidence</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Domnanovich &#x00026; Marsicano (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domnanovich</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>The Triassic dicynodont <italic>Vinceria</italic> (Therapsida, Anomodontia) from Argentina and a discussion on basal Kannemeyeriiformes</article-title><source>Geobios</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geobios.2011.03.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Domnanovich et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domnanovich</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomassini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Manera&#x000a0;de Bianco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalponte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Nuevos aportes al conocimiento de la icnofauna de tetr&#x000e1;podos del Tri&#x000e1;sico Superior de Los Menucos (Complejo Los Menucos), provincia de R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>45</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>D&#x02019;Orazi&#x000a0;Porchetti &#x00026; Nicosia (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Orazi&#x000a0;Porchetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Re-examination of some large Early Mesozoic tetrapod footprints from the African collection of Paul Ellenberger</article-title><source>Ichnos</source><volume>14</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10420940601049990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Duncan (1831)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1831</year><article-title>An account of the tracks and footmarks of animals found impressed on sandstone in the quarry of Corncockle Muir, in Dumfriesshire</article-title><source>Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0080456800021906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Ellenberger (1955)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1955</year><article-title>Note pr&#x000e9;liminaire sur les pistes et les restes osseux de Vert&#x000e9;br&#x000e9;s du Basutoland (Afrique du Sud)</article-title><source>Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des S&#x000e9;ances de l&#x02019;Acad&#x000e9;mie des Sciences</source><volume>240</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>891</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Ellenberger (1970)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Les niveaux pal&#x000e9;ontologiques de premi&#x000e9;re apparition des mammif&#x000e9;res primordiaux en Afrique du Sud et leur ichnologie. Establissement de zones stratigraphique d&#x000e9;taill&#x000e9;es dans le Stormberg du Lesotho (Afrique du Sud) (Trias superior a Jurassique)</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings and papers II Gondwana symposium, 1970</conf-name><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Ellenberger (1972)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0; la classification des Pistes de Vert&#x000e9;br&#x000e9;s du Trias: Les types du Stormberg d&#x02019;Afrique du Sud (I)</article-title><source>Paleovertebrata, Memoire Extraordinaire</source><publisher-name>Laboratoire de Pal&#x000e9;ontologie de Vert&#x000e8;bres</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Montpellier</publisher-loc><fpage>152</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Ellenberger &#x00026; Ellenberger (1958)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1958</year><article-title>Principaux types de pistes de vert&#x000e9;br&#x000e9;s dans les couches du Stormberg au Basutoland (Afrique du Sud) (Note pr&#x000e9;liminaire)</article-title><source>Comptes-Rendus sommaire des S&#x000e9;ances de la Soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; g&#x000e9;ologique de France</source><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Falk et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasiotis</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>A new experimental setup for studying avian neoichnology and the effects of grain size and moisture content on tracks: trials using the domestic chicken (<italic>Gallus gallus</italic>)</article-title><source>Palaios</source><volume>32</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2110/palo.2017.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Falkingham et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falkingham</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Avanzini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Breithaupt</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Castanera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Citton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorillo</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatesy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Getty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatala</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lallensack</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CHA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mil&#x000e0;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Minter</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Razzolini</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Romilio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salisbury</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciscio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>ALA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Belvedere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>A standard protocol for documenting modern and fossil ichnological data</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><volume>2018</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pala.12373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Fichter &#x00026; Kunz (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fichter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>&#x0201c;Dinosauromorph&#x0201d; tracks from the Middle Buntsandstein (Early Triassic: Olenekian) of Wolfhagen, northern Hesse, Germany</article-title><source>Comunica&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es Geol&#x000f3;gicas</source><volume>100</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Francischini et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francischini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dentzien-Dias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Tetrapod tracks in Permo&#x02014;Triassic eolian beds of southern Brazil (Paran&#x000e1; Basin)</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e4764</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.4764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29796341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Franzese &#x00026; Spalletti (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franzese</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Spalletti</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Late triassic-early Jurassic continental extension in southwestern Gondwana: tectonic segmentation and pre-break-up rifting</article-title><source>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0895-9811(01)00029-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Fr&#x000f6;bisch (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;bisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Locomotion in derived dicynodonts (Synapsida, Anomodontia): a functional analysis of the pelvic girdle and hind limb of <italic>Tetragonias njalilus</italic></article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/e06-031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Fr&#x000f6;bisch (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;bisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Composition and similarity of global anomodont-bearing tetrapod faunas</article-title><source>Earth-Science Reviews</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earscirev.2009.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Gallego (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>A new crustacean clam shrimp (Spinicaudata: Eosestheriidae) from the Upper Triassic of Argentina and its importance for &#x02018;conchostracan&#x02019; taxonomy</article-title><source>Alcheringa: An Australasian Journal of Palaeontology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03115510903546152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Galton &#x00026; Heerden&#x000a0;Van (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galton</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heerden&#x000a0;Van</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Anatomy of the prosauropod dinosaur <italic>Blikanasaurus cromptoni</italic> (Upper Triassic, South Africa), with notes on the other tetrapods from the Lower Elliot Formation</article-title><source>Pal&#x000e4;ontologische Zeitschrift</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02987824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Gaston et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title><italic>Grallator</italic>&#x02014;dominated fossil footprints assemblages and associated enigmatic footprints from the Chinle Group (Upper Triassic), Gateway Area, Colorado</article-title><source>Ichnos</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10420940390256258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Gonz&#x000e1;lez et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Llamb&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Basei</surname><given-names>MAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Middle Triassic trachytic lava flows associated with coeval dyke swarm in the North Patagonian Massif: a postorogenic magmatism related to extensional collapse of the Gondwanide orogen</article-title><source>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsames.2017.02.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Haubold (1974)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haubold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><source>Die fossilien Saurierf&#x000e4;hrten</source><publisher-name>A. Ziemsen</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wittenberg</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Haubold (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haubold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Archosaur evidence in the Buntsandstein (Lower Triassic)</article-title><source>Acta Palaeontologica Polonica</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Haubold (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haubold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><source><italic toggle="yes">Saurierf&#x000e4;hrten</italic>. Die Neue Brehm-Bucherei</source><publisher-name>A. Ziemsen Verlagl</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Wittenberg Lutherstadt</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Hitchcock (1836)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hitchcock</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1836</year><article-title>Ornithichnology&#x02014;description of the foot marks of birds (Ornithichnites) on New Red Sandstone in Massachusetts</article-title><source>American Journal of Science</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Hopson (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Patterns of evolution in the manus and pes of nonmammalian therapsids</article-title><source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02724634.1995.10011252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Hopson (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Fossils, trackways, and transitions in locomotion: a case study of <italic>Dimetrodon</italic></article-title><source>Great transformations in vertebrate evolution</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dial</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shubin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brainerd</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7208/chicago/9780226268392.001.0001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Hunt &#x00026; Lucas (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The Triassic tetrapod track record: ichnofaunas, ichnofacies and biochronology</article-title><source>New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science Bulletin</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>Hunt, Lucas &#x00026; Klein (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Late Triassic nonmarine vertebrate and invertebrate trace fossils and the pattern of the Phanerozoic record of vertebrate trace fossils</article-title><source>The Late Triassic world</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-68009-5_12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>Hunt-Foster et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt-Foster</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>ARC</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Breithaupt</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Tracking dinosaurs in BLM canyon country, Utah</article-title><source>Geology of the Intermountain West</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>Jenkins&#x000a0;Jr (1971)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins&#x000a0;Jr</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>The postcranial skeleton of African cynodonts</article-title><source>Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University, Bulletin</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>Kammerer (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kammerer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>The first skeletal evidence of a dicynodont from the lower Elliot Formation of South Africa</article-title><source>Palaeontologia Africana</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>128</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-65"><label>Kaup (1835a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaup</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1835a</year><article-title>&#x000dc;ber Thierf&#x000e4;hrten bei Hildburghausen</article-title><source>Neues Jahrbuch f&#x000fc;r Mineralogie, Geologie und Pal&#x000e4;ontologie</source><volume>1835</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>328</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-66"><label>Kaup (1835b)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaup</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1835b</year><article-title>F&#x000e4;hrten von Beuteltieren</article-title><source>Das Tierreich</source><publisher-loc>Darmstadt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>J.P. Diehl</publisher-name><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-67"><label>Kemp (1978)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>Stance and gait in the hindlimb of a therocephalian mammal-like reptile</article-title><source>Journal of Zoology</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7998.1978.tb03362.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-68"><label>King (1981a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981a</year><article-title>The functional anatomy of a Permian dicynodont</article-title><source>Philosophical Transaction of the Royal Society of London B</source><volume>291</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1981.0001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-69"><label>King (1981b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981b</year><article-title>The post cranial skeleton of <italic>Robertia broomiana</italic>, an early dicynodont (Reptilia, Therapsida) from the South African Karoo</article-title><source>Annals of South African Museum</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-70"><label>King (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>The postcranial skeleton of <italic>Kingoria nowacki</italic> (von Huene) (Therapsida: Dicynodontia)</article-title><source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1985.tb01801.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-71"><label>Klein &#x00026; Lucas (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Tetrapod footprints&#x02014;their use in biostratigraphy and biochronology of the Triassic</article-title><volume>vol. 334</volume><source>The Triassic Timescale Geological Society, London, Special Publications</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/SP334.14</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-72"><label>Knoll (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Review of the tetrapod fauna of the &#x0201c;Lower Stormberg Group&#x0201d; of the main Karoo Basin (southern Africa): implication for the age of the Lower Elliot Formation</article-title><source>Bulletin de la Societe g&#x000e9;ologique de France</source><volume>175</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2113/175.1.73</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-73"><label>Kokogian et&#x000a0;al. (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kokogian</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spalletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcober</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Milana</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavattieri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pap&#x000f9;</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Los dep&#x000f3;sitos continentales tri&#x000e1;sicos</article-title><source>Anales del Instituto de Geologia y Recursos Minerales</source><volume>29</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>398</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-74"><label>Kubo &#x00026; Benton (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Tetrapod postural shift estimated from Permian and Triassic trackways</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-4983.2009.00897.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-75"><label>Kubo &#x00026; Ozaki (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Does pace angulation correlate with limb posture?</article-title><source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Paleoecology</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2009.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-76"><label>K&#x000fc;mmell &#x00026; Frey (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;mmell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Digital arcade in the autopodia of Synapsida: standard position of the digits and dorsoventral excursion angle of digital joints in the rays II&#x02013;IV</article-title><source>Palaeobiodiversity and Palaeoenvironments</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12549-012-0076-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-77"><label>Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labud&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjerg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>El Grupo Los Menucos: redefinici&#x000f3;n estratigr&#x000e1;fica del Tri&#x000e1;sico Superior del Macizo Nordpatagonico</article-title><source>Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>407</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-78"><label>Labud&#x000ed;a &#x00026; Bjerg (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labud&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjerg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Geolog&#x000ed;a del Grupo Los Menucos, Comarca Nordpatag&#x000f3;nica, Argentina</article-title><conf-name>16&#x000b0; Congreso Geol&#x000f3;gico Argentino</conf-name><conf-loc>La Plata</conf-loc><conf-sponsor>RAGA (Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina)</conf-sponsor><comment>Abstract book, 233&#x02013;238</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-79"><label>Labud&#x000ed;a et&#x000a0;al. (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labud&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Llamb&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapela</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>El Tri&#x000e1;sico de Los Menucos: procesos volc&#x000e1;nicos y sedimentarios</article-title><source>2&#x000b0; Reuni&#x000f3;n del Tri&#x000e1;sico de Cono Sur</source><publisher-name>Universidad Nacional del Sur</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bah&#x000ed;a Blanca</publisher-loc><comment>Abstract book, 17&#x02013;21</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-80"><label>Lema et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Busteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacosa</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cucchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Geolog&#x000ed;a del complejo volc&#x000e1;nico Los Menucos en el &#x000e1;rea tipo, R&#x000ed;o Negro</article-title><source>Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-81"><label>Leonardi (1987)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><source>Glossary and manual of tetrapod footprint <italic toggle="yes">palaeoichnology</italic></source><publisher-name>Departamento Nacional da Produ&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Mineral</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Brasilia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-82"><label>Leonardi (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><source>Annotated atlas of South America tetrapod footprints (Devonian-Holocene)</source><publisher-name>Ministerio de Minas y Energia, Companhia de Pesquisa de Recursos Minerais</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Brazil</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-83"><label>Leonardi &#x00026; De&#x000a0;Oliveira (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Oliveira</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>A revision of the Triassic and Jurassic tetrapod footprints of Argentina and a new approach on the age and meaning of the Botucatu Formation footprints (Brazil)</article-title><source>Revista Brasileira de Geociencias</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>229</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-84"><label>Lockley (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><source>Tracking Dinosaurs. A new look at an ancient world</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-85"><label>Lockley &#x00026; Hunt (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><source>Dinosaur tracks and other fossil footprint of the Western United States</source><publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-86"><label>Lockley et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrea</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Breithaupt</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierlinski</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Surmik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Theropod courtship: large scale physical evidence of display arenas and avian-like scrape ceremony behaviour by Cretaceous dinosaurs</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>18952</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep18952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26741567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-87"><label>Lockley &#x00026; Meyer (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><source>Dinosaur tracks and other fossil footprints of Europe</source><publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-88"><label>Lucas (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Global Triassic tetrapod biostratigraphy and biochronology</article-title><source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology</source><volume>143</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-0182(98)00117-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-89"><label>Lucas (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A new dicynodont from the Triassic of Brazil and the tetrapod biochronology of the Brazilian Triassic</article-title><source>New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science Bulletin</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-90"><label>Lucas (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>The Triassic timescale based on nonmarine tetrapod biostratigraphy and biochronology</article-title><volume>334</volume><source>The Triassic timescale</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Geological Society</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><comment> Special Publications</comment><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/SP334.15</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-91"><label>Lucas (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Late Triassic Terrestrial Tetrapods: biostratigraphy, biochronology and biotic events</article-title><source>The late triassic world</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-68009-5_12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-92"><label>Lucas &#x00026; Hancox (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Tetrapod-based correlation of the nonmarine Upper Triassic of Southern Africa</article-title><source>Albertiana</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-93"><label>Luppo et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luppo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez De&#x000a0;Luchi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapalini</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez&#x000a0;Dopico</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Geochronologic evidence of a large magmatic province in northern Patagonia encompassing the Permian-Triassic boundary</article-title><source>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</source><volume>2017</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsames.2018.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-94"><label>Mackenzie, Donaldson &#x00026; Guilford (1982)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><source>Atlas of igneous rocks and their textures</source><publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-95"><label>Mallison &#x00026; Wings (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallison</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wings</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Photogrammetry in Paleontology&#x02014;a practical guide</article-title><source>Journal of Paleontological Techniques</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-96"><label>Mancuso et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaetano</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leardi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcucci</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>The Cha&#x000f1;ares formation: a window to a Middle Triassic tetrapod community</article-title><source>Lethaia</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/let.12055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-97"><label>Marsicano et&#x000a0;al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcucci</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caselli</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Middle Triassic tetrapod footprints of southern South America</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>41</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-98"><label>Marsicano &#x00026; Barredo (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsicano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barredo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>A Triassic tetrapod footprint assemblage from southern South America: palaeobiogeographical and evolutionary implications</article-title><source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeocology</source><volume>203</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-0182(03)00689-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-99"><label>Marty, Falkingham &#x00026; Richter (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Falkingham</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Dinosaur track terminology: a glossary of terms</article-title><source>Dinosaur tracks: the next steps</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Falkingham</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>402</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-100"><label>Melchor &#x00026; de&#x000a0;Valais (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melchor</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Valais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>A review of Triassic tetrapod track assemblages from Argentina</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-4983.2006.00538.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-101"><label>Melchor, Genise &#x00026; Poir&#x000e9; (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melchor</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Genise</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Poir&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>DGG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Icnolog&#x000ed;a de los dep&#x000f3;sitos continentales tri&#x000e1;sicos</article-title><source>El Sistema Tri&#x000e1;sico en Argentina</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamuner</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-loc>La Plata</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Fundaci&#x000f3;n Museo de La Plata &#x02018;Francisco Pascasio Moreno&#x02019;</publisher-name><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-102"><label>Michilsens et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michilsens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van&#x000a0;Damme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Aout</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Scaling of plantar pressures in mammals</article-title><source>Journal of Zoology</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7998.2009.00611.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-103"><label>Morato (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title><italic>Dinodontosaurus</italic> (Synapsida, Dicynodontia): reconstitui&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es morfol&#x000f3;gicas e aspectos biomec&#x000e2;nicos</article-title><source>Master Thesis</source><institution>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul do Porto Alegre, Instituto de Geoci&#x000ea;ncias, &#x000c1;rea de Concentra&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Paleontologia</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-104"><label>Olsen &#x00026; Galton (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Galton</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>A review of the reptile and amphibian assemblages from the Stormberg of southern Africa, with special emphasis on the footprints and the age of the Stormberg</article-title><source>Paleontologica Africana</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-105"><label>Peabody (1948)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peabody</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1948</year><article-title>Reptile and Amphibian trackways from the Lower Triassic Moenkopi Formation of Arizona and Utah</article-title><source>Bulletin of the Department of Geological Sciences</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>468</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-106"><label>Peabody (1959)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peabody</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1959</year><article-title>Trackways of living and fossil salamanders</article-title><source>University of California Publications in Zoology</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-107"><label>Rapela et&#x000a0;al. (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapela</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pankhurst</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Llamb&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Labudia</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Artabe</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Gondwana magmatism of Patagonia: inner cordilleran calc-alkaline batholiths and bimodal volcanic provinces</article-title><conf-name>3&#x000b0; international symposium on Andean Geodynamics, Saint Malo</conf-name><conf-loc>Paris</conf-loc><conf-sponsor>ORSTOM</conf-sponsor><comment>Extended Abstract book, 791&#x02013;794</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-108"><label>Retallack (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Retallack</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Early Triassic therapsid footprints from the Sidney Basin, Australia</article-title><source>Alcheringa</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03115519608619473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-109"><label>Rogers et&#x000a0;al. (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereno</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Paleoenvironment and taphonomy of the Cha&#x000f1;ares Formation tetrapod assemblage (Middle Triassic), northwestern Argentina: spectacular preservation in volcanogenic concretions</article-title><source>Palaios</source><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1669/0883-1351(2001)016&#x0003c;0461:PATOTC&#x0003e;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-110"><label>Romano, Citton &#x00026; Nicosia (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Citton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Corroborating trackmaker identification through footprint functional analysis: the case study of <italic>Ichniotherium</italic> and <italic>Dimetropus</italic></article-title><source>Lethaia</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/let.12136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-111"><label>Romer (1922)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1922</year><article-title>The locomotor apparatus of certain primitive and mammal-like reptiles</article-title><source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-112"><label>Romer (1956)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1956</year><source>Osteology of the reptiles</source><publisher-name>Krieger Publishing Company</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Malabar (FL)</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-113"><label>Romer (1966)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1966</year><article-title>The Cha&#x000f1;ares (Argentina) Triassic reptile fauna; I. Introduction</article-title><source>Breviora</source><volume>247</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-114"><label>Rubidge &#x00026; Hopson (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubidge</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>A primitive anomodont therapsid from the base of the Beaufort Group (Upper Permian) of South Africa</article-title><source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source><volume>117</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1996.tb02152.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-115"><label>Scasso &#x00026; Limarino (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scasso</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Limarino</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Petrolog&#x000ed;a y diag&#x000e9;nesis de rocas cl&#x000e1;sticas</article-title><volume>vol. 1</volume><source>Asociaci&#x000f3;n Argentina de Sedimentolog&#x000ed;a, Publicaci&#x000f3;n Especial</source><publisher-name>Asociaci&#x000f3;n Argentina de Sedimentolog&#x000ed;a</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc><fpage>259</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-116"><label>Sciscio et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sciscio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Kock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Magnetostratigraphy over the Triassic-Jurassic boundary in the main Karoo Basin</article-title><source>Gondwana Research</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2017.07.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-117"><label>Smith (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RMH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Sedimentology and ichnology of floodplain paleosurfaces in the Beaufort Group (Late Permian), Karoo Sequence, South Africa</article-title><source>Palaios</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3515265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-118"><label>Spalletti (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spalletti</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Cuencas tri&#x000e1;sicas del Oeste argentino: origen y evoluci&#x000f3;n</article-title><source>Acta Geol&#x000f3;gica Hisp&#x000e1;nica</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-119"><label>Stipanicic (1967)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stipanicic</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year><article-title>Consideraciones sobre las edades de algunas fases magm&#x000e1;ticas del Neopaleozoico y Mesozoico</article-title><source>Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>133</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-120"><label>Stipanicic &#x00026; Methol (1972)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stipanicic</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Methol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>Macizo de Som&#x000fa;n Cur&#x000e1;</article-title><source>Geolog&#x000ed;a Regional Argentina</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Leanza</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Academia Nacional de Ciencias de C&#x000f3;rdoba</publisher-name><publisher-loc>C&#x000f3;rdoba</publisher-loc><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>600</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-121"><label>Stipanicic &#x00026; Methol (1980)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stipanicic</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Methol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>Comarca Norpatag&#x000f3;nica</article-title><source>Geolog&#x000ed;a Regional Argentina</source><publisher-name>Academia Nacional de Ciencias de C&#x000f3;rdoba</publisher-name><publisher-loc>C&#x000f3;rdoba</publisher-loc><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1097</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-122"><label>Stipanicic et&#x000a0;al. (1968)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stipanicic</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baulies</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1968</year><article-title>Las formaciones pre-senonianas en el denominado Macizo Nordpatag&#x000f3;nico y regiones adyacentes</article-title><source>Revista de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Geol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-123"><label>Sumida &#x00026; Modesto (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumida</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Modesto</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>A phylogenetic perspective on locomotory strategies in early amniotes</article-title><source>American Zoologist</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/41.3.586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-124"><label>Von&#x000a0;Huene (1931)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von&#x000a0;Huene</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1931</year><article-title>Die fossilen F&#x000e4;hrten im Rh&#x000e4;t von Ischigualasto in Nordwest-Argentinien</article-title><source>Palaeobiologica</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-125"><label>Walter (1986)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>The limb posture of kannemeyeriid dicynodonts: functional and ecological consideration</article-title><source>The beginning of the age of Dinosaurs</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Padian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-126"><label>Zavattieri &#x00026; Arcucci (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zavattieri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcucci</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Edad y posici&#x000f3;n estratigr&#x000e1;fica de los tetr&#x000e1;podos del cerro Bayo de Potrerillos (Tri&#x000e1;sico), Mendoza, Argentina</article-title><source>Ameghiniana</source><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>