<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26540101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-18885</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Collagen Sequence Analysis of the Extinct Giant Ground Sloths <italic>Lestodon</italic> and <italic>Megatherium</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Collagen Sequence Analysis of Extinct Giant Ground Sloths</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lawless</surname><given-names>Craig</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tambusso</surname><given-names>P. Sebasti&#x000e1;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Varela</surname><given-names>Luciano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>Alfredo A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>Jaime E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>Jorge G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff006">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Life Sciences, Manchester Interdisciplinary Biocentre, The University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Secci&#x000f3;n Paleontolog&#x000ed;a, Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad de la Rep&#x000fa;blica, Igu&#x000e1; 4225, Montevideo, Uruguay</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Michael Smith Building, The University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Facultad de Ciencias Naturales y Museo, Museo de La Plata, Buenos Aires, Argentina</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff005">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Facultad de Ciencias Naturales, Universidad Nacional de Tucum&#x000e1;n, Tucum&#x000e1;n Province, Argentina</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff006">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Instituto Superior de Estudios Sociales-CONICET, Instituto de Arqueolog&#x000ed;a y Museo-UNT, Tucum&#x000e1;n Province, Argentina</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>Axel</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>BiK-F Biodiversity and Climate Research Center, GERMANY</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Performed the experiments: MB RF CL PST LV JEP JGM. Analyzed the data: MB CL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MB RF CL PST LV JEP JGM AC. Wrote the paper: MB RF CL PST LV JEP JGM AC.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>m.buckley@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e0139611</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Buckley et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Buckley et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0139611.pdf"/><abstract><p>For over 200 years, fossils of bizarre extinct creatures have been described from the Americas that have ranged from giant ground sloths to the &#x02018;native&#x02019; South American ungulates, groups of mammals that evolved in relative isolation on South America. Ground sloths belong to the South American xenarthrans, a group with modern although morphologically and ecologically very different representatives (anteaters, armadillos and sloths), which has been proposed to be one of the four main eutherian clades. Recently, proteomics analyses of bone collagen have recently been used to yield a molecular phylogeny for a range of mammals including the unusual &#x02018;Malagasy aardvark&#x02019; shown to be most closely related to the afrotherian tenrecs, and the south American ungulates supporting their morphological association with condylarths. However, proteomics results generate partial sequence information that could impact upon the phylogenetic placement that has not been appropriately tested. For comparison, this paper examines the phylogenetic potential of proteomics-based sequencing through the analysis of collagen extracted from two extinct giant ground sloths, <italic>Lestodon</italic> and <italic>Megatherium</italic>. The ground sloths were placed as sister taxa to extant sloths, but with a closer relationship between <italic>Lestodon</italic> and the extant sloths than the basal <italic>Megatherium</italic>. These results highlight that proteomics methods could yield plausible phylogenies that share similarities with other methods, but have the potential to be more useful in fossils beyond the limits of ancient DNA survival.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors gratefully acknowledge the Royal Society for fellowship funding to MB. This is a contribution to the project "Prospecci&#x000f3;n de nuevos sitios fosil&#x000ed;feros y arqueol&#x000f3;gicos en el &#x000e1;rea del Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no" funded by the Comisi&#x000f3;n Sectorial de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Cient&#x000ed;fica, Universidad de la Rep&#x000fa;blica and both Comuna Canaria and Municipio de Sauce partially funded the excavations of RF and his team. The authors are grateful to funding for recovery of one of the Megatherium specimens under the grant CIUNT 26G522 to JP.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are available from the PeptideAtlas (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753">http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are available from the PeptideAtlas (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753">http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the last few decades, the impressive South American megafauna has been the subject of an increasing research effort [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Among its several appeals, its taxonomic composition is highly peculiar, with many giant xenarthrans across a range of localities. With only about 30 living, rather small species (21 armadillos, four tree sloths and six anteaters; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]), this monophyletic group of placental mammals had an impressive richness throughout the South American Cenozoic [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. They reached North America during the Great American Biotic Interchange (GABI; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]) and many of its species (especially those of large body size) went extinct near the Pleistocene&#x02014;Holocene border [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. According to the latest classification, xenarthrans, one of the four main placental clades, are the sister group of the remaining placentals, the Epitheria [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], although that node has proved unstable in recent molecular phylogenies (e.g., associated with Afrotheria to make up the Atlantogenata, [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]). Within the Xenarthra, with an origin of around 105 Ma [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], two groups are recognized [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]; one of them, Cingulata, consisting of the armadillos and their extinct relatives (glyptodonts and pampatheres) and the other, Pilosa, including the anteaters (Vermilingua) and the sloths (Tardigrada [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]&#x02013;but see discussions on nomenclature in Fari&#x000f1;a &#x00026; Vizca&#x000ed;no [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]).</p><p>While the cingulates, with their several modern species, have been the subject of molecular systematics [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], sloths, being so poorly represented in modern faunas, have been mostly classified based on morphological characteristics [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], although molecular phylogenies including extant sloths do exist and they are congruent with those based on morphological characters [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Moreover, it should be noted that ancient DNA (aDNA) has been described for the fur and faeces of the exceptionally well-preserved <italic>Mylodon darwinii</italic> found mummified in &#x000da;ltima Esperanza, southern Chile [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and <italic>Nothrotheriops shastensis</italic> in Gypsum Cave, USA [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Molecular results are congruent with morphological phylogenies [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] that place the modern three-toed sloth <italic>Bradypus</italic> as the sister group of the remaining sloths and the two-toed sloth <italic>Choloepus</italic> among the Megalonychidae. The Mylodontidae, the group that includes one of the species analysed here, <italic>Lestodon armatus</italic>, split in the first subsequent dichotomy from the Megatherioidea, which includes the other species dealt with in this paper, <italic>Megatherium americanum</italic>.</p><p>Although aDNA gives interesting results in terms of phylogeny and systematics, some proteins, another phylogenetically-informative class of biomolecules, especially collagen, are promissory as well [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. They survive in fossils for lengths of time that are an order of magnitude greater than for DNA [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and have been investigated for the phylogenetic potential to resolve the relationships of extinct taxa for decades [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Recent developments in protein sequence analysis enable complex mixtures of proteins (i.e., proteomes) to be routinely analysed using techniques of &#x02018;soft-ionisation&#x02019; mass spectrometry. This technology now allows us the ability to obtain protein sequence information and infer evolutionary relationships from long extinct organisms much deeper into the past than previously thought possible.</p><p>Although the biomineralised tissue that is bone contains thousands of different proteins [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], most of these do not survive long periods of time within a burial environment, where a general qualitative decrease in proteome complexity with increasing chronological age has been observed [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, the dominant protein of bone, type 1 collagen, has been demonstrated to survive much longer than other non-collagenous proteins [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and also, more importantly, in specimens that no longer yield aDNA [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Recent analyses unambiguously reporting the survival of collagen within Pliocene sub-fossil material ~3.5 Ma [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] demonstrate its potential for a wide range of extinct taxa. Although the use of ancient collagen to infer phylogenetic relationships of extinct taxa has been practised for several decades [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], it is only relatively recently that collagen sequence information has been acquired using proteomics techniques. Although proteomics has the advantage that it can retrieve sequence information from complex mixtures of proteins and peptides [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], because of its probability-matching nature, it is prone to false positive matches and potentially non-random sequence acquisition. Thus the sometimes highly-partial nature of the acquired sequences, which have recently been used to identify the &#x02018;malagasy aardvark&#x02019; as a type of giant tenrec [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and confirmation that the South American endemic ungulates derive from condylarths [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] needs further validation in light of new sequence information from other taxonomic groups.</p><p>The aims of this research are to evaluate the phylogenetic integrity of collagen sequencing by proteomics where sequence information of closely-related taxa is limited. Given that the xenarthrans remain the poorest studied of the four major mammalian groups, here we present results of the species <italic>Megatherium americanum</italic>, known since the last years of the 18<sup>th</sup> century [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and <italic>Lestodon armatus</italic>, described in the mid-19<sup>th</sup> century [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>All permits were obtained to recover archaeological/palaeontological material where required. Protein extraction from two specimens of <italic>Lestodon</italic> (specimen numbers 474 and 975A; repository: held in the Colecci&#x000f3;n del Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no, Sauce, Departamento de Canelones, Uruguay, no permits were required for the described study under Uruguayan law) from the Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no site, ca. 30 Ka; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]) and two specimens of <italic>Megatherium</italic> (one ungual phalange from Penas de las Trampas 1.1, Argentina, ca 12.5 Ka [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] specimen code PVL 6786&#x02013;1 held in the Colecci&#x000f3;n Paleontolog&#x000ed;a Vertebrados Lillo, Facultad de Ciencias Naturales e Instituto Miguel Lillo&#x02014;Universidad Nacional de Tucum&#x000e1;n, Miguel Lillo 205. (4000) San Miguel de Tucum&#x000e1;n, Argentina under permits issued by the Direcci&#x000f3;n Provincial de Antropolog&#x000ed;a-Secretar&#x000ed;a de Estado de Catamarca, Argentina Resoluci&#x000f3;n N&#x000b0; 098/11, and one from Las Chacras, Rio Negro, Argentina, ca Late Pleistocene; MAPB# 3965, a museum specimen at the Museo Arqueol&#x000f3;gico y Paleontol&#x000f3;gico de Bariloche, R&#x000ed;o Negro, Argentina, dated to ca. 18 Ka) was carried out following methods described by Wadsworth &#x00026; Buckley [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In brief, ~30&#x02013;50 mg bone powder was decalcified with 0.6 M hydrochloric acid (HCl) for ~18 hours, and centrifuged (14,000 rpm) for 5 min. The supernatant was then frozen whilst the acid-insoluble residue was gelatinised with 6 M Guanidine hydrochloride/5 mM Tris-HCl for a further 18 hours. The fraction of acid-soluble proteins (predominantly collagen) was then applied to a 10 kDa ultrafilter (Vivaspin, UK) and centrifuged, which was repeated with the centrifuged supernatant from the acid-insoluble residue extraction. After the solubilised proteins had passed through the filter, two volumes of 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate (ABC) were also passed through. A further 200 &#x003bc;L ABC was added to the filter, mixed and recovered, which was then incubated with 10 &#x003bc;L 100 mM dithiothreitol (in 50 mM ABC) for 10 min at 60&#x000b0;C. 40 &#x003bc;L of iodoacetamide was added to each sample and then stored in the dark at room temperature for 45 min followed by the addition of a further 10 &#x003bc;L 100 mM dithiothreitol. The sample was then digested overnight with 2 &#x003bc;g sequencing grade trypsin (Promega, UK) at 37&#x000b0;C and subsequently cleaned using C18 ziptips following manufacturer&#x02019;s procotol (Varian OMIX, UK), dried down and resuspended with 10 &#x003bc;L 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid. 1 &#x003bc;L of each sample was then spotted onto a Bruker 384 well Matrix Assisted Laser Desorption Ionization (MALDI) target plate and co-crystalised with 1 &#x003bc;L alpha-cyano hydroxycinnamic acid prior to MALDI analysis. MALDI spectra were acquired on a Bruker Ultraflex II with a Time of Flight (ToF) mass analyser, over an <italic>m/z</italic> range of 700&#x02013;3700 using 1000 laser acquisitions.</p><p>Samples were also analysed by LC&#x02014;MS/MS using an UltiMate<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> 3000 Rapid Separation LC (RSLC, Dionex Corporation, Sunnyvale, CA) coupled to an Orbitrap Elite (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) mass spectrometer (120 k resolution, Full Scan, Positive mode, normal mass range 350&#x02013;1500). Peptides in the sample were separated on a 75 mm &#x000d7; 250 &#x003bc;m i.d. 1.7 &#x003bc;M Ethylene Bridged Hybrid (BEH) C18 analytical column (Waters, UK) using a gradient from 92% A (0.1% formic acid in water) and 8% B (0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile) to 33% B in 44 min at a flow rate of 300 nL min&#x02212;1. Peptides were then automatically selected for fragmentation by data-dependent analysis; 6 MS/MS scans (Velos ion trap, product ion scans, rapid scan rate, Centroid data; scan event: 500 count minimum signal threshold, top 6) were acquired per cycle, dynamic exclusion was employed, and 1 repeat scan (2 MS/MS scans total) was acquired in a 30 s repeat duration with that precursor being excluded for the subsequent 30 s (activation: CID, 2+ default charge state, 2 <italic>m/z</italic> isolation width, 35 eV normalised collision energy, 0.25 Activation Q, 10.0 ms Activation time). Peptide spectra obtained via LC&#x02014;MS/MS were searched against the SwissProt database using the Mascot search engine (v. 2.2.0.6; Matrix Science, London, UK). Error tolerant searches included the fixed carbamidomethyl modification of cysteine (+57.02 Da) and the variable modifications for oxidation of lysine and proline residues (all +15.99 Da) to account for PTMs (the oxidation of lysine and proline being equivalent to hydroxylation commonly observed in collagen, the dominant protein in bone), whereas decoy searches were run with the additional variable modifications allowing for the oxidation of methionine and deamidation of asparagine and glutamine (+0.98 Da) to allow for diagenetic alterations. Enzyme specificity was limited to trypsin (trypsin/P) with one (error tolerant) or two (decoy) missed cleavages allowed, mass tolerances were set at 5 ppm for the precursor ions and 0.5 Da for the fragment ions; all spectra were considered as having either 2+ or 3+ precursors. Highest matching peptide scores for homologous sequences were then manually inspected for quality, and the most appropriate added to a custom sequence database for subsequent further Error Tolerant and decoy Mascot searches. Initial sequences were obtained via Mascot searches against the other 44 mammalian sequences obtained from the Ensembl databases and the UCSC genome browser as well as the COL1A2 sequence (81% complete) for two-toed sloth (<italic>Choloepus</italic>) and supported by the use of &#x02018;mammal&#x02019; sequences whereby variable amino acid loci, across all sequences, were replaced with an X (a similar method to the Error Tolerant search mentioned above but that allow for more variable post-translational modifications).</p><p>The Mascot results from the MS/MS queries for the specimens that produced collagen PMFs were filtered to only include peptide matches greater than the highest false positive score for that individual analysis (<xref rid="pone.0139611.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref> Sheets A-F); only peptide matches found in both specimens for each extinct species were used for the sequence analyses. These sequences were then ordered by position and manually aligned in BioEdit Sequence Alignment Editor v.7.1.3.0 with X representing unknown/unmatched amino acid residues (? when at an indel site in sequences from other taxa); where isobaric residues such as isoleucine and leucine were present at the same site, the most abundant was used throughout due to the inability of the presented technique to distinguish between them (<xref rid="pone.0139611.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 File</xref>). MS/MS spectra for new unique peptides are presented in the supplementary material (Figures B-P in <xref rid="pone.0139611.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 File</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses of the concatenated collagen alpha 1 and alpha 2 sequences (via an R residue; yielding a total length of 2098 amino acid residues) were then carried out using the PhyML plugin [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] for Geneious version 7.1.2 with 44 other mammalian type 1 collagen sequences (concatenated chains) obtained from the Ensembl databases and the UCSC genome browser. The JTT + I + G model was used, identified as most appropriate by PartitionFinderProtein v1.1.1 [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Trees were rooted to the duck-billed platypus (<italic>Ornithorhynchus</italic>) as a prototherian out-group. 10,000 bootstraps were carried out to estimate support with NNI branch swapping. Bayesian analyses were also carried out using the MrBayes 3.2.2 [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] with 3,000,000 MCMC generations, discarding the first 25% as burn-in, estimated invariable gamma distribution (4 categories), 4 chains (3 heated, 1 cold) with unconstrained branch lengths and also rooted to the duck-billed platypus (<italic>Ornithorhynchus</italic>). For analyses including only alpha 2 (I) sequences, the <italic>Choloepus</italic> sequence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec003"><title>Results</title><p>MALDI mass spectrometric fingerprints of the extracted <italic>Megatherium</italic> and <italic>Lestodon</italic> bone collagen (<xref rid="pone.0139611.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) were evaluated primarily for qualitative purposes to confirm the extraction and subsequent enzymatic digestion of protein from the sub-fossil material, but peak differences were also studied for potential variations that could aid the subsequent in-depth proteome analysis. Close inspection of the fingerprints (<xref rid="pone.0139611.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) indicate numerous potentially homologous differences (<xref rid="pone.0139611.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), each likely to possess one or more amino acid substitutions. The number of shared MALDI peaks was substantially greater between the two extant sloths than between any other pair of taxa (<xref rid="pone.0139611.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). By comparison there are more amino acid substitutions in the recovered proteomic data between the two extinct ground sloths identified from the LC-MS/MS data (<xref rid="pone.0139611.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0139611.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>). However, it should be noted that sequence coverage can be highly variable between analyses of different species, ranging from 56% to 77% when only peptide matches above the highest scoring false positive match are used (<xref rid="pone.0139611.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0139611.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>MALDI-ToF mass spectra of collagen extracted from <italic>Lestodon</italic> and <italic>Megatherium</italic> digested with trypsin. *Note the clearly observable difference in deamidation as a marker for protein ageing due to the presence of a glutamine residue in this peptide.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139611.g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0139611.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Number of amino acid variations detected through LC-based methods compared with number of most intense 100 peaks shared in MALDI fingerprints (numbers in brackets indicate observations confirmed in both fossil replicates for each species).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0139611.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0139611.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxa</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Choloepus (MALDI)</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Bradypus(MALDI)</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Lestodon (MALDI)</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Megatherium (MALDI)</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Choloepus</italic> (ESI)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Bradypus</italic> (ESI)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Lestodon</italic> (ESI)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Megatherium</italic> (ESI)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0139611.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Proteomics information relating to the quality of the Mascot search results, including the False Decoy Rate (FDR), highest scoring false positive peptide (HFPS), the total protein score for sloth collagen, the number of peptide matches used for this score, the number of unique sequences and the percentage coverage.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0139611.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0139611.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FDR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFPS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matches</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequences</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Cov.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Choloepus</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20144</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Bradypus</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">669</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lestodon (474)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31482</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1198</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lestodon (975a)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18467</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">462</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Megatherium (PdlT)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penas de las Trampas 1.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12368</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Megatherium (LC)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Las Chacras, Rio Negro</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52195</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1853</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Although there is currently no available COL1A1 sequence for any extant sloth, there is a partial COL1A2 two-toed sloth (<italic>Choloepus hoffmanni</italic>) sequence. When the sequence dataset is cropped to the COL1A2 sequence only and the LC-MS/MS analysis of the three-toed sloth (<italic>Bradypus variegates</italic>) added, the <italic>Bradypus</italic> is consistently placed sister to <italic>Choloepus</italic>, with <italic>Lestodon</italic> and then <italic>Megatherium</italic> forming a grade, and the remainder of the tree still consistent with expected phylogeny for all extant taxa with strong order-level support in most cases, but weak support at the super-order level. In terms of the stability of the xenarthran group on the whole, in the Maximum Likelihood analyses Xenarthra is consistently placed as sister to Boreoeutheria (Laurasiatheria + Euarchontoglires) with Afrotheria as the basal group (<xref rid="pone.0139611.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) even when all other xenarthran sequence information from extant taxa (<italic>Dasypus</italic> and <italic>Choloepus</italic>) are not used (<xref rid="pone.0139611.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0139611.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Maximum Likelihood analysis of the concatenated COL1A1 and COL1A2 sequences of eutherian mammals including the proposed consensus sequences of the two extinct ground sloths <italic>Lestodon</italic> and <italic>Megatherium</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139611.g002"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Both the comparison of the MALDI fingerprints and, to a lesser extent, the proteomics-based sequencing indicate that the type 1 collagen is noticeably more different between with the Folivora (sloth) suborder than initially anticipated given their estimated divergence times. By comparison to the Proboscidea, within which we only typically see one or two differences between families (Elephantidae&#x02014;Mammutidae; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]) that diverged ~20 Ma, the xenarthran mylodontids and megalonychids are known as well-established groups in South America since Deseadan times (late Oligocene, 28&#x02013;24 Ma; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; and megatherioids since the Santacruzian (early&#x02014;middle Miocene, 19&#x02013;16 Ma; [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]). With regards to the two extinct sloths in this study, although we observed numerous points of likely amino acid variation through analysis of the collagen-dominant MALDI fingerprints, we only confirmed the variation of fifteen of these through LC-based sequencing, which reduced to only five substitutions using results from duplicate specimens. Although one amino acid substitution could be responsible for multiple observed peak differences in MALDI, due to the presence of both missed cleavages as well as post-translational modifications, this is indicative of the bias against discovering sequence variation in more distantly related taxa. This is particularly clear in the example of the inability to confirm all of the sequences of peptides described previously as peptide biomarkers (e.g., marker F in [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]) in <italic>Megatherium</italic>, and subsequent identification of the homologous peptide in <italic>Lestodon</italic>, identical to that of the extant taxa. This discrepancy of missing peptide sequence information specific to particular regions of the molecular may impact upon phylogenetic inferences from proteomics-derived sequence data to an extent that has not yet been explored.</p><p>Previous studies on the phylogenetic relationships of sloths showed a clear distinction between the two extant families (Megalonychidae and Bradypodidae) well supported by both morphological and molecular differences. In particular, Sarich [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] found considerable evolutionary distance between the albumins of the two genera. Previous aDNA studies on extinct sloths [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] indicated a relationship between, on the one hand, <italic>Mylodon darwinii</italic> (Mylodontidae) and <italic>Choloepus</italic> (Megalonychidae), and, on the other, between <italic>Nothrotheriops shastensis</italic> (Megatheriidae) and <italic>Bradypus</italic> spp. (Bradypodidae). However, this assumption was questioned by more recent studies [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The inclusion of Mylodontidae as the sister taxon of Megalonychidae does not support the monophyly of Megatherioidea (including the megatheriids, nothrotheriids and megalonychids) as in the widely accepted phylogenetic reconstruction proposals by Gaudin [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] based on craniodental morphological traits. Although in that paper the grouping of Mylodontidae and Megalonychidae is not supported, most of the molecular phylogenetic reconstructions show an allied relation of <italic>Mylodon</italic> and <italic>Choloepus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], even with the inclusion of other Megatherioidea as <italic>Nothrotheriops</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, Gaudin [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] states that the hypothesis of a close relation of <italic>Choloepus</italic> with mylodontids cannot be statistically rejected and that the position of <italic>Choloepus</italic> within megalonychids could not unambiguously be resolved. More recently, an aDNA phylogeny by Clack et al. [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] placed <italic>Choloepus</italic> close to <italic>Mylodon</italic>, with <italic>Bradypus</italic> occupying a derived position among megalonychids and <italic>Nothrotheriops</italic> occupying a basal position as the sister group of all the mentioned sloths. Our study shows a relationship between the extant and extinct sloths not previously proposed by molecular or morphological phylogenies, since both extant sloths appear as sister taxa with <italic>Lestodon</italic> (Mylodontidae) and <italic>Megatherium</italic> (Megatheriidae) forming a successive grade. As noted before, a basal position of Megatheriidae (<italic>Nothrotheriops</italic>) is reported by Clack et al. [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] but the Mylodontidae groups with <italic>Choloepus</italic>, as most aDNA phylogenies. The discrepancies between the collagen, aDNA and morphological phylogenies could be due to the incompleteness of the collagen data, as alluded to earlier. One of the limitations of proteomics-based approaches to phylogenetic reconstruction that needs to be addressed is deciding on an appropriate level of confidence&#x02014;in this case we have chosen to rely on a peptide score equivalent to the highest false positive match in order to accommodate for differences in the quality of each analysis; this approach is likely to unnecessarily reduce sequence coverage, but comparison of the phylogenies recovered here (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0139611.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A and 3B</xref>) imply that the variation in percentage sequence coverage alone in this study is not an issue. Also, the fact that the MALDI fingerprints also show greater similarity between the two extant taxa implies that perhaps it is more likely related to the more limited source information of the collagen-based approach in relation to the other methods. In regard to the phylogenetic relationships of the fossil sloths, belonging to Mylodontidae and Megatheriidae, it should be noted that the absence of northotheriids in our analysis leaves uncertain the possible placement of this taxon, which has been closely associated to Megatheriidae in most morphological studies [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139611.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0139611.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139611.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic analyses of COL1A2 sequences of eutherian mammals including the extinct South American native ungulates and two extinct ground sloths <italic>Lestodon</italic> and <italic>Megatherium</italic> in comparison to extant sloths <italic>Bradypus</italic> and <italic>Choloepus</italic> showing (A) Maximum Likelihood analysis of consensus peptide matches observed in the PMF, (B) Maximum Likelihood of peptide matches observed in the PMF from either specimen, (C) Maximum Likelihood of the alpha 2 (I) sequences only, using the Ensembl <italic>Choloepus</italic> sequence and (D) Bayes analysis of consensus peptide matches observed in the PMF.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139611.g003"/></fig><p>In conclusion, given that the resulting topologies of these extinct xenarthran taxa remain consistent, with or without the inclusion of any other xenarthran sequence, the analysis of collagen using proteomics techniques clearly has potential to resolve many currently ambiguous relationships in palaeontology that are currently dominated by morphological analyses. Although collagen sequence phylogenies will not yield as great a phylogenetic resolution as DNA-based analyses, they have the potential to produce results that are to some extent congruent and that can be applied to vertebrates that went extinct much earlier (e.g., millions of years in ideal conditions) than can be currently achieved with the DNA-based methods. However, the minor disagreement with aDNA and morphological methods at the higher taxonomic level could imply that a wider range of proteins [<xref rid="pone.0139611.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] should be investigated to further improve the potential of proteomics applications to palaeontology and the evolution of vertebrate life.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec005"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0139611.s001"><label>S1 File</label><caption><p>Excel files of peptide matches for each sample: modern <italic>Bradypus</italic> (Sheet A), modern <italic>Choloepus</italic> (Sheet B), extinct <italic>Lestodon</italic> from Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no #474 (Sheet C), extinct <italic>Lestodon</italic> from Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no #474 (Sheet D), extinct <italic>Megatherium</italic> Penas de las Trampas (Sheet E), and extinct <italic>Megatherium</italic> from Las Chacras (Sheet F). Raw data can be accessed on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753">http://www.peptideatlas.org/PASS/PASS00753</ext-link>.</p><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0139611.s001.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0139611.s002"><label>S2 File</label><caption><title>Concatenated COL1A1 and COL1A2 sequences, and additional COL1A2 sloth sequences.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0139611.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0139611.s003"><label>S3 File</label><caption><p>Supplementary figures (Figures A-P) including additional Maximum Likelihood phylogenetic tree (Figure A) and tandem mass spectra for new unique peptide sequences (Figures B-P).</p><p>(ZIP)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0139611.s003.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We gratefully acknowledge the Royal Society for fellowship funding to MB. This research paper is a contribution to the project "Prospecci&#x000f3;n de nuevos sitios fosil&#x000ed;feros y arqueol&#x000f3;gicos en el &#x000e1;rea del Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no" funded by the Comisi&#x000f3;n Sectorial de Investigaci&#x000f3;nCient&#x000ed;fica, Universidad de la Rep&#x000fa;blica and both Comuna Canaria and Municipio de Sauce partially funded the excavations of RF and his team. We are grateful to funding for recovery of one of the <italic>Megatherium</italic> specimens under the grant CIUNT 26G522 to JP. We also thank the Richard Cooke at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute for modern samples used in this study and The University of Manchester&#x02019;s Faculty of Life Sciences Proteomics Facility for analytical and bioinformatics support.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0139611.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Iuliis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <year>2013</year>
<source>Megafauna: giant beasts of Pleistocene South America</source>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loughry</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Biology of the Xenarthra</source>. <publisher-name>University Press of Florida</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Florida</publisher-loc>, pp <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Phylogeny of the Xenarthra (Mammalia)</article-title>. <source>Senckenbergiana biologica</source>
<volume>83</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catzeflis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The virtues of gaps: Xenarthran (Edentate) monophyly supported by a unique deletion in &#x003b1;A-crystallin</article-title>. <source>Systematic biology</source>
<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12078648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12078648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>). <chapter-title>The phylogeny of the Xenarthra</chapter-title>
<source>The evolution and ecology of armadillos, sloths, and vermilinguas</source>. <publisher-name>Smithsonian Institution Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>, pp <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The great American biotic interchange: patterns and processes</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Missouri Botanical Garden</source>
<volume>93</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Woodburne</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The Great American Biotic Interchange: dispersals, tectonics, climate, sea level and holding pens</article-title>. <source>Journal of Mammalian Evolution</source>
<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 21125025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21125025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lessa</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Reassessment of extinction patterns among the late Pleistocene mammals of South America</article-title>. <source>Palaeontology</source>
<volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>651</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giallombardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The placental mammal ancestor and the post&#x02014;K-Pg radiation of placentals</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>339</volume>(<issue>6120</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1229237</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23393258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23393258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hallstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kullberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Phylogenomic data analyses provide evidence that Xenarthra and Afrotheria are sister groups</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>
<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17630282?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Placental mammal diversification and the Cretaceous&#x02014;Tertiary boundary</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>100</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1056</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Influence of Tertiary paleoenvironmental changes on the diversification of South American mammals: a relaxed molecular clock study within xenarthrans</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15115541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Slow moving or browsers? A note on nomenclature</article-title>. <source>Senckenbergiana Biologica</source>
<volume>83</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Molecular systematics of armadillos (Xenarthra, Dasypodidae): contribution of maximum likelihood and Bayesian analyses of mitochondrial and nuclear genes</article-title>. <source>Molecular phylogenetics and evolution</source>
<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12878463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <chapter-title>Morphology-based investigations of the phylogenetic relationships among extant and fossil xenarthrans</chapter-title> In <source>The Biology of the Xenarthra</source> (<name><surname>Vizca&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Loughry</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, eds.) <publisher-name>University Press of Florida</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Gainesville</publisher-loc> pp <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ctzeflis</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Douzery</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The evolution of armadillos, anteaters and sloths depicted by nuclear and mitochondrial phylogenies: implications for the status of the enigmatic fossil Eurotamandua</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>268</volume>(<issue>1476</issue>):<fpage>1605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11487408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofreiter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spaulding</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stankiewicz</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Molecular coproscopy: Dung and diet of the extinct ground sloth Nothrotheriops shastensis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>281</volume>(<issue>5375</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9665881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9665881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldmaier-Fuchs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paabo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A molecular phylogeny of two extinct sloths</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11161746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11161746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>H&#x000f6;ss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dilling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Currant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>P&#x000e4;&#x000e4;bo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of the extinct ground sloth Mylodon darwinii</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hofreiter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spaulding</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Possnert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>A molecular analysis of ground sloth diet through the last glaciation</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11123610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11123610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Comment on &#x0201c;Protein Sequences from Mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex Revealed by Mass Spectrometry&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>4</volume>(<issue>319</issue>):<fpage>33c</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A Molecular Phylogeny of Plesiorycteropus Reassigns the Extinct Mammalian Order &#x02018;Bibymalagasia&#x02019;</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e59614</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059614</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23555726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23555726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nielsen-Marsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Biomolecules in fossil remains</article-title>. <source>The Biochemist</source>
<fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shoshani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Proboscidean origins of mastodont and woolly mammoth demonstrated immunologically</article-title>. <source>Paleobiology</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarich</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Albumin systematics of the extinct mammoth and Tasmanian wolf</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>1409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Method development of efficient protein extraction in bone tissue for proteome analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Proteome Research</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17488005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wadsworth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Proteome degradation in fossils: investigating the longevity of protein survival in ancient bone</article-title>. <source>Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom</source>
<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.6821</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24519823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24519823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Comment on "protein sequences from mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex revealed by mass spectrometry"</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>319</volume>(<issue>5859</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rybczynski</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gosse</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harington</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wogelius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hidy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Mid-Pliocene warm-period deposits in the High Arctic yield insight into camel evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature communications</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1550</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2516</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23462993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23462993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Proteomics analysis of ancient food vessel stitching reveals &#x0003e; 4000&#x02010;year&#x02010;old milk protein</article-title>. <source>Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom</source>
<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.6481</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23322659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23322659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cappellini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ginolhac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>TW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Proteomic analysis of a pleistocene mammoth femur reveals more than one hundred ancient bone proteins</article-title>. <source>Journal of proteome research</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>917</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr200721u</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22103443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22103443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Ancient collagen reveals evolutionary history of the endemic South American &#x02018;ungulates&#x02019;</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>282</volume> (<issue>1806</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cuvier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1796</year>). <article-title>Notice sur de squelette d'une tr&#x000e8;s grande esp&#x000e8;ce de quadrup&#x000e8;de inconnue jusqu'&#x000e1; pr&#x000e9;sent, trouv&#x000e9; au Paraguay, et d&#x000e9;pos&#x000e9; au Cabinet d&#x000aa;Histoire Naturelle de Madrid</article-title>. <source>Magasin encyclop&#x000e9;dique, ou Journal des Sciences, des lettres et des Arts</source> (<issue>2</issue>)<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <year>1855</year>
<source>Recherches sur les mammif&#x000e9;res fossiles de l'Am&#x000e9;rique m&#x000e9;ridionale</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>P. Bertrand</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tambusso</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Varela</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Czerwonogora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Di Giacomo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Arroyo del Vizca&#x000ed;no, Uruguay: a fossil-rich 30-ka-old megafaunal locality with cut-marked bones</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>281</volume>(<issue>1774</issue>):<fpage>20132211</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aschero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Investigaciones en el sitio Pe&#x000f1;as de las Trampas 1.1: entre megafauna y contextos funerarios (Antofagasta de la Sierra, Catamarca)</article-title>. <source>Serie Monogr Did FCN e IML, UNT</source>. <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Systematic biology</source>
<volume>52</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14530136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calcott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>PartitionFinder: combined selection of partitioning schemes and substitution models for phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1695</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss020</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22319168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11524383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Mammoth and Mastodon collagen sequences; survival and utility</article-title>. <source>Geochim Cosmochim Acta</source>
<volume>75</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2007</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pujos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Iuliis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Late Oligocene Megatherioidea fauna (Mammalia: Xenarthra) from Salla-Luribay (Bolivia): new data on basal sloth radiation and Cingulata-Tardigrada split</article-title>. <source>J Vertebr Paleontol</source>
<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Iuliis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <chapter-title>Fossil history of sloths</chapter-title> In <source>Biology of the Xenarthra</source> (eds. <name><surname>Vica&#x000ed;no</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Loughry</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>). <publisher-name>University Press of Florida</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Florida</publisher-loc>, pp <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas-Oates</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Species identification by analysis of bone collagen using matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionisation time-of-flight mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom</source>
<volume>23</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.4316</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19899187?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19899187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Sarich</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>). <chapter-title>Xenarthran systematics: albumin immunological evidence</chapter-title> In <source>The Evolution and Ecology of Armadillos, Sloths and Vermilingues</source> (ed. <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>). <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Smithsonian Institution</publisher-name>, pp <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldmaier-Fuchs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>P&#x000e4;&#x000e4;bo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A molecular phylogeny of two extinct sloths</article-title>. <source>Molecular phylogenetics and evolution</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11161746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11161746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of 16S mitochondrial DNA data in sloths and anteaters</article-title>. <source>Genetics and molecular biology</source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among sloths (Mammalia, Xenarthra, Tardigrada): the craniodental evidence</article-title>. <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source>. <volume>140</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hofreiter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sbriller</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markgraf</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Phylogeny, diet, and habitat of an extinct ground sloth from Cuchillo Cura, Neuquen Province, southwest Argentina</article-title>. <source>Quaternary Res</source>
<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacPhee</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Case study: ancient sloth DNA recovered from hairs preserved in paleofeces</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<volume>840</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-61779-516-9_7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22237521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pujos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Iuliis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Argot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Werdelin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A peculiar climbing Megalonychidae from the Pleistocene of Peru and its implication for sloth history</article-title>. <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source>
<volume>149</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139611.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wadsworth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Proteome degradation in ancient bone: diagenesis and phylogenetic potential</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology</source>
<volume>416</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>