<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Anthropol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Anthropol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">canm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Anthropology &#x00026; Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1364-8470</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-2910</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13648470.2011.591193</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Introduction. Shrines, substances and medicine in sub-Saharan Africa: archaeological, anthropological, and historical perspectives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Archaeology, School of Arts, Histories, and Cultures, University of Manchester, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>Tim.Insoll@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2011 Taylor &#x00026; Francis</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/mpp/uploads/iopenaccess_tcs.pdf"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.informaworld.com/mpp/uploads/iopenaccess_tcs.pdf">Supplemental Terms and Conditions for iOpenAccess articles published in Taylor &#x00026; Francis journals</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Whereas shrines in Africa, and to a lesser extent their links with medicine and healing, have been extensively studied by historians and anthropologists, they have been largely neglected by archaeologists. Focus has been placed upon palaeopathology when medicine is considered in archaeological contexts. Difficulties certainly exist in defining medicine shrines, substances and practices archaeologically, yet research can take various forms &#x02013; scapegoats and figural representations of disease; divination and diagnosis; trade and spread of medicinal substances, shrines, and amulets; syncretism of different traditions and materiality; the material culture associated with healing and medicinal substance; depictions in rock art; genetic research. A move beyond palaeopathology is required to begin to understand the archaeology of medicine shrines, substances, practices and healing in sub-Saharan Africa.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>shrines</kwd><kwd>medicine</kwd><kwd>substances</kwd><kwd>Africa</kwd><kwd>archaeology</kwd><kwd>divination</kwd><kwd>palaeopathology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Shrines in Africa, and to a lesser extent shrines and their links with medicine, are subjects that have been intensively explored by anthropologists and historians (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">Werbner 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">Schoffeleers 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Allman and Parker 2005</xref>), but less so by archaeologists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Mather 1999</xref>: 214; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Dawson 2009</xref>). Hence, emphasis here will be placed upon considering the link between shrines, medicinal practices, medicinal substances, and health in sub-Saharan Africa from an archaeological perspective.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Medicine &#x02018;shrine&#x02019; definitions and typologies</title><sec id="s3"><title>Shrine</title><p>&#x02018;Shrine&#x02019; is a term that fails to describe the range of structures included within its boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Insoll 2004</xref>, 105). The reason perhaps being because &#x02018;shrine&#x02019; is derived ultimately from the Latin <italic>scrinium &#x02013;</italic> meaning &#x02018;box&#x02019; or &#x02018;receptacle&#x02019;, as in &#x02018;containers of sacred meaning and power&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Courtright 1987</xref>, 299). Within sub-Saharan Africa this can encompass the domed Muslim <italic>qubba</italic> of Ethiopia or the Sudan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Foucher 1994</xref>) to the single pot <italic>yin</italic> (destiny) shrine of the Talensi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Insoll 2008</xref>). Hence &#x02018;shrine&#x02019; has been variously defined in the African context. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">Van Binsbergen (1979</xref>, 47&#x02013;48) defines a shrine as an &#x02018;observable object or part of the natural world, clearly localized and normally immobile&#x02019;, and &#x02018;a material focus of religious activities&#x02019;. Most recently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Dawson (2009</xref>, vii) has referred to shrines as &#x02018;vessels&#x02019;&#x02014;containers for spirits or entities and as symbolic vessels.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Medicine</title><p>&#x02018;Medicine&#x02019; is also a problematic term. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Almquist (1991</xref>, 103) describes how <italic>bebobe</italic>, &#x02018;medicines&#x02019;, was used by the Pagibeti (Congo) as a &#x02018;favourite one-word explanation&#x02019; for &#x02018;the unusual power of a chief, a witch, or a highly successful curer or hunter&#x02019;. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Lewis Wall (1988</xref>, 211) similarly indicates the problem with the word &#x02018;medicine&#x02019; in the Hausa (Nigeria) context. Rather than meaning &#x02018;the science and art concerned with the cure, alleviation, and prevention of disease, and with the restoration and preservation of health&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Little, Fowler, and Coulson 1973</xref>, 1300), the Hausa concept of <italic>magani</italic> &#x02018;includes much more&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Little, Fowler, and Coulson 1973</xref>, 1300) in that it can &#x02018;refer to anything which corrects or prevents an undesirable condition&#x02019;. The problematic nature of &#x02018;medicine&#x02019; as defined in English is also clearly indicated by the fact that medicines can become Gods. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Field (1937</xref>, 113) refers to such a process amongst the G&#x000e3; (Ghana). This was probably common but remains under-researched, and indicates how &#x02018;medicine&#x02019;, especially if enshrined, can become a cosmological axis that transcends a concern with health.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Medicine shrine</title><p>Defining a medicine shrine is equally problematic. Although the level of detail recorded in the studies drawn upon varies significantly, an idea of the diversity of medicine shrines in one area of West Africa, northern Ghana, is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Selected examples of medicine shrines in northern Ghana (compiled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Mather 1999</xref>, 107&#x02013;12; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Apentiik 1997</xref>, 242; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Mendonsa 1982</xref>, 102; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethno-linguistic group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name and purpose</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Form/material elements</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kusasi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Mather 1999</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gebik &#x02013;</italic> diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calabash</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kusasi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Winam tongo fun y or &#x02013;</italic> diagnosing whether a patient is close to death</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wide-mouthed pot filled with a pile of stones</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kusasi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Amar kapar &#x02013;</italic> diagnosing whether a patient is close to death</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wide-mouthed pot containing water and roots and used in association with a cow's tail</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kusasi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tiik/tiis &#x02013;</italic> curing illnesses caused by trees</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wide-mouthed pot containing plant parts soaked in water</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bulsa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Apentiik 1997</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tiim-Bogluta &#x02013;</italic> protection for self and family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) Pot containing water and &#x02018;herbs&#x02019;
<break/>(ii) Horn (unspecified) filled with clay</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S&#x000ed;sala (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Mendonsa 1982</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Daaluno &#x02013;</italic> medicine shrine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structure and appearance differs but generally composed of a container (unspecified) for the medicine (roots, herbs, bark, and other material).</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>This indicates difference, but also similarity, in relation to the recurrence of the container or vessel. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Dawson's (2009</xref>, vii) &#x02018;vessel&#x02019; shrine definition would appear valid. This, however, does not equal typology. Shrines &#x02018;are not immutable&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Dawson 2009</xref>, xi) and medicine shrines seem to be able to mutate and develop into other &#x02018;forms&#x02019; of shrines and entities. As mentioned, they can become Gods, but also ancestor, or earth shrines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Lentz 2009</xref>, 140), or be derived from these. They can cross the boundaries of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Colson's (1997)</xref> human-constructed &#x02018;shrines of the land&#x02019; and natural &#x02018;places of power&#x02019;. A typological approach to medicine shrines would appear largely ineffectual, certainly archaeologically, where what might be constructed above ground will likely be rendered unrecognizable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Insoll 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Mather (2009</xref>, 115) has explored aspects of the ethnoarchaeology of shrine taphonomy in northern Ghana and is more optimistic about their recognition in the archaeological record, but his theoretical emphasis placed on residue analysis and &#x02018;morphological, histological, and chemical criteria&#x02019; awaits practical validation when archaeological and analytical reality is less forgiving (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>; van Dongen, Fraser, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>).</p><p>Evidential constraints might mean that typology is inappropriate in most archaeological contexts, but a narrative that recognises a historical trajectory in relation to medicine shrines is vital. They, as has been recently noted for sacred groves, are historical constructs and not &#x02018;icons of static tradition&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">Sheridan 2008</xref>, 23).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Shrine medicine substance, efficacy, and disease representation and transference</title><sec id="s7"><title>Substance, efficacy, &#x02018;scapegoats&#x02019;</title><p>Discussion centred on exploring their substances &#x02013; what gives medicine shrines their efficacy &#x02013; is potentially a topic for research. This, however, should transcend a sole concern with pharmaceutical components and active agents, although these obviously play a role (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>). Instead, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">James (2009</xref>, 41) has noted in relation to Hausa medicinal substances, medicinal power &#x02018;is partly drawn from their interconnections to a wider framework of metaphorical associations and not simply inherent biomedical qualities of the constituent ingredients&#x02019;. This also applies to illness, for as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Devisch (1993</xref>, 31) remarks, &#x02018;the interpretation of illness can only be understood within the wider context of the forces at work in the social context and life-world&#x02019;. From an archaeological perspective, the emphasis upon overall context in understanding medicine shrines and substances becomes paramount, for example, in how they might relate to concepts of taboo and prohibition. Amongst the &#x02018;LoDagaba&#x02019; and &#x02018;Birifor&#x02019; (Dagara, Ghana), for instance, the benefits from &#x02018;eating&#x02019; a medicine connected with a shrine could only be derived by observing certain prohibitions, otherwise unspecified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Goody (1967</xref>, 76; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">Saako 2009</xref>, 74&#x02013;75). Breaking a taboo might also be believed to cause disease for the infractor, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Meek (1931</xref>, 310) relates for the Jukun (Nigeria). Hence, to isolate &#x02018;medicine&#x02019; from its overall context would be to separate it from other material domains of potential archaeological relevance, such as the residues of sacrifice, diet, and taboo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Insoll 2010</xref>).</p><p>The concept of the scapegoat also links in with taboo and medicine and provides a material case study. The scapegoat can take several forms, one of which is the sacrifice of an animal and it being cast out into the bush as an agent of disease transference. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Ngubane (1977</xref>, 11) describes how Zulu (South Africa) healers threw the clay medicine pot and medicine remnants onto the carcass of a black sheep killed by suffocation. This was then covered with thorny branches and stones. Another form of scapegoat is provided by the figural representation of an afflicted individual in the hope that the disease or condition represented would be attracted to the figurine as part of the processes of healing and disease prevention (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Kankpeyeng, Nkumbaan, and Insoll 2011</xref>). This has been recorded in many instances ethnographically. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Fagg (1990</xref>, 32), for example, describes the recent use of<italic> Kwandala</italic> pot figures amongst the Longuda of Nigeria. The pot figures served almost as shrines in the way that they were ritually treated in having beer poured on them and meat offered to them because, &#x02018;the spirit of the disease, placated by sacrifice, is believed to leave the body of the invalid, and enter its clay representation&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Fagg 1990</xref>, 32).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Nok</title><p>Disease transference and aversion agents can also take plainer forms. Related, but not directly analogous are the Giriama (Kenya) <italic>vifudu.</italic> These are ordinary cooking pots that are believed to be representations of deceased female ancestors and that, if properly handled, will help avert disease and ill health. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99">Udvardy's (1990</xref>, 140) warning on the improbability of their archaeological interpretation without an understanding of their spatial symbolism is, however, entirely appropriate. Figurative images offer greater interpretive potential. In addition to the Koma Land figurines discussed in this issue (see Kankpeyeng, Nkumbaan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>), disease and disfigurement has been noted in the Nok figurine corpus from Central Nigeria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Fagg 1990</xref>). These have been radiocarbon and thermoluminescence dated to between 500 BC and AD 200 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Rupp, Ameje, and Breunig 2005</xref>), and can indicate precisely identifiable conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Conditions and diseases represented by Nok and Ife figurines (compiled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Fagg 1990</xref>, 31&#x02013;2, 108&#x02013;9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">Willett 1967</xref>, 61&#x02013;3, 208; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake 1974</xref>, 126, 130).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identification code</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Context</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition(s) and diseases(s) represented</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMG Nok</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mining, Nok (no context)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bell's Palsy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jos N 287.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mining, Nok (no context)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prolapsed haemorrhoids</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jos 58.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mining, Big Paddock, Nok (no context)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elephantiasis of the scrotum</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Nok) None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possible tuberculosis of the spine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osongongon Obamakin Grove, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elephantiasis of the scrotum</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osongongon Obamakin Grove, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possible anacephaly</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osongongon Obamakin Grove, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right hand and foot with elephantiasis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain provenance, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rickets</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None given</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain provenance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face with nose eaten away by gangosa or similar</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obalara's Land, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unidentified &#x02013; fluid from nostrils, swollen upper lip, swelling of right side of neck, bags under eyes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obalara's Land, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right hand deformed by elephantiasis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obalara's Land, Ife</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possible anacephaly</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> indicates that what is lacking in relation to most examples of Nok terracotta figurines is a precise understanding of context, although this is beginning to be redressed (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Rupp, Ameje and Breunig 2005</xref>). Hence, it is not possible to say if they were linked with shrines, including medicinal ones.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Tago</title><p>It is easier to explore context in relation to other figurines found in West Africa. At the Sao site of Tago, c. 30 km north of Ndjamena in Chad, figurines were found in context, and this suggests, by analogy with elsewhere, a medicinal or healing association as a potential, at least partial, interpretation. Level 2 at this site had three figurines with human torsos, arms, and heads represented, oriented to the east with one placed upon part of a funerary jar accompanied by four balls of fired clay put at the cardinal points. Arranged in three semi-circles behind and to the side of these figurines were further groups of hundreds of figurine fragments; people, animals, masked dancers, as well as stone pounders, pieces of ochre, and faunal remains interpreted as the residue from offerings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Lebeuf and Masson Detourbet 1950</xref>, 68&#x02013;70). This has been referred to as the &#x02018;central shrine&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">Phillips 1995</xref>, 533). The date of Tago is unclear, but the highpoint of the Sao seems to have been between the tenth to sixteenth centuries AD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Lebeuf, Treinen-Claustre, and Courtin 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Insoll 2003</xref>, 278).</p><p>A shrine interpretation for Tago would appear valid and, based on contextual similarities with the deposition patterns at the Koma Land sites (see Kankpeyeng, Nkumbaan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>), suggests a curative, healing, or medicinal element might also have underlain the deposition of the figurines and other materials and their arrangement. Such an interpretation need not replace <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Lebeuf and Masson Detourbet's (1950</xref>, 128&#x02013;129) suggestion that an ancestor cult, a form of totemism, and beliefs in various spirits underpinned Sao religion and ritual, and hence shrines, but merely accompany these as a further interpretive option. Various interpretive possibilities exist in relation to a medicinal/healing function for the figurines and their context, as a whole &#x02013; as a medicine shrine &#x02013; or in part &#x02013; through serving to protect from disease, functioning as scapegoats, or representing the disposal of the residue of healing processes. The former, as a medicine shrine, gaining interpretive value when the excavators&#x02019; suggestion that Tago, through the diverse figurine styles represented, perhaps signifies, &#x02018;que le lieu recevait la visite de p&#x000e8;lerins &#x000e9;trangers qui y pla&#x000e7;aient des masques model&#x000e9;s suivant le canon particulier de leur cite&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Lebeuf and Masson Detourbet 1950</xref>, 129). Whether the figurines were linked with birth as they also suggest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Lebeuf and Masson Detourbet 1950</xref>, 129) is unclear, but Tago was undoubtedly perceived of as a powerful place, efficacious in the purpose it served.</p><p>Figurines representing diseased individuals can be used for various purposes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Cory (1956</xref>, 132, 135&#x02013;136) illustrates two clay figurines used during boyhood initiation by the Pare (Tanzania). One is of an individual with a swelling on his neck representing <italic>Kinundu</italic>, &#x02018;the cripple&#x02019;, and was used to illustrate that it is unwise to mock someone because of physical defects. The other also shows someone with a swelling on the neck and represents a hypochondriac who took a different medicine every day, leading to his affliction, and was linked to the instruction that, &#x02018;illness can be caused by taking too much medicine&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Cory 1956</xref>, 137).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Ife</title><p>At Ife in Nigeria, diseased individuals are, as at Nok, also represented in the terracotta figurines produced in the so-called Classic period of the twelfth to fourteenth centuries AD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">Willett 1967</xref>). Unlike at Nok, the context of the figurines at Ife is more informative, even if precise meanings cannot be reconstructed. Particularly significant is the Classic period site of Obalara's Land where the excavator suggests that it seems that people who had died of disease were interred with their heads disposed of separately as a preventive measure so the disease did nor recur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake 1974</xref>, 146). Material suggestive of this included sorted piles of human remains, such as a compact group of both fragmentary and complete human skulls whose condition seemed to indicate they were collected together post-mortem or after decapitation. This comprised eight complete crania (minus mandibles), 14 complete calvaria, 12 almost complete calvaria and fragments of a further five calvaria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Insoll 2004</xref>:. 108). Against the uppermost skull rested a terracotta head depicting &#x02018;an expression of malevolence or horror&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake 1974</xref>, 122). Placed close by was another terracotta head of a diseased individual, along with two fragments of human long bones and further terracotta and pottery fragments. Similar evidence for &#x02018;bodily partition&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Ogundiran 2002</xref>, 115) was discovered at the central Yorubaland site of &#x000cc;loy&#x000ed; (Nigeria) where the burial of human remains, including a skull, thoracic vertebrae and parts of the humerus, ulna and radius, were recorded in contexts radiocarbon dated to between the thirteenth to fifteenth centuries AD. The excavator suggests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Ogundiran 2002</xref>, 39) that one of the interpretations that can be proposed is, as at Obalara's Land, post-mortem decapitation of people who died of disease.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake (1974</xref>, 143) suggests the material from Obalara's Land indicates it was a shrine. Again this is a realistic interpretation, and, based on the material present and its contextual arrangement, it can be further suggested that this potentially had a medicinal function as one of its purposes &#x02013; possibly here in relation to disease transference and containment. Such a medicine-shrine related interpretation might be given additional support by the repeat representations of scarification on many of the figurines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Some of these could be signifiers of identity and cosmetic beauty as known ethnographically (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Harley 1970</xref>, 125&#x02013;126; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Drewal 1988</xref>), others might denote medicinal practices (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>; Kankpeyeng, Nkumbaan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>), also recorded ethnographically as a way of introducing medicinal substances below the skin (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Drewal 1997</xref>, 247; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Drewal and Mason 1997</xref>, 336; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">Samuelsen 2001</xref>, 164). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato (1977</xref>, 177) describes this in a Bambara context as a cicatrization process whereby mineral or herbal products are rubbed into the scarified area creating a &#x02018;foreign-body&#x02019; reaction and the formation of heavy scar tissue or keloids.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Examples of scarification represented in the Obalara's Land figurines (compiled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake 1974</xref>, 132&#x02013;4).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identification Code</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Figurine Type/Part</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scarification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups of three small keloid scars on right temple and above both eyes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertical striations to the face</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Torso</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertical striations on abdomen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 21/22/38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower torso, legs and feet</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertical striations on abdomen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLT 43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentric arcs of scarification from top centre of forehead. Alternate stripes are cross-hatched and vertical scars on chin and nose</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Recurrent in these examples is the link to what can be interpreted as a shrine by way of context and association, with the shrine, if such an interpretation is valid, functioning as the agent of efficacy in association with the figurines.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Diagnosis, association, and cosmological substance</title><p>Divination can, but need not, function in relation to shrines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Peek 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Insoll 2010</xref>), and, potentially, divination offers a material insight into wider metaphorical associations and beliefs related to medicinal substance and shrines, as well as to objects that symbolically or metaphorically function to indicate disease, its causes, and generic illness. Divination is often the primary or a primary mechanism of diagnosis in many parts of sub-Saharan Africa (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Janzen 1992</xref>, 42; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton 1973</xref>, 42; Lienhardt 1961, 148), but the material dimension of divination as it relates to medicine, diagnosis and healing has been less well explored, certainly with regard to the potential archaeological implications. Although somewhat simplistic to reduce systems as complex as divination to their material dimension, it is instructive to do so from an archaeological perspective, and the objects in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref> relate to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Peek (1991</xref>, 12) describes as causal divination systems involving the &#x02018;chance cast of objects&#x02019; as opposed to, for example, those involving oracles (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Evans-Pritchard 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98">Tonkin 2004</xref>) or possession (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton 1973</xref>, 78&#x02013;86). Unfortunately, in many studies, detail on what the code objects actually are is either partial or wholly lacking, although conversely effort will be expended in discussing their interpretation (see for example <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">Pemberton 2000</xref>), thus limiting the number of examples that can be drawn upon.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Selected examples of primarily West African causal divination systems involving medicine related purposes, their relevant associated objects, and their potential archaeological visibility.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethno-linguistic group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purpose</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant material element(s)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archaeological visibility</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Batammaliba (Togo) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Blier 1991</xref>, 83&#x02013;5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical Divination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) Wooden consultation club
<break/>(ii) Flat stone
<break/>(iii) Two cowries</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sisala (Ghana) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Mendonsa 1982</xref>, 115, 124)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosing and treating illness and other forms of affliction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) Pieces of calabash
<break/>(ii) Dried fruit of the <italic>nanpapamun</italic> and <italic>bubina</italic> trees
<break/>(iii) Bundle of twine
<break/>(iv) A Y-shaped stick
<break/>(v) One cowrie shell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Talensi (Ghana)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All forms of problem solving including diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flat seed of the <italic>kpenkpalik</italic> tree (only object of 35 code objects explicitly linked with &#x02018;sickness&#x02019;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None (but other code objects would be archaeologically visible)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jukun (Nigeria) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Meek 1931</xref>, 311, 325&#x02013;8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All forms of problem solving including diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two strings to which are attached four pieces of calabash to each. Between the pieces of calabash are 16 pieces of bone from the <italic>dan sarki</italic> fish (Hausa, species unknown)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None (but fish bones would survive)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bambara (Mali) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato 1977</xref>, 57)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) <italic>Belee &#x02013;</italic> small stones
<break/>(ii) <italic>Golongise &#x02013;</italic> cowrie shells
<break/>(iii) <italic>N'kenyede &#x02013;</italic> reading of marks made in sand</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None (though cowries and stones would obviously survive, their linkage with divination is highly unlikely)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senufo <italic>Sando</italic> (C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Glaze 1981</xref>, 64&#x02013;6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All forms of problem solving including diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) Forged iron miniatures of cultivator's and blacksmith tools
<break/>(ii) Iron, wood, basketry &#x00026; brass miniatures of sacred objects &#x00026; divination equipment
<break/>(iii) Abstract symbols in metal, wood and fibre
<break/>(iv) Natural objects such as seeds and shells</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some &#x02013; objects and miniatures in durable materials would survive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tswana (Botswana) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">Staug&#x000e1;rd 1985</xref>, 74&#x02013;81)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical divination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(i) <italic>Kgokong &#x02013;</italic> wildebeest-tail broom
<break/>(ii) <italic>Ditaola &#x02013;</italic> casting the bones or holy bones &#x02013; small carved pieces of antelope-horn or ivory, snail shells, pieces of plastic or glass, jackal's teeth, goat's vertebrae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some &#x02013; dependent on preservation conditions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barotse (Zambia) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Reynolds 1963</xref>, 98&#x02013;102)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All forms of problem solving including diagnosing illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ngombo yakusekula</italic> (basket divination)
<break/>(i) small wooden figurines
<break/>(ii) case of the <italic>psychidae</italic> moth
<break/>(iii) miniature axe, hoe, stool, canoe, and drum
<break/>(iv) plaited palm leaf strip
<break/>(v) cowry shells on a leather disc
<break/>(vi) interlocking wooden rings</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some &#x02013; objects and miniatures in durable materials would survive</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>It is evident from <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref> that, in general, it will be virtually impossible to identify divination archaeologically. The ephemeral nature of the code objects which are often made of organic materials, as well as the transitory nature of the contexts and actions used in the divination process, will usually render them irretrievable. In some instances, however, divination apparatus might be evident archaeologically, context and ethnographic analogy permitting. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake (1974</xref>, 143), for example, suggests that two of the artefact concentrations at Obalara's Land could have been marked by iron staffs placed upright in their midst. Iron staffs described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Garlake 1974</xref>, 143) as reminiscent of the Yoruba diviners&#x02019; <italic>Opa orere</italic> or <italic>osun</italic> staff. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Nutor (2010</xref>, 87&#x02013;88) also refers to a sandstone boulder carved with nine hollows on its surface and found during excavation at the nineteenth century Dente Ga Shrine site at Dzake-Peki, Volta Region, Ghana. This he suggests could be an <italic>oware</italic> game board, or because of the shrine context, linked with divination. Regardless of archaeological visibility, an awareness of the frequent centrality of divination in relation to medicine and medicine shrines is vital. For divination is often, and probably was equally so in the past, &#x02018;the primary institutional means of articulating the epistemology of a people&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Peek 1991</xref>, 2), and within which medicines and medicine shrines obviously function.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Agency of medicine shrine and substance dispersal</title><sec id="s13"><title>Spread and fission</title><p>Medicine shrines and their substances can also be spread extensively and this potentially holds archaeological implications. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Almquist (1991</xref>, 103), for example, describes how Pagibeti travellers sought out medicines from neighbouring villages and ethnic groups, whilst Boyd Christensen (1959, 277) refers to the process by which the Fanti (Ghana) <italic>Tigari</italic> became the name for exotic cults set up by individuals bringing &#x02018;medicine&#x02019; or a deity from another locality, and often northern Ghana. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Field (1937</xref>, 124) also refers to G&#x000e3; healers invariably obtaining their medicine from outside G&#x000e3; or neighbouring Twi or Fanti country. Instead, medicine was obtained from Togo or northern Ghana. More famously, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton (1973</xref>, 64) discusses how the importation and infiltration of<italic> jok</italic> or powers that was central to Mandari systems of health, medicine, and wellbeing occurred in the 1920s as a correlate of cultural influences from the neighbouring Aliab Dinka and Atwot peoples in the Sudan. It is evident that shrine types, illness, and medicine were clearly integrated in the Mandari <italic>jok</italic> structure. A summary of Buxton's patchy data (1973, 74&#x02013;76, 419, 420&#x02013;422) is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref> and illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, but it is impossible to link them to specific <italic>jok;</italic> even though <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton (1973</xref>, 74) states that &#x02018;the distinctive pole shrines make it possible to tell, immediately, which Power is involved&#x02019;, her data does not permit such an identification.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Mandari &#x02018;Shrines for Powers&#x02019; (not to scale; after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton 1973</xref>, 419; U = unspecified). Top (L&#x02013;R): (1) Unshaped branch pole. (2) Horns of sacrificial ox placed over wooden horns. (3) Pole with bands of bark and metal ring attached. (4) Shaped pole lacking horns. Bottom (L&#x02013;R): (1) Pot and cattle-peg shrine. (2) and (3) Poles imitating oxen display horns. (4) Shrine with &#x02018;offerings&#x02019;. Horned poles are described as 5 to ten feet height (1.5&#x02013;3 m) and plain poles as 3 to 5 feet (90 cm-1.5 m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="canm18_145_f1"/></fig><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Imported Mandari &#x02018;powers&#x02019;, shrines, and associated medicines (compiled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Buxton 1973</xref>, 74&#x02013;6, 419, 420&#x02013;2).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Jok</italic> (power)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Illness</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicine</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shrine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mutianagok</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe pains in head, chest or back, possible delirium and high temperature</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root medicine (1) Unidentified tuberous root (2) <italic>Cistus populnea?</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pole shrine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mayom/Myom</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swelling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pounded medicine (unspecified)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pole shrine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ukor</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhoea, passing blood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used but unspecified. Perhaps <italic>Ziziphusl</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pot and cattle-peg shrine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Adwegdwor</italic> and <italic>Agok</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe headache, diarrhoea, vomiting, high temperature</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used but unspecified</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pole shrine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Weltoc</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wasting disease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small pole shrine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Abyel</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain in the side near heart</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mayar</italic> and <italic>Wonkoro</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest illnesses, possibly pulmonary tuberculosis and pneumonia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified &#x02013; perhaps Gloriosa simplex?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Notwithstanding the data provided, the archaeological recognition of the Mandari <italic>jok</italic> structure and its component linkages of shrine-illness-medicine would be unlikely. The largely organic nature of the shrines and medicines &#x02013; even allowing for theoretically ideal conditions of contextual association &#x02013; precludes survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Moreover, the linkage to specific illnesses as a correlate of symbolic and cognitive systems will be completely lost without direct ethnographic information.</p><p>Looking at processes comparatively, no single process of medicine shrine and substance dispersal seems to have existed even in ethnically or environmentally similar regions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Mendonsa (1982</xref>, 101) records how amongst the Sisala of northern Ghana the <italic>daaluno</italic> or &#x02018;medicine shrine&#x02019; could be &#x02018;split&#x02019; if someone wanted to share in its power. This could occur within the same ethno-linguistic group or across ethno-linguistic lines. In this way it is similar to Talensi processes of &#x02018;shrine franchising&#x02019;, also in northern Ghana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Insoll 2006</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>), but the processes behind the spread of Sisala medicine shrines appear also to differ, as less emphasis was placed on substance transfer and more on knowledge of rites and medicines.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Exotic Materia Medica</title><p>A potentially similar correlate, however, of these processes is variation in pharmacopeia as they need not reflect the surrounding environment botanically, geologically, or even in terms of animal species that might also be utilised for medicinal purposes. Exotic <italic>materia medica</italic> could result that perhaps encapsulates what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">Rekdal (1999</xref>, 473) refers to as &#x02018;the healing power of the culturally distant&#x02019;. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato (1977</xref>, 103) mentions how Sahelian and Saharan Qur'anic healers were disadvantaged &#x02018;from the lack of abundant flora in the environments where they live&#x02019;. Hence medicinal plants were imported from latitudes further south. This does hold potential archaeobotanical implications for recognition of medicinal plants, either imported or locally obtained. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Mercader (2003</xref>, 109) suggests that some of the phytoliths represented in the sequences of the rock shelters he excavated in the Ituri region of northeastern Congo represented in situ deposition by human activity, including bringing in &#x02018;medicinal and ritual plants&#x02019;, and it seems in contexts dated as early as 10,530&#x000b1;50 BP at the site of Matangai Turu Northwest.</p><p>Rarity of ingredients can also be a factor in the perceived efficacy of medicine, as evident among the Igala-speaking peoples of the middle belt of Nigeria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Boston 1971</xref>, 202). The trade in medicinal substances and components &#x02013; animal, vegetable, and mineral &#x02013; can be on a vast scale as evident in the <italic>kemwin-kemwin</italic>, &#x02018;anything and everything&#x02019; apothecaries shops in Benin City, Nigeria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">Nevadomsky 1988</xref>, 73). Similarly, a survey of the largest market in animal remains for medicinal and magical purposes in West Africa, the so-called &#x02018;fetish market&#x02019; at Lom&#x000e9; in Togo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">Taylor and Fox 1992</xref>), recorded 15 bird species, 30 mammal species and six reptile species for sale as well as molluscs, amphibians, and echinoderms. The mammals represented included species from outside Togo such as the chimpanzee <italic>(pongidae)</italic>, Baboon <italic>(cercopithecidae)</italic>, lion <italic>(felidae)</italic>, and aardvark <italic>(orycteropodiddae)</italic>, and Taylor and Fox estimated that the total number of animals represented were 420 reptiles, 4080 mammals, 4360 birds, 1540 snails, 244 fish, and 1570 amphibians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">Taylor and Fox 1992</xref>, 120) attesting to the level of this trade. An insight into the potential meaning of animal remains used for medicine and protective purposes is provided by the Tiv (Nigeria) <italic>kuraiyol</italic>, &#x02018;body protectors&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>The imitative meaning of animal remains included in Tiv <italic>kuraiyol</italic> (compiled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bergsma 1973</xref>, 149&#x02013;51).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Part</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meaning</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gafa</italic> (eagle) <italic>Ishuwa</italic> (weaverbird)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified Feathers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can fly like an eagle and avoid danger The weaverbird builds a nest high up and has to enter it upside down. The wearer would escape danger if thrown head over heels from a vehicle or canoe</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hiar</italic> (unspecified bird)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feathers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This is a bird that flies high, near God. Wearing it will frighten away witches</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ive</italic> (monitor lizard)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">An elusive lizard. The wearer can hide from or confuse an enemy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iyar</italic> (Buffalo)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hair from front of head</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunity from the danger of a charging buffalo</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gwe</italic> (unspecified lizard)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A slippery lizard and thus the wearer can slip away from evil or danger</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dried penis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Power to have repeated intercourse without impotency</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ambe</italic> (crocodiles); <italic>Begha</italic> (lions); <italic>Anyam</italic> (leopards)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Claws, hair, or skin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protect from attack by these animals</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Syncretism, movement, storage</title><p>The transference of medicinal substances into world religious contexts also needs recognising. The boundaries between so-called world and indigenous religions can obviously be blurred (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Bowie 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Insoll 2003</xref>), but conversion to world religion can lead to the continuation, syncretism, or adaptation and abandonment of medicinal practices, beliefs, and associated substances. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato (1977)</xref> describes these processes amongst the Bambara (Mali). Old cults, shrines, and beliefs could be abandoned but belief in the power of Qur'anic amulets <italic>(higab)</italic> for healing and protective purposes could increase with Qur'anic verses and other formulae written on paper by a marabout, encased in leather and worn on the body, or written on a wooden board, washed off and drunk. Repeatedly, the protective and/or medicinal power of the Arabic script has been commented on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Insoll 1996</xref>, 90&#x02013;91), as by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">Mungo Park (1807</xref>, 57) who in his journey along the River Niger in the early nineteenth century observed that, &#x02018;all the natives of this part of Africa consider the art of writing as bordering on magic&#x02019;.</p><p>Protective charms and amulets bearing Arabic script have been encountered archaeologically in sub-Saharan Africa. At Gao (Mali) a <italic>kankarey</italic> pot with an ink-drawn Arabic inscription running around it was recovered from an undated context during building work at a depth of 3 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Insoll 1996</xref>, 30). The copper case for a <italic>higab</italic>, itself apparently represented by a fibrous deposit inside the case, was also found in Gao and dated to the early fifteenth to late sixteenth centuries AD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Insoll 2000</xref>, 134&#x02013;35).</p><p>As an alternative to outright abandonment of older practices, substances, shrines, and associated material culture, Islamic-derived elements such as geomantic signs written on cloth or engraved on pieces of calabash could be integrated into non-Muslim power objects such as the Tiv <italic>kuraiyol</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bergsma 1973</xref>, 149), or Bambara <italic>boliw</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Colleyn 2009</xref>, 43). Both objects that were assembled from a range of materials &#x02013; mineral, animal, botanical, human; and elements &#x02013; textual, liquid, fats, powder, and solid. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Bravmann (1974</xref>, 88&#x02013;93) also describes the impact of Muslim charms amongst non-Muslim populations in west central Ghana and the adjacent Cercle de Bondoukou in the Ivory Coast, which included the embedding of Islamic talismans in mud shrine altars as at Agyekuah and Jakari (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Bravmann 1974</xref>, 93), i.e. practical syncretism of efficacious materials and proven formulae.</p><p>Medicinal substances can also be spread via, and literally on, the person through the agency of amulets and charms (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Reynolds 1963</xref>, 91; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bergsma 1973</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Arkell (1926</xref>, 91) refers to meeting an <italic>eruki</italic> or &#x02018;root-man&#x02019; in Dar Masalit in western Sudan wearing a protective double necklace formed of pieces of sheep rib bones, c.8 cm apart and c.3 cm in length with each containing vegetable powder or pieces of root. In other instances, medicinal substances could be encased in cloth, fibre, wood, or metal packets and containers (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Mendonsa 1982</xref>, 102), as among non-Muslim Bambara where the <italic>tafo</italic> or &#x02018;verbal formulas that are materialized&#x02019; could be made of small pieces of bones or herbs sealed in leather and worn around the affected part of the body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato 1977</xref>, 64). These would rarely survive in archaeological contexts but could be modelled on the types of figurines already considered. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Fagg (1990</xref>, 38), for example, interprets one of the Nok figurines from the site of Jemaa as depicting just above the elbow a smooth object held by four plaited cords, &#x02018;very like the type of charm worn regularly to this day&#x02019;. Koma Land figurines also seem to indicate charms having been worn on the body (see Kankpeyeng, Nukumbaan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The diversity of Barotse medicine containers (not to scale; after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Reynolds 1963</xref>, 71, 73, 75, 78, 82, 84, 87). Top (L&#x02013;R): (1) and (2) Medicine horns (unspecified). (3) Medicine horn with cover. (4) Bottle. (5) Bundle of &#x02018;medicinal roots and sticks&#x02019;. (6, top) Gourd, seemingly with cover. (6, bottom) Clay pot. (7) Basket. Bottom (L-R): (1) Miniature canoe. (2) Tortoise shell. (3) Portion of human skull with beeswax and &#x02018;lucky beans&#x02019; added to it.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="canm18_145_f2"/></fig><p>The material culture associated with medicinal substance can be extremely diverse. Medicine containers, for example, can encompass the whole spectrum of available materials, reflecting the diversity of substances they contain. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Reynolds (1963)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) indicates the variety that can exist in his study of the Barotse (Zambia) where these containers included horns, snail and tortoise shells, skulls, sisal, cloth, and bark-cloth bags, skin wrappers, pots, gourds, and baskets, bottles, tins and enamelwares, and miniature wooden canoes, &#x02018;aeroplanes&#x02019;, and mortars. Unfortunately, accessing this diversity in the archaeological record would be problematic for reasons of preservation. Equally, the recurrent emphasis placed on the form, elemental association, texture, and colour of medicine recorded ethnographically (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Table 7</xref>) would, for similar reasons, be elusive archaeologically.</p><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><p>Selected examples of medicines given importance according to texture and/or colour and/or form and/or elemental/association.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethno-linguistic group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prominent features</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archaeological visibility</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chamba (Cameroon and Nigeria) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Fardon 1990</xref>, 175)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Form.<break/>Male cult medicine <italic>(Cissus quadrangular is)</italic>, female cult medicine <italic>(Amaryllidae)</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shona (Zimbabwe) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Jacobson-Widding 1990</xref>, 67)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elemental association.<break/>Ashes and salt as the end products of fire/heat are used as medicines</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zulu (South Africa) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Berglund 1990</xref>, 270)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colour and elemental association.<break/>Red iron ore/heat and black iron/cool.Forge &#x02018;dross&#x02019; pounded as menstruation medicine and rust pounded as field medicine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Various (lower Congo) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Jacobson-Widding 1979</xref>, 177&#x02013;8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colour.<break/><italic>Nkisi</italic> Nkomina. Chalk (1), red or yellow ochre (2) and <italic>tukula-red</italic> dye if used for healing wounds and sores</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Besides knowledge transfer the movement of substances often of precise provenance can be involved in establishing medicine shrines and in healing practices and treatments. This poses challenges for archaeological recognition through, for example, organic and geochemical analysis. Identifying medicinal substances in the archaeological record has rarely been done (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Arnott 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Baker and Carr 2002</xref>), and never in sub-Saharan Africa. The difficulty of identification can be compounded where wholly natural materials, what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anderson and Kreamer (1989</xref>, 58) refer to as &#x02018;containing nature's power&#x02019;, are used unaltered by anthropogenic action (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">van Dongen, Fraser, and Insoll 2011</xref>). Further research on the analytical protocols and signatures is needed and the recent funding of relevant research by the Wellcome Trust is an indication that this might start to be achieved.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Medicine and health in African archaeological contexts</title><p>It is possible to criticise both anthropological and historical approaches in their neglect of medicine shrines and especially their associated medicinal substances but this is more profound in sub-Saharan African archaeology. Recurrently, archaeologists have neglected medicine beyond, for example, physical indications of trauma or disease on skeletal remains (see Kankpeyeng, Nkumbaan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>). This reflects general archaeological epistemology whereby palaeopathology, the study of past disease and injuries on skeletal materials, routinely neglects any possible connection with shrines, ritual, or religion (see for example <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Roberts and Manchester 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Mays 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102">Waldron 2001</xref>). This would seem to reflect the background from which such studies are generated, i.e. a Western empirical biomedical/scientific one where such factors might be abstracted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">Singer and Baer 2007</xref>: 114&#x02013;116; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Fabrega 1980</xref>: 40, 89). In many archaeological contexts such a concern might be irrelevant, in others its omission could be central. A more accurate interpretation of past medicinal beliefs/practices/processes, at least in the African archaeological context, needs to embed an awareness of a possible ritual/religious/ shrine dimension as either a direct or indirect, but certainly an implicit part of the healing process.</p><p>As noted, physical indications of trauma or disease on skeletal remains have been the focus of archaeological research in sub-Saharan Africa. In many contexts such a concern is warranted where a link with shrines, if at all relevant, would be impossible to reconstruct. Such is the case at Shum Laka rockshelter (Cameroon) where 18 human skeletons were excavated dated to between c.5000&#x02013;1000 BC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">De Maret 1996</xref>). Numerous palaeopathologies were recorded including dental diseases, unhealed trauma caused by an embedded stone arrowhead on a child of between 5&#x02013;7 years age, joint diseases such as osteoarthritis, and stress indicators (Harris lines) on child skeletal material (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Ribot, Orban, and de Maret 2001</xref>, 181).</p><p>Palaeopathology can and should be embedded, in research terms, in a medicine-based framework, and an example directly related to surgical procedures is skull trepanation. This has been recorded archaeologically in numerous contexts including African ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Lisowski 1967</xref>, 652). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato (1977</xref>, 182) notes that trepanation was more common in East Africa than elsewhere in the continent and was possibly related to the prevalence of clubs &#x02013; smashing &#x02013; as opposed to stabbing and slashing weaponry, with trepanation accordingly employed for healing skull fractures. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Schweinfurth (1874</xref>, 155), for instance, refers to the favourite weapon of the Dinka (Sudan) being a club or stick cut from <italic>Balanites</italic> or <italic>Diospyrus mespiliformis</italic>, and thus their neighbours, the Azande, called them &#x02018;<italic>A-Tagbondo&#x02019;</italic> or &#x02018;stick-people&#x02019;. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Margetts (1967</xref>, 691) does not make such a link but also stresses the commonplace nature of trepanation in East Africa. Tooth alteration, &#x02018;dentistry&#x02019;, for example tooth filing has also been recorded archaeologically, but in most instances this seems to be due to task-related wear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Haour and Pearson 2005</xref>, 431) or for ritual, initiation, or cosmetic, rather than medical purposes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">Mower 1999</xref>, 40&#x02013;42, 45&#x02013;46; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Reichart, Creutz, and Scheifele 2008</xref>, 54).</p><p>In some contexts, rock art can permit a potential insight into past healing and, to a lesser extent, medicinal practices. This is of relevance in two regions in particular, southern Africa and the Sahara. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Lewis-Williams (1981</xref>, 76, 81), for example, describes various healing dances seemingly depicted in rock paintings in South Africa as at Fetcani Glen, Barkly East, and in the Natal Drakensberg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Lewis-Williams 1987</xref>, 167). The healing practices potentially represented, such as the &#x02018;medicine man&#x02019; entering trance and nasal haemorrhaging, are interpreted via analogy with the ethnography of southern San groups such as the !Kung and /Xam (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Marshall 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Katz 1982</xref>). On the very edge of the area considered here at Wadi Mineh in the Eastern Desert of Egypt there appears to be a childbirth scene represented in a rock engraving at site MLM1 (R. Simonis pers. comm. 29 April 2010). This depicts a standing female figure with outstretched arms and legs and with a smaller upside down human emerging from between her legs (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Judd 2009</xref>, 119).</p><p>Death has been a major focus of archaeological research in sub-Saharan Africa (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">De Maret 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Ribot, Orban, and de Maret 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Magnavita 2009</xref>), birth has not. Again, this is due to an absence of archaeological visibility, but beyond, theoretically, neonatal and perhaps mother and infant/neonatal burials, other indications might exist. Recurrent as a practice is placenta burial. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Imperato (1977</xref>, 117) discusses various examples including amongst the Banyoro (Uganda) and Kababish (Sudan). He does not, however, specify the mechanisms for burial, i.e. if a container was used. The Talensi (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Insoll 2011</xref>) bury umbilical cords in pots on the midden close to the family compound. Archaeologically, these pot burials were recorded during the excavation of a midden associated with a relatively recently abandoned compound in the Tamboog section of the Tong Hills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Insoll, MacLean, and Kankpeyeng 2008</xref>, 18). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96">Sterner and David (2009</xref>, 8, 11) also describe placenta burial in upturned pots amongst the Sirak and Sukur of the Mandara Mountains (Cameroon and Nigeria).</p><p>Related directions for future research on medicine and health in African archaeological contexts could include, for instance, the incorporation of relevant genetic studies, thus reflecting the more general trend in palaeopathology identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">Singer and Baer (2007</xref>, 19). For instance, the investigation of genetic anaemia, in particular sickle cell anaemia, which is a disease with high rates of occurrence today amongst populations in West, Central, and Eastern Africa. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Roberts and Manchester (1997</xref>, 171) describe how anaemia precipitates two reactions in the skeleton. First, bone changes occur in the vertebrae, the skull, foot and hand bones, and pelvis, as a result of marrow enlargement and over-activity as the body attempts to produce more red blood cells, and second the death of the bone occurs as the blood vessels are blocked by the abnormal cells. Differentiating sickle cell from other anaemia in the archaeological record is also referred to as only rarely achieved, based on the similarity of cranial changes across anaemia types involved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Roberts and Manchester 1997</xref>, 171), although fossilized sickle cell anaemia cells seem to have been identified in the bone marrow of the skeleton of a young man excavated from a Hellenistic context (c.330&#x02013;150 BC) on Failaka Island off Kuwait in the northern Arabian Gulf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Maat and Baig 1990</xref>, 271).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Map of Africa indicating the countries discussed (Brazil is obviously omitted).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="canm18_145_f3"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s17"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Medicinal substances and shrines can be vital in sustaining physical and mental wellbeing and in creating and defining personhood both dividually and individually. In seeking as far as possible to achieve an interpretive &#x02018;thick text&#x02019; in the African context, medicine, shrines, and their substances must be acknowledged, explored, and analysed from a material perspective, past and present. It needs to be recognised that shrines, substance, and medicine are not peripheral but frequently central to exploring and understanding human ontology, society and belief in Africa, and that this can be addressed by adopting an interdisciplinary perspective such as that employed in this issue. The papers illustrate the diversity of approaches that can be employed in investigating shrines, substances, medicine, and healing in varied regions of sub-Saharan Africa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The contributors adequately contextualise their research so further introduction to the papers in unnecessary here.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The author is grateful to Peter Mitchell for providing references on Southern African images of healing, and Roberta Simonis for doing likewise for the Sahara, but the author is responsible for all inadequacies and inaccuracies in interpretation. The author is also grateful to the Wellcome Trust for providing the funding so that the conference from which most of these papers originated could be held. The author would also like to thank Rachel MacLean for reading a draft of this paper.</p><p>Conflict of interest: none.</p></ack><sec id="s18"><title>Notes on Contributor</title><p>Timothy Insoll is professor of archaeology at the University of Manchester, UK. His current fieldwork is in northern Ghana and previously he has worked in Mali, Bahrain, and western India. His most recent book is the <italic>Oxford Handbook of the Archaeology of Rituals and Religions</italic>, which he edited (2011, Oxford University Press).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allman</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tongnaab</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almquist</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divination and the hunt in Pagibeti ideology</article-title><source>African divination systems</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Martha G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreamer</surname><given-names>Christine M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Wild spirits. Strong medicine</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Centre for African Art</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apentiik</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bulsa technologies and systems of thought</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>University of Calgary</publisher-name><comment>MA diss.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magic and medicine in Dar Masalit</article-title><source>Sudan Notes and Records</source><year>1926</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Arnott</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name></person-group><source>The archaeology of medicine. BAR S1046</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Archaeopress</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>Gillian</given-names></name></person-group><source>Practitioners, practices and patients. New approaches to medical archaeology and anthropology</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxbow Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jacobson-Widding</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Beek</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fertility as a mode of thought: Some Zulu examples</article-title><source>The creative communion</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Uppsala</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Uppsala University Press</publisher-name><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergsma</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tiv &#x02018;Kuraiyol&#x02019; body protectors</article-title><source>Africa</source><year>1973</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diviners as alienists and annunciators among the Batammaliba of Togo</article-title><source>African divination systems</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicines and fetishes in Igala</article-title><source>Africa</source><year>1971</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>Fiona</given-names></name></person-group><source>The anthropology of religion</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd Christensen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bascom</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herskovits</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adaptive functions of Fanti priesthood</article-title><source>Continuity and change in African cultures</source><year>1959, 1968</year><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bravmann</surname><given-names>Rene</given-names></name></person-group><source>Islam and tribal art in West Africa</source><year>1974</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name></person-group><source>Religion and healing in Mandari</source><year>1973</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colleyn</surname><given-names>Jean-Paul</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bamana</source><year>2009</year><comment>Milan: 5 Continents Editions</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Places of power and shrines of the land</article-title><source>Paideuma</source><year>1997</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cory</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name></person-group><source>African figurines</source><year>1956</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Faber and Faber</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Courtright</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Eliade</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shrines</article-title><source>The encyclopedia of religion</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>302</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction</article-title><source>Shrines in Africa</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Calgary</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Calgary Press</publisher-name><fpage>vii</fpage><lpage>xvii</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Maret</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fouilles Archaeologiques dans la Vallee de Haut-Lualaba, Zaire</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>Tervuren</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mus&#x000e9;e Royal de l'Afrique Centrale</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Maret</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pwiti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soper</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shum Laka (Cameroon): Human burials and general perspectives</article-title><source>Aspects of African archaeology</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Harare</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Zimbabwe Publications</publisher-name><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devisch</surname><given-names>Rene</given-names></name></person-group><source>Weaving the threads of life</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chicago University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewal</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beauty and being: Aesthetics and ontology in Yoruba body art</article-title><source>Marks of civilization</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Museum of Cultural History</publisher-name><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewal</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Art or accident: Yoruba body artists and their deity Ogun</article-title><source>Africa's Ogun</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewal</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ogun and mind/body potentiality</article-title><source>Africa's Ogun</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans-Pritchard</surname><given-names>Edward Evan</given-names></name></person-group><source>Witchcraft, oracles, and magic among the Azande</source><year>1976</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabrega</surname><given-names>Horatio</given-names></name></person-group><source>Disease and social behaviour. An interdisciplinary perspective</source><year>1980</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagg</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nok Terracottas</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ethnographica</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fardon</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></person-group><source>Between God, the dead and the wild</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Smithsonian Institution Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Margaret</given-names></name></person-group><source>Religion and medicine of the G&#x000e3; people</source><year>1937</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foucher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Zewde</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pankhurst</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyne</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cult of Muslim saints in Harar: Religious dimension</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference of Ethiopian Studies</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Institute of Ethiopian Studies</publisher-name><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garlake</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excavations at Obalara's land, Ife: An interim report</article-title><source>West African Journal of Archaeology</source><year>1974</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaze</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Art and death in a Senufo village</source><year>1981</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>The social organisation of the Lo Wiili</source><year>1967</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>HMSO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An instance of dental modification on a human skeleton from Niger, West Africa</article-title><source>Oxford Journal of Archaeology</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>33</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>George Way</given-names></name></person-group><source>Native African medicine</source><year>1970</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Frank Cass</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imperato</surname><given-names>Pascal James</given-names></name></person-group><source>African folk medicine</source><year>1977</year><publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>York Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name></person-group><source>Islam, archaeology and history. Gao region (Mali) ca.AD 900&#x02013;1250. BAR S647</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tempus Reparatum</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name></person-group><source>Urbanism, archaeology and trade. Further observations on the Gao region (Mali). BAR S829</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>British Archaeological Reports</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name></person-group><source>The archaeology of Islam in sub-Saharan Africa</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name></person-group><source>Archaeology, ritual, religion</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shrine franchising and the Neolithic in the British Isles: Some observations based upon the Tallensi, Northern Ghana</article-title><source>Cambridge Archaeological Journal</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negotiating the archaeology of destiny. An exploration of interpretive possibilities through Tallensi shrines</article-title><source>Journal of Social Archaeology</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>403</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Talensi animal sacrifice and its archaeological implications</article-title><source>World Archaeology</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance and materiality? The archaeology of Talensi medicine shrines and medicinal practices</article-title><source>Anthropology &#x00026; Medicine</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kankpeyeng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excavations and surveys in the Tongo Hills, Upper East Region, and Birifor, Upper West Region, Ghana. March-April 2008. A preliminary fieldwork report</article-title><source>Nyame Akuma</source><year>2008</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson-Widding</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name></person-group><source>Red-white-black as a mode of thought</source><year>1979</year><publisher-loc>Uppsala</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Uppsala University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson-Widding</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jacobson-Widding</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Beek</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fertility of incest</article-title><source>The Creative Communion</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Uppsala</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Uppsala University Press</publisher-name><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Broadening interpretive perspectives on indigenous healing: The case of Bori spirit possession amongst the Hausa</source><year>2009</year><comment>MA Thesis, University of Manchester</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ngoma. Discourses of healing in central and southern Africa</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name></person-group><source>Rock art of the eastern desert of Egypt. BAR S2008</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Archaeopress</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kankpeyeng</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkumbaan</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous cosmology, art forms and past medicinal practices: Towards an interpretation of ancient Koma Land sites in Northern Ghana</article-title><source>Anthropology &#x00026; Medicine</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></person-group><source>Boiling energy</source><year>1982</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebeuf</surname><given-names>Jean-Paul</given-names></name><name><surname>Masson Detourbet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>La Civilisation du Tchad</source><year>1950</year><publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Payot</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lebeuf</surname><given-names>Jean-Paul</given-names></name><name><surname>Treinen-Claustre</surname><given-names>Fran&#x000e7;oise</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtin</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name></person-group><source>Le Gisement Sao de Mdaga</source><year>1980</year><publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Societe d'Ethnographie</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constructing ritual protection on an expanding settlement frontier: Earth shrines in the Black Volta region</article-title><source>Shrines in Africa</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Calgary</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Calgary Press</publisher-name><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis Wall</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Hausa medicine</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis-Williams</surname><given-names>J. David</given-names></name></person-group><source>Believing and seeing</source><year>1981</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis-Williams</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dream of Eland: An unexplored component of San shamanism and rock art</article-title><source>World Archaeology</source><year>1987</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lienhardt</surname><given-names>Godfrey</given-names></name></person-group><source>Divinity and experience</source><year>1961 (1987)</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisowski</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brothwell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandison</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prehistoric and early historic trepanation</article-title><source>Diseases in antiquity</source><year>1967</year><publisher-loc>Springfield, IL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Charles C. Thomas</publisher-name><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson Fowler</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>Jessie</given-names></name></person-group><source>The shorter Oxford English dictionary</source><year>1973</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maat</surname><given-names>G.J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baig</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microscopy electron scanning of fossilized sickle-cells</article-title><source>International Journal of Anthropology</source><year>1990</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnavita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Magnavita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kot&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P. Breunig</given-names></name><name><surname>Id&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sahelian crossroads: Some aspects on the Iron Age sites of Kissi, Burkina Faso</article-title><source>Crossroads/Carrefour Sahel</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Africa Magna Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margetts</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brothwell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandison</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trepanation of the skull by the medicine-men of primitive cultures, with particular reference to present-day native East African practice</article-title><source>Diseases in antiquity</source><year>1967</year><publisher-loc>Springfield, IL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Charles C. Thomas</publisher-name><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>701</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The medicine dance of the !Kung bushmen</article-title><source>Africa</source><year>1969</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>An ethnoarchaeology of Kusasi shrines, upper east region, Ghana</source><year>1999</year><comment>PhD Thesis, University of Calgary</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shrines and compound abandonment: Ethnoarchaeological observations in northern Ghana</article-title><source>Shrines in Africa</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Calgary</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Calgary Press</publisher-name><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name></person-group><source>The archaeology of human bones</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>Charles Kingsley</given-names></name></person-group><source>A Sudanese kingdom</source><year>1931</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kegan Paul</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendonsa</surname><given-names>Eugene</given-names></name></person-group><source>The politics of divination</source><year>1982</year><publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercader</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Mercader</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foragers of the Congo</article-title><source>Under the canopy. The archaeology of tropical rain forests</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deliberate ante-mortem dental modification and its implications in archaeology, ethnography and anthropology</article-title><source>Papers from the Institute of Archaeology</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nevadomsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The apothecary shop in Benin City</article-title><source>African Arts</source><year>1988</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><fpage>100</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngubane</surname><given-names>Harriet</given-names></name></person-group><source>Body and mind in Zulu medicine</source><year>1977</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nutor</surname><given-names>B.K</given-names></name></person-group><source>An archaeology of indigenous religion at Dzake-Peki, Volta region</source><year>2010</year><comment>MPhil Thesis, University of Ghana, Legon</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogundiran</surname><given-names>Akinwumi</given-names></name></person-group><source>Archaeology and history in &#x000cc;l&#x000e0;r&#x000e8; district (central Yorubaland, Nigeria) 1200&#x02013;1900 AD. BAR S1090</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Archaeopress</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Mungo</given-names></name></person-group><source>Travels in the interior districts of Africa, 1795, 1796, and 1797</source><year>1807</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>W. Bulmer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction. The study of divination past and present</article-title><source>African divination systems</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></person-group><source>Insight and artistry in African divination</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Smithsonian Institution Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name></person-group><source>Africa. The art of a continent</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Royal Academy of Arts</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reichart</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Creutz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental mutilations and associated alveolar bone pathology in African skulls of the anthropological skull collection, Charit&#x000e9;, Berlin</article-title><source>Journal of Oral Pathology and Medicine</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18154578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rekdal</surname><given-names>O.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-cultural healing in east African ethnography</article-title><source>Medical Anthropology Quarterly</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10626276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>Barrie</given-names></name></person-group><source>Magic, divination and witchcraft among the Barotse of northern Rhodesia</source><year>1963</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chatto and Windus</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>Isabelle</given-names></name><name><surname>Orban</surname><given-names>Rosine</given-names></name><name><surname>de Maret</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name></person-group><source>The prehistoric burials of Shum Laka rockshelter</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Tervuren</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mus&#x000e9;e Royal de l'Afrique Centrale</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Charlotte</given-names></name><name><surname>Manchester</surname><given-names>Keith</given-names></name></person-group><source>The archaeology of disease</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Stroud</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sutton</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ameje</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breunig</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New studies on the Nok culture of central Nigeria</article-title><source>Journal of African Archaeology</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saako</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name></person-group><source>An archaeological perspective of the culture history of Birifoh-Sila Yiri, upper west region, Ghana</source><year>2009</year><comment>MPhil thesis, University of Ghana, Legon</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samuelsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infusions of health: The popularity of vaccinations among Bissa in Burkina Faso</article-title><source>Anthropology and Medicine</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Guardians of the land</source><year>1979 (1999)</year><publisher-loc>Gweru</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mambo Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schweinfurth</surname><given-names>Georg</given-names></name></person-group><source>The heart of Africa</source><year>1874</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sampson Low, Marston, Low, and Searle</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyamweru</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dynamics of African sacred groves</article-title><source>African sacred groves</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>James Currey</publisher-name><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R94"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>Merrill</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name></person-group><source>Introducing medical anthropology</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Lanham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Altamira</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R95"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staug&#x000e5;rd</surname><given-names>Frants</given-names></name></person-group><source>Traditional healers</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>Gabarone</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ipelegeng Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R96"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sterner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pots, stones, and potsherds: Shrines in the Mandara mountains (North Cameroon and Northeastern Nigeria)</article-title><source>Shrines in Africa</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Calgary</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Calgary Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fetish market, Lom&#x000e9;, Togo</article-title><source>The Nigerian Field</source><year>1992</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Consulting Ku Jlople: Some histories of oracles in West Africa</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute (N.S.)</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>560</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R99"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Udvardy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jacobson-Widding</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Beek</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kifudu: A female fertility cult among the Giriama</article-title><source>The creative communion</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Uppsala</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Uppsala University Press</publisher-name><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R100"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Binsbergen</surname><given-names>W.M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schoffeleers</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Explorations in the history and sociology of territorial cults in Zambia</article-title><source>Guardians of the land</source><year>1979 (1999)</year><publisher-loc>Gweru</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mambo Press</publisher-name><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Insoll</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The composition and origin of Ghana medicine clays</article-title><source>Anthropology &#x00026; Medicine</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R102"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name></person-group><source>Shadows in the soil. Human bones and archaeology</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Stroud</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Tempus</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R103"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Werbner</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></person-group><source>Regional cults</source><year>1977</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R104"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ife in the history of West African sculpture</source><year>1967</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Thames and Hudson</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>